<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A short reply vnto the last printed books of Henry Barrow and Iohn Greenwood, the chiefe ringleaders of our Donatists in England VVherein is layd open their grosse ignorance, and foule errors: vpon which their whole building is founded. By George Gyfford, minister of Gods holy worde, in Maldon.</title>
            <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1591</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 245 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01735</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11868</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118836</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99854043</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99854043</idno>
            <idno type="VID">19449</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01735)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 19449)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 958:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A short reply vnto the last printed books of Henry Barrow and Iohn Greenwood, the chiefe ringleaders of our Donatists in England VVherein is layd open their grosse ignorance, and foule errors: vpon which their whole building is founded. By George Gyfford, minister of Gods holy worde, in Maldon.</title>
                  <author>Gifford, George, d. 1620.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 98 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Thomas Orwin, for Tobie Cooke: and are to be solde at the Tygers head, in Pauls Churchyard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Imprinted at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1591.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Barrow, henry.  "A plaine refutation of M. G. Giffardes booke", itself a refutation of: Gifford, George.  "A short treatise against the Donatists of England, whome we call Brownists".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Barrow, Henry, 1550?-1593. --  Plaine refutation of M. G. Giffardes booke --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:1"/>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:leaf">❧</g> A ſhort Reply <hi>vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the laſt printed books of</hi> Henry Barrow <hi>and</hi> Iohn <hi>Greenwood,</hi> the chiefe ring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaders of our Donatiſts in England: <hi>VVherein is layd open their groſſe</hi> ignorance, and foule errors: vpon which their whole buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is founded.</p>
            <p>By <hi>George Gyfford,</hi> Miniſter of Gods holy worde, in Maldon.</p>
            <p>Imprinted at London by <hi>Thomas Orwin,</hi> for <hi>Tobie Cooke:</hi> and are to be ſolde at the Tygers head, in Pauls Churchyard. 1591</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here were (good Chriſtian Reader) foure haynous accuſatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s laid againſt the Church of England, for which the accuſers haue condemned her, &amp; all her publique aſſemblies, as moſt wicked Antichriſtian Idolatrons ſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogues of Sathan. I ſhewed how falſely they doo accuſe, and howe preſumptuouſly agaynſt God they doo condemne: And that indeede they are the very ſame with the auncient Donatiſts. They haue replyed and publi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in print their defence, but their bookes are intercepted: yet ſome few haue eſcaped, and are diſperſed among theyr fellowes. Wherefore I hold it needfull to publiſh ſome an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere, not dealing with euery error and abſurditie, (for that would aske the trauaile of ſome yeares) but onely with the chiefe grounds of their Schiſme. In this, I truſt euery ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple man that hath a Chriſtian heart, ſhall ſee the effectuall power of Sathan, when he turneth himſelfe into the likenes of an Angell of light, to ſeduce ignorant men, which are lif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp in their mindes, with opinion of their knowledge: For being men vnlearned (onely ſome little froth excepted, I ſpeake thus becauſe they peruert that little which they haue read in other means writings, in ſundry poynts) yet as if they were ſent from heauen with reuelations, or as great Apoſtles, they take vpon them to confute, and controll, and condemne all Churches, and all the moſt worthy Inſtruments which GOD hath rayſed vp in theſe laſt times. For knowe this (good Reader) that the foure accuſations which they haue brought agaynſt the Church of England, to condemne her,
<pb facs="tcp:19449:3"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> alſo (though with ſome differences) brought againſt all Churches in <hi>Europe,</hi> and that in expreſſe wordes in theſe their laſt bookes. For the preſcript formes of prayers, which all the Reformed Churches doo vſe, they condemne as moſt horrible and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> blaſphemie. The people (they ſay) are prophane multitudes. They ſay, that in all <hi>Europe,</hi> &amp; in all theſe knowen partes of the world there is no miniſter of Chriſt. The gouernment by Elderſhips, they condemne as a moſt proude thing, as being without any warrant of Gods word. Doo but readeouer theſe fewe things which I haue noted out of their booke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and iudge how fit they be for ſuch a work as they haue taken in hand, &amp; whether it be like that GOD hath ſent them, euen as it were <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron,</hi> to conduct his people out of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> from vnder the bondage of <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> for ſo they take it; as appeareth by their owne wordes, ſpeaking of thoſe which cleaue vnto them. Many they ſee by Gods mightie hand (ſay they) eſcaped, and mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching with the banner of the Goſpell diſplayed, before all the inchaunters of <hi>Aegipt,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh</hi> his troupes, <hi>pag.</hi> 5. of the Epiſtle. And if it ſeeme loſt time to ſtand vpon ſuch groſſe things: yet take this profit, as to ſee how needfull it is not to be high minded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and preſumptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bolde in Gods matters, but to feare and tremble with Humilitie.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="prefatory_letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:3"/>
            <head>To Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Greenwood.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>E complaine much of hard dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling offered you, and ſay ye are blaſphemed with odious tearmes. And if ye doo erre, your deſire is to be reduced by a Chriſtian man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. It is certaine when men are cleane aw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye in ſimplicitie, &amp; the matter toucheth but themſelues, they are to be dealt withall without ſeeking their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace: But when they be publike and notorious ſeducers, defacing Christs Ministers, and many poore ſheepe of Christ are in hazard to be ſpoyled. They that take it to be vncharitable dealing, to diſcloſe, and to paynt out ſuch ſeducers in their colours, and to diſgrace them vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly, to the end that the ſimple may not be ſpoyled by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as a praie, doo want ſome iudgement. For as it is Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian charitie in the Shepheards to deale meekely with the ſheepe, ſo is it high treachery and vnfaythfull dealing to Christ and his Church, when the VVoolfe dooth come in ſheepes clothing, not to pluck it off, and to let the ſheepe ſee that he is a VVoolfe. VVhy elſe did our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our call the Phariſies, hypocrites, Serpents and generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Vipers? VVhy ſayd S. <hi>Paule</hi> of the falſe Apoſtles, beware of dogges? Ye haue drawen many into an outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious
<pb facs="tcp:19449:4"/>
preſumption against God and his people, flat con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the rules of his holy word, as ſhall appeare in the diſcourſe. Ye hauerent out of the hearts of many, all reuerence and loue towards the preachers of the Goſpell, and led them into ſuch a preſumptuous opinion of their owne vnderſtanding, that if they become not heretikes, yet experience doth teach, that many of them growe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to irreligious prophanenes. Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Greenwood,</hi> I doo not know your perſons, and I proteſt vnto ye, there is no priuate thing hath moued me to ſeeke your diſgrace, but indeede the care of Chriſts ſheepe. And let it appeare by the things which follow whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I haue done ye any wrong.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:19449:4"/>
            <head>A ſhort Replie vnto the laſt printed <hi>Bookes of Henry Barrow and</hi> Iohn Greenwood, the chiefe <hi>ringleaders of our Donatiſtes</hi> in England.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Did lay to your charge (M Barrow and Maſter Greenwood) a matter very haynous and deteſtable; yea, moſt odious in the ſight of euery good man, as namely intollerable pride, preſumption, and wicked intruſion into Gods office, for that ye vtterly condemne and abandon, all our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, as haynouſty, faulty, and ſo wilfully obſtinate, in ſuch principall tranſgreſſions, as that they haue forfayted the couenant and are ſeparated from the fayth and communion of Chriſt. I ſet downe reaſons from Gods word to conuince yee in this, that if it pleaſed God ye might repent for this ſauage crueltie, by which ye indeuour to rend and teare vp all the Lords tender plants: If not, yet that others might ſee, &amp; tremble at your inordinate and outra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious boldenes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vnto this ye haue replied; ſtifly affirming, and labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to maintayne, that ye haue rightly condemned and caſt foorth our aſſemblies as moſt wicked Antichriſtian Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues. Adding moreouer, that ye lie in priſon as Chriſts poore afflicted ſeruants, the Lords witneſſes agaynſt vs, that your bonds and ſufferings are glorious, and that I as a wicked falſe Prophet, and as a marked ſeruant of Antichriſt, haue</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:19449:5"/>
               <hi>vncharitably, reuiled ye, both for thoſe former wordes, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that I that tearme you Donatiſtes; Schiſmatikes, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ye be Chriſts ſeruants, and haue iuſtly accuſed, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned, and caſt forth, doing no more that Chriſt hath ſent ye for, and authoriſed ye to doo, then haue I vnchriſtianly and as a falſe Prophet indeede, reuiled ye and your glorious ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes. But then take this withall by the way, that the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natiſts in olde time, and the Annabaptiſts of late daies, were Chriſts poore afflicted ſeruants, &amp; Gods witneſſes, &amp; that the Churches and their miniſters did vnchriſtianly reuile them and their glorious ſufferings. For I haue giuen yee none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tearmes then the Churches gaue them: And if in the chiefe poynts of Donatiſme ye be not full Donatiſts, and ſo holde ſundry poyntes of Annabaptiſme, being fallen into their tents and as outragiouſly fighting againſt all Churches, and with the ſame weapons that they did, and with as blinde fury condemning them, as thoſe other, let me be accounted for no better indéede than a lying Prophet.</p>
            <p>Your words are many, and great are your outcries, but let vs ſee how well ye defend and cleare your ſelues by them, from this moſt wicked intruſion into Gods office. I ſet down firſt againſt ye, that he doth wickedly and proudly thruſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe into Gods office, which taketh vpon him to iudge and condemne any one man to be no true Chriſtian, which hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the place and dignitie of a brother in Gods Church and profeſſing the fayth ſoundly, ſtudieth to pleaſe God, for the common errors and frailties vnto which euen the moſt perfect are ſubiect, becauſe the holy ſcriptures ſpeaking of the rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerate, haue theſe ſayings: <hi>We know but in part, <hi>1. Cor. 13.</hi> who vnderſtandeth his errors. <hi>Pſal. 19.</hi> And in many things wee ſinne all. <hi>I am. 3.</hi>
               </hi> Then how much more intollerable is their wicked preſumption and intruſion into Gods office, which take vpon them vtterly to condemne as quite ſeparate from Chriſt all the aſſemblies in a kingdome, which profeſſing the Goſpell, haue many particuler members in them, that ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly indeuour to pleaſe God, and are not ſpotted with any groſſe errors or notorious offences?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:19449:5"/>Then further doe I alleadge, that as a brother hath his place and dignitie in a Chriſtian aſſemblie, ſo our Church of England hath her place and dignitie among all the godly Churches: which for the fayth that ſhee doth together with them publiquely profeſſe, and ſincerely in all the principles and grounds of the holy Chriſtian religion, doe not only allow her the place, but alſo do regarde and loue her, giuing vnto her the dignitie of a ſiſter, yea euen of a mother in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> becauſe ſhee hath not beene barren, but hath brought forth many deare chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren to God, and not a few of them crowned with martyrdome. Ye haue not (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) anſwered one worde vnto al this, but haue with déepe ſilence ſlipt paſt it.</p>
            <p>But ye ſay, <hi>He that is in his conſcience conuinced of errors and doth perſiſt in them, is wilfully obſtinate, and ſo euidently declareth that he hath no faith. And in this caſe yee ſay is the Church of England, it holdeth errors and is conuinced in them, and yet perſiſteth to defend and teach the ſame, and therefore it is quite ſeperated from Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Agaynſt this I ſet downe, that a brother offending, is not to be iudged ſo wilfully obſtinate, as that he is to be caſt forth and condemned to be but as an heathen, becauſe he is conuinced of his ſinne and error by priuate admonitions, and doth perſiſt, but when the admonition and cenſure of the Church is deſpiſed. For our Sauiour ſayth not, If hee will not heare thee count him as an heathen, or if thou take one or two with thee, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e will not heare them: <hi>But if he will not heare the Church, then let him be vnto thee as an heathen. <hi>Math. 18.</hi>
               </hi> This ye haue not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, for ye can ſhew no place in Gods word, where this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is giuen to priuate men, but onely to the Church. And yet perſiſt in this moſt horrible intruſion, forgetting the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, <hi>Judge not that ye be not iudged, <hi>Math 7.</hi> and he that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demneth his brother, condemneth the lawe: and thou condemneſt the law, thou art not an obſeruer of the law, but a Iudge. <hi>Iam. 4. verſ. 11.</hi>
               </hi> And therefore we muſt heare enter into a larger dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe about it. I will firſt ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t downe that which yee bring to mayntayne your doing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>We doubt not (ſay you) neither euer thought, but the beſt</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:19449:6"/>
               <hi>Church, that conſiſteth of mortall men may fall, either of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence or ignorance into grieuous offences and dangerous er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors: yea wee doubt not but that ſome famous Churches and Chriſtians may fall into ſuch errors, as he te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>meth fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall: the holding whereof ſhould vtterly ſubuert the faith. As in the Church of <hi>Corinth, Galatia,</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> there were &amp;c. But this wee holde withall, that no true Church or Chriſtian will maintaine any ſinne or error, when it is euidently ſhewed and conuinced vnto them by the word of God, &amp;c. To your ſecond charge we anſwer, that wee haue learned to put difference, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt error and hereſie. All good men (as is ſayd) doo and may erre, but no good man will defend or perſiſt in his error, when it is ſhewed and conuinced vnto him. Obſtinacie ioyned vnto error after it is duely conuinced, maketh hereſie. Further, we ſay that any error, being obſtinatly holden and taught, after it is duely reprooued and conuinced vnto him maketh an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, and hereſie in that partie, or in that congregation that ſo holdeth and teacheth it, doth ſeparate from the faith and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Chriſt. Wherefore we can but wonder at your ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance who ſtand for a teacher in your Church, and yet hold ſome errors obſtinatly held and taught agaynſt the trueth of GOD, not to be hereſies, or (at the leaſt) not to be fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In theſe words (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) which I doubt not, ye will acknowledge, lieth the whole defence and cléering of your ſelues from that wicked and preſumptuous intruſion into Gods office, which I haue layd to your charge. I am ſure (that in your ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination) ye vtter in them moſt diuine &amp; vndoubted principles, or els how could yee bring in your concluſion of ſuch wonder at mine ignorance, ſtanding for a Teacher in our Church? Then muſt we ſtand and wonder each at other: for I doo indeed great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wonder to ſee how ſtrong the illuſions of Satan be, when he is turned into the likenes of an Angell of light, that ſuch men as you (taking vpon ye, not to ſtand as teachers in ſome particular Churches, but to controule all Churches, and all the learned teachers that haue been ſince the Apoſtles, as if yee were ſent from heauen with ſpeciall knowledge aboue all others) ſhould
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:19449:6"/>
in ſo fewe words bewray ſo much confuſed palpable ignorance, and abſurd errors. In very deede vnder this ſtreame of words lieth one of the chiefe rocks vpon which ye are runne, and againſt which ye cauſe many a ſimple ſoule to daſh with great hazard, leading them into the ſame wicked preſumption agaynſt God, which your ſelues are fallen into. The reader ſhall ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that here is no cléering your ſelues from that foule in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſion into Gods office, vnleſſe the heaping vp of errors may be déemed cléering. I will begin firſt with the difference which (ye ſay) ye haue learned to put betwixt error and hereſie. The onely difference which ye make is the obſtinate perſiſting in it, and teaching it, after it is conuinced vnto him that erreth. Which is nothing els indeede but confuſedly in ſtead of putting diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt error and bereſie, to note the difference betwixt a man that erreth in ſimplicitie, and an hereticke. In deed becauſe S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſayth, <hi>That an hereticke is peruerted and ſinneth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned of himſelfe. <hi>Tit. 3.</hi> And that ſuch cauſe offences and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſions contrary to the wholeſome doctrine which we haue learned. <hi>Rom. 16.</hi>
               </hi> We hold them not hereticks vnleſſe they bee conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, and obſtinatly deſpiſe the iudgement of God, and the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Church, conuincing them by the light of the word, and ſeeke to peruert others and to draw them into their faction. But will it hereupon followe that no error is of it ſelfe an here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie, vnleſſe it light into ſuch a man as obſtinatly will holde and teach it? Or that euery error (euen the leaſt) by obſtinacie of man ioyned with it, becommeth hereſie? Then you ſay thus in effect, euery error is an hereſie, no error is an hereſie. This (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) is your déepe ſkill which ye boaſt of that ye haue learned: for if the man put the difference by his obſtinacie, it muſt needes be ſo. Then let me aſke ye where ye haue learned y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> to deny the vnitie of the Godhead, is not an hereſie, or y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> trini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of perſons in the ſame, or to deny that Chriſt is God, or that he is man, vnleſſe the man that erreth in them be conuinced and found obſtinate? Are not theſe and ſuch like, hereſies in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, although the men that erre in them be not conuin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t hold them ignorantly? Agayne, ſhew vs where ye haue <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rned, that euery error, euen to the leaſt, being in an hereticke becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:19449:7"/>
an hereſie. Thus may the reader ſee how confuſedly ye haue put that to diſtinguiſh errors, which doth but diſtinguiſh betweene the men that doo erre.</p>
            <p>In the next place, where you ſay, that the error muſt be duely conuinced vnto the conſcience of the man that erreth, before he can be ſo wilfully obſtinate, as doth ſeparate him from the faith and from the communion of Chriſt: ye ſpeake ſome trueth, but ye ſpeake ye knowe not what. For it ye could ſee, it is ſo farre from cléering ye, from preſumptuous intruſion into Gods of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, that it vtterly ouerthroweth ye; and your former words and ſomewhat which ye write elſewhere in this booke being laid with it, becommeth a very ſnare for to hold ye. Ye haue accuſed the Church of <hi>England,</hi> condemned, and caſt her foorth for wilful obſtinacie, as quite ſeparated from Chriſt; now let vs ſee how duely ye haue conuinced out whole Church all the aſſemblies, and all the particular members in the ſame, and found them he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks. Firſt remember your owne words in this place; <hi>that ye doubt not, neither euer thought, but that the beſt Church which conſiſteth of mortall men, may fall either of negligence or ignorance, into grieuous offences and dangerous errors, and that ſome famous Churches and Chriſtians may fall into ſuch errors, as I terme fundamentall &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Touching the faults which you charge the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> withall in our worſhip, in our people, in our Miniſtrie and gouernment Eccleſiaſticall, albeit in the whole courſe of your writings your ſpeaches be merueilous exceſſiue, yet in the 180, 181, 182. pages of this your booke agaynſt me, ye plainly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe them to bee ſuch as right excellent Chriſtians haue igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantly erred and dyed in. For ſpeaking of thoſe which ſuffered death for religion in our Church, ye call them godly Martyrs, ſaying; <hi>that ye doubt not of their happie and bleſſed eſtate, all their ſinnes, and theſe falſe offices and miniſtrie which they executed in their ignorance among the reſt, being forgiuen them.</hi> Theſe be your owne words (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) which I haue ſet downe. You acknowledge them to bee godly bleſſed Martyrs, they erred (you ſay) in theſe things, but of ſimplicitie through ignorance. If thoſe principall men were ignorant in
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:19449:7"/>
theſe matters, then is it no meruaile if all the reſt in the land were ignorant in them, which imbraced the Goſpell. Vpon this it followeth, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> was or might bee a true Church, vntill ſuch time as ſhe was duely conuinced of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er errors and found obſtinate. And if ſhe hath not been duely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced, and found in ſuch wilfull obſtinacie, as doth quite ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the faith, and from the communion of Chriſt, then is ſhe ſtill or may bee the true Church hauing (it may bee for ought that you knowe, and there is no likelihood to the contrarie) ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands in her, which are readie to ſhed their bloud for the holy Goſpell of Chriſt. And then how wicked, and how accurſed is your preſumption in condemning her vtterly?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Nay (ſay you) but ſhe is conuinced and all your aſſemblies, and found ſo wilfully obſtinate in maintayning her errors euen againſt her knowledge, that ſhe hath forfaited the couenant, and is ſeparated from the communion of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is your bare accuſation, you may not cary away the matter ſo (for then indeede ye may eaſily cleare your ſelues from wicked intruſion into Gods office) but wee muſt examine (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ye graunt there muſt be a due conuincing) firſt what it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> be duly conuinced, then, when, and by whome ſhe hath been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſuch ſorte, or ſo duly conuinced as ye charge her, and yet found obſtinate. This is the rule, that one brother offending is not to looſe the dignitie and place of a Chriſtian, and to be reputed as an heathen, vntill ſuch time as he bee conuinced by the Church, and found ſo obſtinate that he doth deſpiſe her iudgement and authoritie. This is the onely due conuincing, and here is the onely power to eaſt fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rth as heathen, a man in ſome offence conuinced. And ſhall not a Church haue as great priuiledge as a man? Is it not more then abſurd, to ſay, one man cannot be caſt foorth as an heathen for obſtinacie in ſome offence agaynſt priuate admonitions, but whole Churches may? All the true Churches haue conuinced the Church of Rome, and condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned her as obſtinate, not in ſome light offences, in which true Chriſtians may erre, but as moſt blaſphemous and Idolatrous againſt the principles of fayth and grounds of Religion, tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching that no Chriſtian man ought to ioyne with her. But
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:19449:8"/>
what Churches are they which haue conuinced the Church of England of ſuch errors, and found her ſo obſtinate, that they haue condemned her and willed all men to forſake her? O<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> M. <hi>Barrow,</hi> you ſhall finde that all the godly Churches are ſo farre from this, that contrariwiſe they acknowledge her for a ſiſter. Looke then againe vpon your horrible preſumption, and ſee who hath giuen you ſuch power aboue and agaynſt all Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches? If ye minde obſtinately to perſiſt in your euill without warrant, and euen agaynſt this manifeſt worde of God, (being much better ye ſhould fall downe and bewayle your vngodly wayes, and ſeeke for pardon) ye haue no way to ſhift or to colour your wickednes but this, that men may bee conuinced of error by particular perſons, and that ſo hath the Church of England beene duly conuinced. It is out of all doubt that men which erre may <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e conuinced by any particular perſons whatſoeuer, for it is the power and light of Gods word onely which conuin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth: but that which maketh men to be caſt forth as heathen for obſtinacie when they are conuinced, is not (as I haue ſhewed) obſtinacie agaynſt pryuate admonitions, but the deſpiſing the iudgement and power of the Church when ſhe hath conuinced and reproued. So that your paſſage is here agayne ſtopped, and ye are cut off: but yet I will follow ye in this, yeelding this ſcope, to ſee when or who they be of particular perſons which haue duely conuinced the Church of England and al her aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of ſuch errors. Firſt for the martyrs in our Church, yee haue ſet them vpon the ſhore ſafely landed, out of all danger of wilfull obſtinacie: for <hi>pag.</hi> 181. thus ye write.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe godly martyrs, ſo lately eſcaped out of the ſmoa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kie furnace of the popiſh Church, coulde not ſo clerely diſcerne, and ſodainely enter into the heauenly, and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full order of a true eſtabliſhed Church. And thoſe godly men being ſo vnexpert, and vnexerciſed in his heauenly worke, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer hauing long liued in, ſeen or heard of any orderly commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints, any true eſtabliſhed Church vpon the earth of ſo many hundreth yeares, neuer ſince the generall defection of Antichriſt, no meruaile, (I ſay) if they erred in ſetting vp the frame. But what then ſhould we perſiſt in their errors? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:19449:8"/>
               <hi>ſhould we reiect the true patterne of Chriſts Teſtament, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre be your wordes Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> in which the reader may ſee, that ye haue (as I ſay) landed thoſe godly men out of all daungers, which ſet vp the frame of our Church, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they did (as you ſay) nay they could ſee no better: But our Church now can not be excuſed, becauſe ſhe hath reiected the heauenly patterne being brought. Indéede I am of this minde (to anſwere your wordes as they lye) that right excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent men come ſhort in ſome things about the ordering of Gods Church, and eſpecially at the beginning, becauſe time is a tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher: But thoſe men were not ſo blinde as you make them, or ſo vnexpert in the heauenly worke. Many of them liued long after they came out of popery. They did read the ſcriptures, both for other poynts of doctrine and for the gouernement, and all the auncient hiſtories of the Church, and (in my iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) might haue b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>en able in thoſe dayes, after twenty years ſeparatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> popery, to ſee as much as ſome in theſe dayes that haue béen but foure or fine yeares from the Bowling Alleyes. Agayne, I am of this mind, that when any error in the Church appeareth, it ought (if it can bee brought to paſſe) to be refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med: And that they doo greeuouſly ſinne which reiect the truth agaynſt their knowledge and conſcience to the dammage of Gods people, but there lieth the matter howe you can proue that our Church is conuinced. We muſt ſee who they bee that haue layd this patterne which ye ſpeake of before her, which was not layd before thoſe bleſſed martyrs, and conuinced here let vs come to the matter. In ſome Ceremonies, and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in the manner of gouernment, our Church doth differ from other Churches: Thoſe Churches (indéede) haue ſhewed their rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, why they vſe not ſuch ceremonies and gouernment: but yet they condemne not our Church, for not being perſwaded by them: for they do know that in ſome matters of controuerſie, it falleth out often, that men may thinke they haue truth and be deceiued, alſo that the truth may be ſhewed, and yet men that erre not conuinced in their conſcience vnto whom it is ſhewed. This is your great ignorance (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) which ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:19449:9"/>
that ſo ſoone as a truth is ſhewed in any matter, the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie that erreth is by and by conuinced in his conſcience. There were thouſands in the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem, Act.</hi> 21. which erred groſlie about the retayning the ceremoniall law, and the holy Apoſtles were driuen to beare with them, when they could not perſwade them from it, and that many yeares. And who can conuince errors like the bleſſed Apoſtles? And you muſt conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der here further, that euen thoſe marryrs in our Church whom you ſo fully cleare, had the ſame paterne layd before them then, which our Church hath had layd before her ſince: for they did know that there was another forme of gouernement vſed at <hi>Geneua,</hi> and in ſome other places, and they did not onely reade their writings which ſhewed the reaſons for the ſame, but alſo ſome of them, as Biſhop <hi>Hooper,</hi> and Archdeacon <hi>Philpot,</hi> were trauailers euen to that ende and purpoſe, and liued in ſome &amp; did ſee, if not al, yee ſome number of the reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches beyond the ſeas. Moreouer, the reſt of the martyrs had here among them out of diuers reformed Churches, as <hi>Peter Martyr, Bucer, Fagius, Alaſco,</hi> and others. Howe ignorantly then, and how falſely Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> doo ye affirme that thoſe godly martyrs, had neuer liued in, ſeene, nor heard, of any or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly communion of Saints, any true eſtabliſhed Church? If thoſe martyrs, had the very ſame patterne layd before them which hath béene layd ſince before our Church, and were not conuinced? Peradunture you will ſay, it was nothing ſo fully and ſo clearely brought and layd it before the martyrs as it hath been layd before our Church. Then if I demaund here, who they be that haue more fully and more clearely layd this pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne before our Church, and thus conuinced her; whether your ſelues alone, or partly your ſelues and partly others. I ſuppoſe, yee will take it but in parte vnto your ſelues: let vs then begin with theſe other, and then come to you. The Church of England at the firſt (as you co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe) ſet vp the frame as they were perſwaded in conſcience to be very right and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gréeable to Gods word. Since that there hath riſen controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie at home about ſome Ceremonies and obſeruations, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the gouernement. Reaſons and allegations haue beene
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:19449:9"/>
brought, to ſhew that there be hurtfull things amiſſe in both: and many are perſwaded. But now the viſible Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland, the prince and all thoſe which excerciſe the chiefe power therein haue ſtood and doe ſtand reſolute, that the ceremonies and obſeruations are agreeable to Gods worde, or at the leaſt not contrary, but tollerable; and that gouernement is ſuch as is by Gods word moſt fit and profitable for our Church. They ſtand vpon their reaſons and allegations for this: And many thouſands in the land. both men and women which profeſſe the Goſpel and fayth of Chriſt; either know not what the things in controuerſie, or, if they doe knowe them, yet are perſwaded that our worſhip and gouernment are right. Tell me then M. <hi>Barrow</hi> (ſeeing ye confeſſe the martyrs were not conuinced) how you know for certainetie that all theſe are conuinced in their conſcience (becauſe matters haue béen more fully opened) and ſo continue wilfully obſtinate againſt the knowen truth? Hath God giuen you ſome ſpeciall reuelation, or doe yee knowe the ſecrets of all mens hearts? You ſée by the Church in Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that men may ignorantly remayne ſtill in error, if the bleſſed Apoſtles themſelues ſhould lay downe matter againſt the ſame vnto them. But to conuince you, I may reaſon from your own wordes, for Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> if that be true which you holde, touching gouernment eccleſiaſticall (which is the chiefe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in queſtion) the Church of England cannot bee conuinced by that which either our owne or men of other Churches haue ſet foorth. We haue béene perſwaded that the gouernement ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall ought to be by one of theſe two, that is to ſay, either by Biſhops or by preſbyteries, and you condemne both. The go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement by Biſhops ye tearm Antichriſtian: And of thoſe which ſtand for a gouernement by Preſbyteries thus you write <hi>pag.</hi> 189. of your other booke.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Theſe men would bring in a new adulterate forged go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement in ſhew, or rather in deſpight of Chriſts bleſſed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement, which they in their pride, raſhnes, ignorance and ſenſuallity of their fleſhly hearts, moſt miſerablie innon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ate corrupt and peruert. Alſo in the pag. 166. you terme it a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiliſh forgerie. In this booke agaynſt mee you call it a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:19449:10"/>
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>, yee ſay it hath no ground in the word of God but vtterly ſubuerteth the whole order and communion of the Church, &amp;c. pag. 79.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it ſo Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> then how hath our Church béen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced in conſcience, by thoſe which bring no warrant of Gods word for that which they would ſet vp? being vndoubtedly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded (as I haue ſayd) that one of the two ought to be, (a third as yet not hauing been ſhewed) how haue they (I ſay by your ſpeach) been ſo duely conuinced? And further it may bee ſayd, which is of great force agaynſt ye, that if all the learned men in other Churches, and thoſe in our Church which ſtand for the gouernment by preſbyteries, haue erre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſo grofely as you ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe them, why may not they that maintaine the other gouern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment erre alſo of ignorance? Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> theſe poore ſhifts will not defend ye before God, but that ye haue intruded into his ſeate, vnleſſe you haue ſurer ground that all bee conuinced. For what if ſome ſhould be conuinced in ſome matters, yet whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they proteſt the contrary, who can iudge them but God? And now ſeeing it hath not been done by theſe, therefore it reſteth onely vpon your ſelues, let vs come to ſee what you haue done. It cannot bee but you haue conuinced all, you haue opened ſo many matters. Yea but before your matters came to the ſight and knowledge of the thouſand man, (I might ſay almoſt to the ſight of any) ye had abandoned and condemned all with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any order. What a conuincing is this? And when they be come abroad (I meane your writings) though not vnto the hands of all, nor yet of the greater part, wee muſt vppon your bare word, contrary to our owne knowledge, admit many foule and falſe accuſations, we muſt vpon your warrant allowe many fantaſticall opinions, we muſt condemne all the Churches, and iuſtifie the Donatiſts and Annabaptiſts, or els we cannot he by you conuinced. Your outragious dealing being ſuch, as almoſt hath not been ſeene, (which ſhall appeare by laying open ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what of your bookes) and your groſſe errors with palpable ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance to be wondered at euen of the vnlearned, how ſhall wee thinke that God hath ſent ye as it were great Apoſtles, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uince and to refor me all? You ſay Chriſt hath ſent ye, but in
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:19449:10"/>
very deede Satan in the likenes of an Angell of light hath moſt miſerably ſeduced ye. Ye ſay often that many in our Church haue been and are perſwaded that there be many faults; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or not theſe then ſinne agaynſt their conſcience in as much as they ioyne ſtill with it? Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> it is a foule hereticall opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion to hold that a man may not ioyne with that Church which holdeth and maintaineth ſome faults and errors. Did the holy Apoſtles refuſe to ioyne with the multitude in Ieruſalem, which held the Ceremonies? Doth not S. <hi>Paule</hi> labour in diuers pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to ioyne them together in peace, which in ſome matters held and continued in diuers iudgement? Read the <hi>Rom.</hi> 14. and 15. for this poynt. Thus much might ſuffice to ſhewe your hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible and inexcuſable preſumption, contrary to the rules of Gods word, in condemning as quite ſeparated from Chriſt, the whole Church in the land, all particular aſſemblies, and all ſeuerall per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons both yong and old, men and women in the ſame, whom yet ye haue neuer ſeene, much leſſe admoniſhed and conuinced, but that your words which yet remayne vntouched (I meane of thoſe which I ſet downe) do drawe me further.</p>
            <p>There be three things yet remayning in your former words, in which ye erre foully, whereby all men ſhall ſee, how farre off ye are from making any iuſt defence of your vngodly preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. And your ſelues ſhall knowe (if the Lord open your harts) that it is but a thicke couering of darknes and ignorance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder which ye lye ſhrouded, and (as ye imagine) ſhielded from the ſinne, and from the danger of intruſion into Gods office, when ye condemne as heathen and infidels all our aſſemblies. The firſt of the thrée and the ſecond alſo are in theſe words, when ye ſay; <hi>and hereſie in that man, or in that congregation thatſo holdeth &amp; teacheth it doth ſeparate from the faith. &amp;c.</hi> Thus ye reaſon. If a man be in an error, and be duely conuinced, and found obſtinate, ſo that he obſtinately perſiſt in and teach his er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, euen agaynſt his conſcience, wee may ſafely iudge that man to haue no faith, nor communion with Chriſt. The ſame is to be ſayd of a congregation, and ſo of the whole Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and of all the aſſemblies therein, and of al particular mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the ſame being all in one eſtate, and condition, that is to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:19449:11"/>
ſay, duely conuinced, and found obſtinate. How farre wée may proceed in iudgeing a man voyd of faith, for obſtinacie, we ſhall ſee in the<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> next place<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> here I begin with, and note how blindly and how abſurdly in your conſequence of being conuinced, ye com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a Church and one man together. For a man erring, and his error reproued, either the whole man is conuinced, and is obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, or els the whole man erreth ſtill in iguorance. But it is farre otherwiſe in a viſible Church, becauſe in it, there bee ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry ſorts of members, which may not be all foulded vp together <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> one ſentence. For looke vpon the viſible Church of Iſrael at ſuch time as our Sauiour was borne &amp; liued vpon the earth, and we ſhall ſee there were in it excellent godly ones, as the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Virgin, the Father and mother of <hi>Iohn the Baptiſt, Anna</hi> the Prophetiſſe, olde <hi>Symeon,</hi> and many others. There were heapes of ignorant people called the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of Iſrael: <hi>Math.</hi> 10. And there were the Scribes and Phariſies, which held and taught obſtinately, very wicked errors. It is hereby manifeſt, that ſometime it commeth to paſſe, that in a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church there be which maintaine ſome errors, and it may be ſome of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> conuinced in their conſcience (which yet is known for the moſt part but to God) there be that erre of ignorance and ſimplicitie, and there bee that difallow the errors. Now what warrant is there to wrap vp all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hefe together vnder the ſame condemnation, and to ſay they be all ſeparated from the faith and from the Communion of Chriſt?</p>
            <p>The ſecond error of the thrée is to bee obſerued in this, that you ſay, obſtinacie ioyned with error in a man conuinced thereof in his conſcience, doth ſeparate from the faith, and from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>union of Chriſt. Which, to ſerue your turne agaynſt all our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, muſt ſtand as I haue before ſet it downe. I take it for an vndoubted trueth, that there is no ſound faith in that man which proudly and with a full contempt of God and his trueth doth obſtinatly euen conuinced in his conſcience, hold and teach an error. But yet (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) if you will ſtand to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayne that your ſpeach, you muſt ſhake hands with <hi>Nouatus:</hi> for there be, as of other ſinnes, the remnants yea foule remnants, of obſtinacie and contempt of God and his trueth, in all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>generate
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:19449:11"/>
and ſanctified. Whereupon it commeth to paſſe, that as godly men doo fall into ſundrie knowne ſinnes, and willingly according to the fleſh, yea ſometime into the groſſer, and do con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in them: which cannot be but with ſome wilfull obſtinacie and contempt agaynſt God. As for examples, we haue Samſon that liued in fornication, <hi>Dauid</hi> that did commit adulterie and murther, <hi>Solomon</hi> that fell into Idolatrie. Theſe did knowe they ſinned, and <hi>Nathan</hi> tolde <hi>Dauid, <hi>Thou haſt deſpiſed the Lord, Thou haſt deſpiſed the word of the Lord.</hi>
               </hi> And alſo as it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out in ſome that haue faith, that they fall into foule actions, and the remnants of obſtinacie &amp; wilfull contempt are ſo ſtrong in them, and the worke of grace lyeth in them as it were ſo bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed, that they not onely deſpiſe priuate admonitions, but alſo for a time the iudgement and publike cenſure of the Church. As for example, the man which tooke his mother in law to be his wife, in the Church of <hi>Corinth.</hi> He did knowe euen by the light of nature that it was a foule ſinne. And though the Church neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected to caſt him forth, yet many no doubt did blame him. Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding, he continued ſo obſtinate, that when Saint <hi>Paule</hi> had decreed his excommunication, he was caſt forth. This man in the time of his obſtinacie had faith and was in Chriſt: as it appeareth by his repentance in the ſecond Epiſtle, where Saint <hi>Paule</hi> willeth to receaue him in agayne. Euen ſo it commeth to paſſe in men regenerate, who erring in ſome opinions, which being reproued by the word of God, yet the remnants of obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacie and froward contempt doo make them either vnwilling to ſee any thing agaynſt that which they haue once holden and maintayned, or if they doo ſee, yet they will not yeeld. Now, as it is an hard thing for vs to finde and knowe certainly that a man is conuinced of an error in his conſcience, (eſpecially when it falleth out in lighter matters which are not ſe cleerely diſenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the word) though another man ſee it (as hee thinketh) plainly: ſo alſo is it moſt ungodly and without any warrant of Gods word, to ſay (when one indeed is conuinced and doth not yeeld) this man is ſeparated from the faith and from the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Chriſt. For if great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nants of wilfull obſtinacie, cannot bee in him that hath faith, then hee that wittingly and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:19449:12"/>
willingly (according to the fleſh) falleth into a groſſe ſinne, is by and by ſeparated from the communion of Chriſt. For if ſuch contempt and wilfull rebellion agaynſt God may ſtand one mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, or one yeare with faith, what reaſon is there but that a man regenerate may lye in ſuch ſecuritie ſundrie yeares, vntill the Lord driue him out of it: For God, as a father, doth chaſtiſe his children for their wilfull obſtinacie, contempt, and rebellion, and bringeth them to repentance in his good time. Ye will ſay, if they repent, then ye acknowledge them to be in Chriſt, but while they repent not, how can a man be blamed for ſaying they haue no faith? You muſt knowe (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) that a man is not in Chriſt becauſe he doth repent, but he repenteth becauſe he is in Chriſt. For the beginning and procéeding of repentance is all from Chriſt crucified, and onely vnto thoſe that be in him. <hi>Rom. 6. 1. Pet. 4. 1, 2.</hi> Agayne, doo not you knowe that he which is once hightened and hath imbraced the faith, if he ſinne ſuch a ſinne as doth ſeparate him from the faith, and from the commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Chriſt, he can neuer be reſtored agayne by repentance? Then ſeeing there is no man but ſinneth willingly, and conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nueth with ſome obſtinacie in ſundrie things, how can you main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that euery wilfull obſtinacie in error doth ſeparate from the faith, and from the communion of Chriſt, but that you muſt with <hi>Nouatus,</hi> cut all the regenerate from the hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſeeing all doo tranſgreſſe of knowledge?</p>
            <p>Your third error is in denying the diſtinction of errors fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall and not fundamentall, where ye call it a papiſticall deſtinction, and gather many abſurdities, moſt fooliſhly in very deed, and not ſo much as to be repeated, becauſe they ariſe from your ignorance: for tell me Maſter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Barrow,</hi> Chriſt being the foundation, vpon which all the faithfull as liuing ſtones are built, and grow together into a holy Temple: are there not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, which if a man hold neuer ſo ignorantlie he is not in Chriſt, hee holdeth not the foundation ſo long as hee erreth in them, he is not coupled with the liuing ſtones to make one buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding? And on the contrary, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there not errors which the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full doo erre in, and be in Chriſt? This you cannot denie, (vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe you will maintaine the hereſie of perfection in the regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:19449:12"/>
but you ſay that with wilfull obſtinacie, the leaſt error ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eth a man out of Chriſt. Alas poore man, may not a childe ſee your follie? When ye confeſſe there be errors, that a man may erre and dye in, and yet hold Chriſt the foundation, and ſo be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: is it not as much as to ſay there be errors that are not fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall? If a man be conuinced in them, and hold them ſo obſtinately, that he be thereby ſeparated from Chriſt; It is not any of thoſe errors which haue ſeparated him (which ye confeſſe he may erre in, and yet haue faith) but his wicked obſtinacy and contempt, in holding and teaching them againſt his conſcience. Now therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Greenewod,</hi> l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> all thoſe things together which I haue noted touching your confuſed ignorance, errors, and abſurdities, and ſee whether yee haue brought any thing to cleere your ſelues from the fearefull and odious, yea moſt accurſed preſumption, by which yee take vpon ye to abandon and forſake, as vtterly ſeparated from the faith, and from the Communion of Chriſt, all the aſſemblies of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and all the particular members of the ſame, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a thicke couering of darkenes, which the bright coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance of the great Iudge will pearce through and ſcatter. Ye lye in priſon, not as Chriſts poore afflicted ſeruants, but for this grieuous and outragious ſinne, which no fleſh is able to defend or mitigate, and for ſundry other abuſes, as ſhall appear by your bookes. I ſaide that the fearefull end of one <hi>Boltom,</hi> about twentie yeares paſt, would not be forgotten. You haue heard (as you ſay, pag. 208) that he reuolted and became a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formable member of our Church, and ſo fel into that fearefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate. Seeke better information Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> ſeeing the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample may touch ye, for the trueth is, he did for the ſame cauſes that you doo, vtterly coudemne the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> and was with ſundry other ſeparated from it. And (as it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly affirmed) he was an elder in their ſecret Church, and of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward falling into deepe diſpaire, he could not be recouered, but did hang himſelfe. The mat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er which preſſed him ſo ſore was this, that bee had iudged and condemned men better then himſelfe. Looke yee therefore vnto it in time, and ſeeke repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance before the terror of God breake forth vpon ye, and that it
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:19449:13"/>
be to late, for it is euident vnto all that haue any true light in them, that your offence herein can haue no excuſe or colour: beare not your ſelues vpon other things in your bookes, for it ſhall<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ppeare, that where yee thinke your ſelues moſt deuine, there Satan hath moſt deepely deluded yee, glorie not of any ſufferings<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vnles yee will haue thoſe alſo to glorie which are bound in bedli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>.</p>
            <p>Hauing thus finiſhed about wilfull obſtinacie, we come now to the fower principall accuſations, which ye bring againſt our Church.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The firſt is that we worſhip God after a falſe manner: our worſhip being made of the inuention of man, euen of that man of ſinne, erronious, and impoſed vpon vs.</hi> And here came the booke of common praier into queſtion. I did drawe your accuſation into a Sillogiſme: and you accuſe me to be ſo full of legiet d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> main, that ye had neede to looke to my fingers, for ye ſay I haue left out certaine of your words, as namely theſe (wilfully obſtinate, and impoſed.) Touthing theſe words, wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully obſtinate, looke Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> in the fourth and fift pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of my booke, and ſee whether I did not anſwer them where you haue expreſſely ſet them downe; looke alſo vpon your own booke now printed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and you ſhall finde, that both in the accuſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion you haue omitted theſe words (wilfully abſtinate) and alſo paſſed by mine anſwer vnto them. Now when theſe two, that is, the omitting the words, and paſſing by the anſwer vnto them doo concurre, here is a great ſhew of legier du maine on your part, and yet you would lay it vpon me, that haue not giuen the leaſt ſuſpitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> therof. And for the word impoſed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> you ſay I leaue it out, and put &amp;c. in the place thereof. I doo indeede ſetdowne &amp;c, for theſe words, <hi>erronious and impoſed vpon them,</hi> but doo I leaue them out in handling the matter? Looke in the tenth page, and ſee whether I doo not charge ye with an Annabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall freedome (which ye are not able to auoyde) for this worde impoſed? Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> looke vppon them, learne modeſtie, and bluſh, if not for conſcience, yet that theſe things muſt now lie open to the view of the world.</p>
            <p>And for the booke of common Praier, although the queſtion
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:19449:13"/>
betwéene vs, was not whether there bee faultes in it, but whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e (as you tearme it) a great pregnant Idoll, full of he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies, blaſphemies &amp; a bominations? whether there be any he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſies in it? And whether the beſt part of it be none other but a peece of ſwines fleſh, an abomination to the Lord? Yet you charge me as flying the trial by the word of God: when I ſtand to iuſtifie by the word of God, that in deede there is neither I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dolatrie, hereſie, nor blaſphemie in it, much leſſe that it is full of them, or the beſt part an abhomination. For in mine anſwers and defence, I doo not vndertake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to cleare it of all faults (ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing no occaſion to meddle in that controuerſie) but to ſhew that there are no ſuch faultes, but that both the faithfull people of God haue and mayerre in, &amp; alſo euen chriſtian gouernours and teachers, which are to reforme the church, &amp; that if any doo ſee and be perſwaded that they be corruptions and faultes, yet not of that qualitie or degree, as that they may for the ſame ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parate themſelues from the fellowſhip of thoſe which art o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe minded: this is the thing which I haue taken vpon mee to defend. And if you (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) wil not become a ranke heretick, (as if it pleaſe God you ſhall not) to maintaine this opinion, that we may not ioyne in that worſhip, where wee finde any imperfections and errors holden, and not reformed: why doo you with wonderment crie out, that this ſo large an exception of imperfections, is the odde and onely exception that euer you heard of. And doo you in very deede Maſter <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> thinke that no ſuch exception is to bee made, but that where any error doth appeare in the worſhip, a man is to ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate himſelfe? Nay you will ſay <hi>when it is reproued and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued in, and not reformed, then a man is to forſake that Church as vtterly fallen from the couenant of God. For they be obſtinate and denie reformation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tell me then, what if thoſe that be to reforme, be perſwaded it is no error? What if a great part of the multitude be ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that it is no fault, and ſo bee of diuerſe mindes? Will you deeme that you haue more ſkill to conuince them, then the Apoſtles had? Or will you refuſe to ioyne, as the Apoſtles did ioyne with the Church in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> that held and continued in a groſſe error? Doo you not ſee how by this your doctrine, you
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:19449:14"/>
open the doore as wide vnto all Schiſmaticks, as euer did the Donatiſts or the Annabaptiſts, ſeeing there will euer be er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, and ſome that cannot be made to ſee them? Will you not ſee how you contrarie Saint <hi>Paule</hi> directly, who in whole chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters almoſt (as I haue noted before) dooth labour nothing elſe but to perſwade the Chriſtians that held diuers opinions tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſome things in Gods worſhip, yet to ioyne together? <hi>Rom. 14. and 15.</hi> what a multitude of words, with your accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed reuilings and ſlanders haue you here heaped vp? But I will deale onely with that which is not anſwered alreadie.</p>
            <p>You charged our Church with Romiſh faſts. I charged you with fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e accuſing: becauſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> moſt wickedly againſt the Croſſe of Chriſt, placeth the worſhip of God, and the merite of eternall life in faſting, which doctrine our Church vtterly condemneth. You labour to ſhew faultes in our faſts, what is that now to the purpoſe? And ſo in diuers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther things, is this the queſtion betweene vs?</p>
            <p>You charge vs with idoll feaſtes, as if wee worſhipped Saints and Angels. I told you it is a ſtarke lie, and ſo I muſt affirme, our Church vtterly condemning all that moſt blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous doctrine of popery, touching the meditation of Saints or Angels: here againe you deale but euen as in the former, you muſt not ſtill ſo boldly ſlander, but proue that the dayes are kept in honour of the Saints and Angels. And ſo for the naming of the Churches. I knowe Saint <hi>Luke</hi> did not in any reſpect honour <hi>Mars:</hi> and ſo did not contrarie to that which <hi>Dauid</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſeth, ſaying he would not take the names in his mouth: you may ſee by his example, how <hi>Dauid</hi> is to be vnderſtoode, not of the very naming, but of the naming with ſome honor, for a man may name them either in deteſtation, or as Saint <hi>Luke</hi> dooth onely to make deſtinction.</p>
            <p>Then come tithes and oblations: here in deede Maſter <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row</hi> you bid me looke whether this error be not fundamentall, being obſtinately held, and bring for your reaſon, that they which reuiue any part of the ceremoniall lawe are bound to the whole lawe, and ſo are (as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Galathians</hi>) aboli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed from Chriſt. Truely Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> the more I reade
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:19449:14"/>
of your writings, the more I pittie your blindnes.</p>
            <p>I could not haue beene perſwaded, that you were ſo excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ignorant, taking vpon you to controule all Churches, and farre to excell all the moſt learned deuines: neither could it en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into my thought, that any would ſo boldly abuſe the holy Scriptures, to ſeduce and ſubuert the mindes of ſimple men. I doo here alſo intreate the reader to be atte<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tiue a little<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and to ſee vpon what foundation you doo builde a great part of your dooings. For here to proue the paying of tithes an error funda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentall, and vtterly to ſeparate from Chriſt being obſtinately held: you alleage the words of Saint <hi>Paule, Galath.</hi> 5. I te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie againe vnto euery man which is circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſed, that he is dep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor to keepe the whole lawe: yee are aboliſhed from Chriſt, &amp;c. Let me firſt aſke ye then, were the fathers which were cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed in the time of y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> law, aboliſhed from Chriſt, and fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en from grace? You will ſay no, for circumciſion was a ſeale of the righteouſnes of faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. Then it muſt needes be graun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> doth not ſpeak here of circumciſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the right vſe, for which God did ordeine it, for ſo it was not co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary vnto Chriſt, albeit the retaining of it after Chriſt come, was an error. Alſo let me aſke ye further, doo you thinke that Saint Paule was contrarie to himſelfe, when he circumciſed <hi>Timo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie, Acts 16. ver. 3.</hi> Or after that, when he would with thoſe which had a vow be purified, and offer an oblation according to the lawe? <hi>Act.</hi> 21. 26. will you ſay that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> and <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothie</hi> became deptors to keepe the whole lawe? Or that they were aboliſhed from Chriſt? It is horror to admit any thought that way, or once to make doubt of ſuch a matter<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Neither would <hi>Iames</hi> and the other Apoſtles haue ſuffered or tolerated the Church in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> in that which dooth aboliſh from Chriſt. Whereupon it followeth of neceſſity, that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> here to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> dooth not ſpeake ſimply of the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie of circumciſion: but as it was vrged with the doctrine of the falſe Apoſtles, which was this, that circumciſion was a neceſſary part of Gods worſhip, and that men could not bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnles they were circumciſed: for ſo did the falſe Apoſtles vrge it, as ye may ſee, <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 1. placing righteouſnes and the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:19449:15"/>
merite of eternalllife in it, for againſt that Saint Paule ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth here to the <hi>Galathians,</hi> ſaying, as many as are iuſtified by the lawe, are aboliſhed from Chriſt, &amp; fallenfrom grace. Here is the thing then, that the falſe Apoſtles did ioyne the law and Chriſt together for iuſtification: and Saint <hi>Paule</hi> teſtifieth and denounceth, that he which is circumciſed with ſuch a minde, as to be iuſtified in part thereby, hée is debtor to kéepe the whole law, which is not poſſible for any fleſh, and therefore he ſhall ſtand vnder the curſe. Moreouer he is aboliſhed from Chriſt, and fallen from grace, becauſe the iuſtification by grace, and the iuſtification by the law, are ſo contrarie, that they cannot be ioyned together: he that will holde any thing of the one, muſt forgoe the other. This being the thing which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the <hi>Galathians,</hi> and not the very ceremonies which both he and <hi>Timothie</hi> did ſometime obſerue, nor yet the error of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which was not to place the worſhip of God and righteouſneſſe in them (which the holy Apoſtles would neuer haue borne withall, ſeeing it ouerthroweth the faith of Chriſt) marke well Maſter <hi>Barrowe</hi> (or if you will be wilfull let others marke) how fooliſhly, and yet with what furious ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror, ye thunder out the aboliſhing from Chrſt, for paying tithes, and for the obſeruation of ſome ceremonies, in which, if there be a fault, it is ſo farre from that which the falfe Apoſtles went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to ſeduce the <hi>Galathians</hi> in, that it commeth ſhort of the error of the Church of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> For the Church of <hi>England</hi> (as all men may ſée) dooth condemne fully and abſolutely, not onely that doctrine of the falſe Apoſtles, and of the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> touching iuſtification or merite of words, but alſo tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth the whole law of ceremonies was to ceaſe, now Chriſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing come. Ceaſe therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> this fooliſh rage, and labour not to ſeduce the people, deceiuing, and being decei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, as the bleſſed Apoſtle ſpeaketh. <hi>Ye obſerue dayes and times, months, and yeares</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Galathians) I am afraide of ye, least I haue laboured among ye in vaine. If ye be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed, Christ ſhall profit ye nothing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Church of England (ſay you) obſerueth dayes and times, as Eaſter, Whitſonday, &amp;c. and payethtithes, and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerueth</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:19449:15"/>
               <hi>other ceremonies, therefore Chriſt can profit yee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, ye are aboliſhed from Chriſt, ye are fallen from the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant of grace, in as much as ye obſtinately holde and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue in them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Is it not much to bee lamented, that after ſo many yeares preaching of the Goſpell, much people ſhould lie open to bee fpoyled by ſuch poore ſeely ſtuffe as this, and bee led away by ſuch more then ſottiſh ignorance? Cannot men ſée that the who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e matter lieth in the diuers endes of obſeruation? The falſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtls, the Church in <hi>Ieruſalem, Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi> doo ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the ſelfe ſame things, that is Circumciſion and other ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of the lawe: The falſe Apoſtles are aboliſhed from Chriſt, as they vrge and obſerue them: The Church of Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem is not aboliſhed from Chriſt, but yet erreth groſely, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothie</hi> ſinne not at all thereby. What is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of this difference, but that as ye may ſee, the falſe Apoſtles obſerued and vrged the ceremonies as meritorious for iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and therefore the Epiſtle to the <hi>Galathians</hi> is ſpent in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring the righteouſnes by fayth, and ouerthrowing the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes by the law. The Church in <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> obſerued the ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies not placing righteouſnes in them, but to the end that God had ordayned them, to ſhadow out heauenly things, being ignorant in this that they were ordayned but vnto the time of correction, as the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. And therfore in that Epiſtle to the Hebrues there is no charging or blaming of them, touching the matter of iuſtification, but onely a redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of them from that fore ſayd error in which they did ſtick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> long. When Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſpeaketh of obſeruing the ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, which was but at ſometimes, as occaſion fell out, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſo farre from deeming it a fault, that hee reckoneth it among his vertues: and ſayth, <hi>to thoſe that are vnder the lawe, I became as if I were vnder the law, that I might win thoſe that are vnder the law. <hi>1. Cor. 9.</hi>
               </hi> The Synagogue of Antichriſt in more hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and deteſtable manner then the falſe Apoſtles, againſt the Croſſe of Chriſt, euen againſt the righteouſnes by fayth in his blood, obſerue dayes and times, and a number of ceremonies of their owne inuention, by which they ſeeke remiſſion of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:19449:16"/>
and the merite of eternalllife. Our Church doth renounce and accurſe all ſuch doctrine, neither doe we maintaine any Iuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſme. And touching the paying of tithes, (that I may conclude this poynt) if I ſay there might bee ſomewhat morall in it, though it were annexed to the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uiticall Prieſthood, I doe not ſee how you ſhall be able to diſprooue the ſame.</p>
            <p>In the viſitation of the ſick, there is a forme of abſolution ſet downe. Thus you (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) write agaynſt it: <hi>Let the Reader vnderſtand, that nothing can be more popiſh and blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemousthen it is: wherein a ſacrilegious prieſt taketh vpon him, by the authoritie committed vnto him, to abſolue the ſick from all his ſinnes. Hath any mortall man power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes? Or is it not the office of God alone? Hath the prieſt power to forgiue all ſinnes, ſuch as are not made vnto him? what horrible blaſphemie is this? to him that hath power to forgiue all ſinnes, to him we may make our prayers and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plications, him onely may we worſhip. Hath the greateſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Church any more power to retayne or looſe the ſinne of the leaſt member, then the ſayd member hath to binde or looſe his ſinne? Doth not this rule of our Sauiour Chriſt, as well extend vnto him as vnto the leaſt in the Church, <hi>If thy brother ſinne agaynſt thee, rebuke him, and if hee repent, forgiue him?</hi> Luke. 17. 3. Hath not the Church<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> power to reprooue and caſt out their Paſtor if he deſerue? Is not all this binding and looſing done by the worde of God, and not by any power or excellencie of man? Hath not the word of God the like power and effect againſt ſinne in the mouth of the leaſt of Gods ſeruants, as in the mouth of the greateſt? Let this col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect then (whereby the prieſt in their leiturgie by the power committed to him abſolueth the ſick of all his ſinnes) remaine one witnes (among many other) of their popery, and vntill more come of moſt high blaſphemie.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre be your wordes Maſter <hi>Barrow.</hi> Then this ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution (you ſay) nothing can be more popiſh or blaſphemous, you cry out at it as horrible blaſphemie: And will haue this collect remaine as one witnes of moſt high blaſphemie. If it be ſo, I haue done you great wrong by charging you as falſe
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:19449:16"/>
accuſers: But in very deede while you go about to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>o that nothing can be more popiſh or blaſphemous, yea, that it is horrible and moſt high blaſpe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ie, you bewray ſo darke ignorance and confuſion, as I think wee may tearme deepe &amp; horrible, as ſhal appeare by the reaſons you bring. But now for this abſolution, take this by the way, that I doo not vndertake to diſpute vpon, or to iuſtifie euery circumſtance thereof, as namely the vndiſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reet and vnſkilfull dealing of ſome that may practize it; but onely deale about the ſubſtance of the matter it ſelfe, againſt which your reaſons are brought, to prooue it to be popery and blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>You aſke firſt, <hi>Hath any mortall man power to forgiue ſinnes? or whether it be not Gods office alone?</hi> Why Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> will you denie that mortall men haue power to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue ſinnes? doth not our Sauiour Chriſt ſay vnto his Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, <hi>Whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall forgiue, they are forgiuen, and whoſe ſins ye ſhall retayne, they are retayned? <hi>Ioh. 20. ver. 23.</hi>
               </hi> Dare you contradict the flat teſtimonie of the ſcripture? And for your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion, it is moſt certayne, and the contrary cannot bee held without blaſphemie and ſacriledge, that God onely hath power and authority to forgiue ſinnes, if we reſpect the author of forgiuenes: And men doo but in his name, and from him as miniſters, bring the ſame vnto vs. If wee reſpect the thing i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſelfe, it is peculiar vnto the moſt high God: but the miniſtrie is his hand, by which he reacheth it foorth vnto vs, and therefore they bringing the meſſage and word of reconciliation, are ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with this title, that they forgiue, and retayne ſinnes: yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is but inſtrumentall. It is moſt vndoubted that God alone doth begethis Children by the immortall ſeede of his worde: And yet Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth to the Corinthians, that he was their Father, and that he begat them. All this is but miniſteriall, God is robbed of no honour.</p>
            <p>You demaund, <hi>whether the prieſt hath power to forgiue all ſinnes, ſuch as are not made vnto him?</hi> I anſwere that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Goſpel, is the miniſter of reconciliation, (I meane to bring it) and hath power to forgiue all ſinnes annexed to his miniſtrie, or rather it is the fruite and effect and power of his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:19449:17"/>
miniſtrie, in deliuering the promiſes. You ſeeme to ſpeake of forgiuing of treſpaſſes which are done againſt our ſelues, which declareth alſo your want of ſkill: as namely that you know not what this is, whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall forgiue, they that are forgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. We may make our prayers vnto him, &amp; worſhip him only, that hath power to forgiue all ſinnes. This is true, if we looke to the author of this grace, which is God alone: But not when we looke to thoſe which are but miniſters, and the earthen veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels in which this treaſure is brought.</p>
            <p>You aſke, <hi>whether the greateſt miniſter in the Church, hathanie more power to retayne or looſe the ſinne of the leaſt member, then the ſayd member hath to binde or looſe his ſinnes?</hi> And then you bring certaine reaſons to prooue that he hath not any more power then the leaſt member. Is it not a ſtraunge thing (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) that ſuch geare ſhould come from you? will you take away the whole efficacie and power of the miniſtrie which Chriſt hath ordayned? By the miniſters of the Goſpell (as I ſayd before) God ſendeth the word of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, they be his hand, by which he doth reach it foorth vnto vs: when they preach the glad tidings, or deliuer the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of free pardon vnto all that ſhall beleeue in Chriſt cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and deliuer the ſeales of the doctrine, euen Baptiſme and the holy Supper: God doth accompanie the miniſtration of theſe things, by his ſpirit, &amp; ſo dooth ratifie the ſame. For which cauſe the miniſtrie of the Goſpell is called the miniſtrie of the ſpirit. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. The ſpirit of the Lord giueth vs our freedome by looſing the bonds of our ſinnes, when through faith wee lay hold of the promiſe. And hee that beleeueth not is ſtill bound. Then when Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall forgiue, they are forgiuen, and whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall retaine, they are retained.</hi> This is the ſenſe, that to thoſe whom God doth ſend (publiſhing the Goſpell, and ſetting to the ſeales in thoſe which imbrace it, and ſo bringing free pardon of ſinnes) he doth communicate this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour which belongeth to himſelfe, that they are ſayd to forgiue ſinnes.</p>
            <p>As I ſayd before, he giueth away nothing herein from him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, becauſe it is not giuen vnto them as to the authors of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:19449:17"/>
pardon, but as to the inſtruments and miniſters, by whome hée doth reach it foorth, as by his hand, and by whoſe miniſtrie hee doth ratifie y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> ſame vnto vs. Likewiſe whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> they denounce iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment agaynſt the impenitent, he doth confirme it. What do you tell vs then of that rule of admoniſhing and pardoning? <hi>Luk. 17.</hi> Theſe be things differing. It is alſo very true that the power of binding and looſing is wholly from the word, not depending vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the excellencie of any man: and that the dignitie and power of the word (if wee reſpect it in it ſelfe) is all one, out of whoſe mouth ſo euer. But yet (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) you ſhould know<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that it is Gods ordinance and good pleaſure, to giue a ſpecial o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration and power vnto it by the miniſtrie. Baptiſme doth ſeale vp the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, and hath he not ordayned, that this ſeale ſhalbe ſet to by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtry? I would you ſaw how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>old your ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce hath made you, euen agaynſt Gods ordinance, as to giue no more efficacie vnto the word in the mouth of the mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t excellent miniſter, then in the mouth of any true Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>Your other demaund is to no purpoſe, ſeeing nothing do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th binde or looſe, but onely the word, and the binding or looſing by men, is no more, but when men by authoritie from God, in a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrie which hee dooth ratifie, pronounce remiſſion of ſinnes or iudgement, rightly according to the word, as the word pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth. Shall we then beleeue, that euery true Chriſtian hath the ſame and equall power of binding and looſing that <hi>Paule</hi> or <hi>Peter</hi> had? You ſay ſo, and would prooue it, and not onely haue here ſet downe your blinde reaſons, but in your other booke (which you entitle a briefe diſcouerie of the falſe Church) and in the page 124. <hi>You ſay that by the place <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. wee cannot prooue this power of binding and looſing to bee giuen onely to the Apoſtles, there being many diſciples both men and women in the place when Chriſt gaue it.</hi> This appearing indeed of our Sauiour was the ſame day at night in which hee roſe from the dead, as the Euangeliſts do expreſſely declare. It is plaine alſo by S. <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 33. that there were ſome other with the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles when he appeared vnto them. But yet (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) conſider the place well, and if there be any forehead remayning, it will make you bluſh a little at your owne bolde ſpeach, when
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:19449:18"/>
you ſay that to challenge the power of binding and looſing, as giuen or annexed to the miniſtrie, by theſe words, <hi>whoſe ſinnes ye remit, &amp;c.</hi> is by an old worthles title. For was the Commiſſion of the Apoſtleſhip giuen vnto all that were there, both men and women? Becauſe you ſay; <hi>There were both men and women there beſides the Apoſtles, and that he gaue the power of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and looſing vnto them all alike: and ſayd vnto them all, whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall remit, they are remitted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Marke all his words together. Agayne, <hi>Peace be with ye, as the father hath ſent me, ſo I ſend you. And when he had ſaid this, he breathed vpon them, and ſayd, receaue the holy Ghoſt. Whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall remit, they are remitted, and whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, they are retained.</hi> Did he ſay to all there preſent, yea euen to the women, as the father hath ſent me, ſo I ſend you? I pray ye whether ſent he the women vpon that meſſage vpon which he was ſent by the father? Theſe former words are onely to the Apoſtles vpon whome hee layeth the charge, or the ambaſſage which his father had committed vnto him. As <hi>Paule 2. Cor. 5.</hi> declareth that the Apoſtles were Ambaſſadors from GOD in Chriſts ſtead. If you will ſhame then to ſay that Chriſt layd the charge which the father committed to him vpon the women (as you ſay there were ſome women there, and it is not vnlike) or if you dare not affirme that the women are ſent vpon this ambaſſage to be Apoſtles, which is in theſe former words, as the father ſent me, ſo I ſend you, how dare you ſay the latter words are ſpoken vnto all? For to thoſe onely he ſayth, <hi>receaue the holy Ghoſt: whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall remit, they are remitted.</hi> To whom he had ſayd, <hi>As the father hath ſent me ſo I ſend you.</hi> And tell me Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> is there not ſome part of this power of looſing or remitting ſinnes by the Sacraments? I meane, do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> not the Sacraments effectually ſeale vnto vs the remiſſion of ſinnes? And is that power committed to any but Miniſters? Hath God giuen a power to the Miniſters aboue other to ſet to the ſeales, and no power aboue others in deliuering the word of the couenant which is ſealed? It is no meruaile that you dare goe about to ouerthrowe all the power of the Miniſtrie of the Goſpell (which Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſetteth foorth to be ſo glorious,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:19449:18"/>
2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.) in affirming that the greateſt Miniſter hath no more power to binde the leaſt member, then the ſayd member hath to binde him: when you are thus groſly ignorant, as to affirme that our Sauiour ſpake thoſe words vnto women, <hi>Whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall forgiue. &amp;c. <hi>Ioh. 20.</hi>
               </hi> and ſee not that God hath ratified a power of deliuering the word and Sacraments by a miniſtrie, which hee vſeth as his hand reached foorth vnto vs. They that will further and more fully ſee into this wicked error of yours, muſt looke vpon that which the learned haue written agaynſt the <hi>Swinckfeldians,</hi> about the ſame.</p>
            <p>And now (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) to come to the very poynt indeed that is in controuerſie betweene you and me. I wiſhed that you were as weary of lying and ſlandering, as you ſhould bee in ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king vntill you ſhould finde one blaſphemie or hereſie in all the Collects of the booke: and therefore you haue here gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a whole packe. You tell me firſt, that I haue in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance the Collect wherein the Prieſt by the authoritie commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnto him, doth abſolue the ſick of all his ſinnes. Indeed you tolde vs that this is moſt high blaſphemie, and that nothing can be more popiſh. But learne you Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and remember that God hath giuen a power to the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie of the Goſpell to forgiue ſinnes. The power indeede is but miniſteriall, and ſo the booke it ſelfe declareth, where it ſayth: <hi>He hath giuen power and commandement to his ministers, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare and pronounce to his people being penitent, the abſolution and remiſſion of their ſinnes.</hi> Other power in the miniſter to forgiue ſinnes then this, the booke alloweth none. How the Pope doth challenge this power to himſelfe as head, and how from him it muſt be deriued vnto all Miniſters, how farre alſo he hath exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded it, and how horribly and blaſphemouſly he hath abuſed it, I will not ſtand to ſhewe.</p>
            <p>Then next, you ſay, I muſt not forget the two Collects ſayd ouer our dead brother. The one in which we ſay that God of his mercie hath taken away the ſoule of our brother, &amp;c. This is not ment but where the partie dieth in the profeſſion of the faith and repentance, nor yet abſolutely to pronounce him ſaued, but in a charitable manner of ſpeach to iudge of him as he profeſſed. I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:19449:19"/>
doo not take it the meaning of the booke, that it ſhould be vttered of ſuch as make no profeſſion of the holy faith, (for why then ſhould he be called a brother?) or vpon whome God doth ſhewe his fearefull iudgement, if it be otherwiſe, it may be a fault, but not blaſphemie.</p>
            <p>The other is, that we pray for the ſoule of our brother depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: where we ſay, that wee with this our brother and all other departed in the true faith, may haue our perfect conſummation and bliſſe both in body and ſoule. Prayer for the dead is a groſſe error, but yet not ſimply in it ſelfe an hereſie, or blaſphemie, and our Church dooth vtterly condemne it as a groſſe error. And therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> you do ſtill but belye the booke, which directeth herein to pray onely for our ſelues liuing, and not for the dead. For if the mention of receiuing bliſſe with that brother departed, were to pray for him, then ſhould it be meant that wée would alſo pray for the ſoules of <hi>Abraham, Iſaack</hi> and <hi>Iaakob,</hi> of the Prophets and Apoſtles, becauſe they are included, in theſe words, <hi>with all other departed in the true faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place you are ſo kinde, that as you ſay, to helpe my memorie a little further, you will mee to conſider better of that glorious Anthem which wee ſay at our Communion, <hi>that we with Angels and Archangels and all the companie of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen lawd and magnifie. &amp;c.</hi> Here you will not demaund how wee remaining in the fleſh, can haue ſuch familiar conuerſation with thoſe heauenly Souldiers, that together with them wee can praiſe God. You will not demaund, (that is, you doo in a fine retoricall ſort demaund it) but the finenes of this retoricke will not couer the ſottiſhnes of your ignorance. For albeit men in earth haue not familiar conuerſation with Angels, yet they prayſe God together with them, in as much as both men and Angels do lawd and magnifie him. And therefore the Prophet <hi>Pſal.</hi> 103. calling vppon all things to prayſe the Lord, ioyneth the Angels, ſaying: <hi>Praiſe the Lord ye Angels which are ſtrong in power.</hi> Reade alſo for this, the firſt chapter of the <hi>Reuel verl.</hi> 12, 13, 14. Then you will not preſſe vs with papiſticall ſpecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of making degrees of Angels and Archangels. &amp;c. In ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry deede you cannot but with falſehood preſſe our Church with
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:19449:19"/>
that. But you demaund how many Archangels we reade of and finde in the Scriptures, and whether wee knowe of any more heads of Angels then Chriſt himſelfe?</p>
            <p>We knowe and conſtantly profeſſe that there is but one head of Angels which is Chriſt. And we condemne the popiſh curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie in ſearching into the degrees and orders of Angels, which is not learned out of the holy Scriptures, but from that coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit <hi>Dioniſius Areopagita.</hi> And if that <hi>Michael</hi> the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel which ſtroue with the diuell about the body of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and durſt not giue rayling ſentence were Chriſt: yet S. <hi>Paule</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of an Archangell beſides Chriſt, when he ſayth: <hi>The Lord himſelf ſhal come downe from heauen with the voyce of the Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angell, and with the trumpe of God.</hi> 1. <hi>Theſſ. 4. verſ. 16.</hi> What blaſphemie then (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) is there in the booke, which ſpeaketh but as the Scripture, and you may ſee plainly that, to be a chiefe Angell, or an Archangell, is not to be the head of An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels? The ſainctifying the floud Iordain, and all other waters to the myſticall waſhing away of ſinne, is none other way to be taken, then to ſay that bread and wine are ſainctified to repreſent the body and bloud of Chriſt. All the creatures of God are ſainc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified to our vſe, as the bleſſed Apoſtle ſpeaketh.</p>
            <p>Touching <hi>Michael</hi> and all Angels, we do not worſhip An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, nor yet make Chriſt a creature. You ſay that in the Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, <hi>there is prayer for all that trauaile by ſea or by land, for all that be ſicke, for all ſicke perſons: therefore we pray for Gods enemies, for the breach of all order, and deſtruction both of Church and common wealth.</hi> This is but a vayne collection, when prayer is intended for ſuch as are prayed for, that they may be turned from their euill. Alſo when this word all is vſed, it goeth with this reſtraint, all that belong vnto God, for ſo is Saint <hi>Paule</hi> to be alſo reſtrayued vnto all ſorts of men which belong vnto God, when he willeth to pray for al men. 1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>You demaund where wee learne to pray agaynſt lightning and thunder, tempeſt, plague, famine, battaile, &amp;c. when there is no preſent feare or danger thereof?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then it ſeemeth by your words that wée may intreate the Lord to turne away none of his grieuous and feareful plagues,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:19449:20"/>
but when they be vpon vs? We ſée there are euer anon ſome which are ſtricken with thunder: and when the clap is paſt, it is too late to pray for them. Againe, the praiers of the Church are for all the true members thereof whereſoeuer: and if wee our ſelues bee not in this preſent neede, yet others are, and wée may be, if God turne not a way his diſpleaſure: theſe praiers are not to reſtraine the Lord the vſe of his creatures, or that he ſhould not by them deſtroy his enemies, theſe bee no ſound col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lections. Unles you will argue thus, the Lord afflicteth his Church by perſecutions, by famine and peſtilence, &amp;c. for their good, and for the glory of his owne name: therefore the church ought not to pray to be deliuered from thoſe things. Wée are willed to be alwaies ready for death, and ſuddaine death cannot preuent any one of the faithfull I doo confeſſe. But yet wée e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtéeme it a great comfort &amp; a great bleſſing for ſundry reſpects to be warned before, when wée ſhall depart out of this world, and a thing which we couet, and I ſee no reaſon why we may not, for ſuch reſpects craue it of the Lord. You would make men beleeue that we coniure Chriſt <hi>by his incarnation, by his natiuitie, baptiſme, faſting and temptation, by his agony and bloudy ſweat, by his Croſſe and paſſion, &amp;c.</hi> When we pray to be deliuered by them, hath not our Sauiour dotte theſe things for our deliuerance? And did he not deliuer vs by them? What blaſphemie, hereſie, or coniuration is there then in this praier, as to ſay deliuer vs by thy precious death and paſſion? <hi>You aſke where we learned to pray for our forefathers offences?</hi> I anſwer that wée reade that the Lord will viſit the ſinnes of the Fathers vpon the Children: and therefore we deſire the Lord not to remember the ſinnes of the forefathers, to bring puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. It is a blinde collection whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> any gather herby that we pray for the dead, that their ſinnes may be forgiuen them. Theſe then bée the blaſphemies and hereſies which you Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> doo accuſe the booke of, to ſhew that you did not lye and ſlander: but how well you haue acquit your ſelfe, let all thoſe iudge which haue any ſobrietie. And now touching this that you did affirme the beſt part of the booke to be but as a péece of ſwines fleſh, and abomination to the Lord: you goe about to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:19449:20"/>
your wicked ſpéech by the abuſe, which I told you before could be none anſwer: for the things are holy in themſelues, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though coniurers and Papiſts abuſe them neuer ſo much. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the Lords Praier, we deale about it in the queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of read praier. For the articles of the faith, you wold know <hi>what profe by Scripture we can make for that blaſphemous Article, that Chriſt deſcended into hell?</hi> Alſo in your other booke page 76. theſe be your words: <hi>Their forged patcherie, commonly called the Apoſtles Creede or Symbole, Athanaſius Creede, the Ny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cen Creede.</hi> Let the world iudge what cauſe you haue to glory in your ſufferings: and whether ye be not liker <hi>Rabſaka,</hi> (who boaſted alſo that God ſent him againſt <hi>Ieruſalem</hi>) then any of the holy Martyrs of Chriſt. Is there any Chriſtian eare but will abhorre this beaſtly ſpéech, when you terme the Articles of our faith, a forged patchery? And doo you not I ſay, euen as a very <hi>Rabſaka</hi> moſt wickedly reproach all Churches, both of old and in theſe dayes. <hi>Athanaſius</hi> Créed, which is the Nycen Créed is drawne from the word? It is the ſumme of the moſt glorious faith, concerning the bleſſed Trinitie, and ſome other Articles, which all true Churches and Chriſtians haue euer profeſſed, and doo profeſſe. And for the Apoſtles Créede, if it were not in the time of the Apoſtles, yet was it preſently after, that confeſſion or proſeſſion of the faith, which euery one of yeres made, which was admitted to receaue the holy baptiſme.</p>
            <p>It is euery part drawne expreſſely but of the ſacred writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles. And for that one article of Chriſts deſcending into hell, it is not blaſphemous, nor yet hath in it any error, vnleſſe it be miſunderſtoote. The Papiſts are very groſſe in it, and fabulous, touching his deſcending to fetch out the ſouies of the pacriarches. Others doo hold that our Sauiour in ſoule after his paſſion deſcended into hell, though to no ſuch purpoſe: this is not blaſphemie nor hereſie. The place of Scripture which ſeemeth to warrant that his ſoule deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into hell, is in Pſalme 16. Thou ſhalt not leaue my ſoule in hell, neither ſhalt thou ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corruption. <hi>Scheol</hi> doth ſignifie both hell and the graue, and in this place (ſay they which hold that his ſoule deſcended) it muſt néedes be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:19449:21"/>
taken for hell, becauſe the ſoule goeth not into the graue. Yet becauſe <hi>Nepheſh</hi> may be diuerſely taken, as it is vſed ſundrie times in <hi>Moſes</hi> for the dead bodie, as alſo that it dooth ſignifie the vitall ſpirit, and ſo it is no abſurditie to ſay after a manner of ſpeech, that the life is ſhut vp in the graue ſo long as the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy remaineth there: hereupon ſome doo expounde theſe words, he deſcended into hell, to be no more but thus, hee went downe into the graue. And whereas the order of the articles ſeemeth to ouerthrowe this expoſition, becauſe it is ſaid, he was dead, buried, and deſcended into hell: they expound this clauſe, (he was buried) he was inbaulmed, as it is ſaid when the woman powred the precious oyntment vpon him, that ſhe did it to burie him, <hi>Matth. 26. Nicodemus</hi> brought Mirre and Aloes: this dreſſing of the dead body, ſay they, was of the Iewes called bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall: and the putting into the graue, deſcending into hell. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers doo take it, that deſcending into hell is meant, that he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained in the ſtate of the dead. Others that in his ſoule while he was vpon the Croſſe, he ſuffered the torments of hell, as it is moſt certaine he did. Now Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> ſeeing the words be in the Scripture (thou ſhalt not leaue my ſoule in hell) and the matter reſteth onely vpon the expoſition, what immodeſt and intemporate heat, or rather furiouſe outrage is this, to crie out of a blaſphemous article, and to terme the articles of our faith, our forged patcherie?</p>
            <p>Alſo for ſinging of Pſalmes, I will note here vnto the reader, your foule prophane ſpeeches: in page 180. thus you write. <hi>Heere would not bee forgotten alſo the ſweete Pſalmodicall harmonie of the Vultures, Crowes, Gleads, Owles, Geeſe, of the Leopards, Beares, Wolues, Dogs, Fox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, Swine, Goates, (pardon mee, for thus the holy Ghoſt termeth and likeneth the prophane multitudes aſſembled in the falſe Church) all theſe together with one accord ſimphonie and harmonie, ſing ſome pleaſant Ballad, or elſe vnto Dauids melodious harpe ſome Pſalme in rime (I ſay not rithme now or meeter) well concinnate to the eare (though neuer a whit to the ſence, purpoſe, or true vſe of the Pſalme) before the ſermon, to ſtir vp the ſpirit of their worthy prieſt or preachers: who</hi>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:19449:21"/>
               <hi>being rapt and rauiſhed with this harmony goes to his geere, informe aboue ſaid, where his mouth diſtilles, and his lippes droppe ſuch old parables, ſuch premeditat and well ſtudied and choſen ſentences, as ſhall diſpleaſe no partie, vnles he be of too ſuſpitious a nature.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your owne words Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> which I haue ſet downe, doo ſhew themſelues ſo vngodly and prophane vnto euery Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian minde, yea vnto euery one which hath but a ſparke of hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>uility and modeſty left in hun, that I néede not to ſay much: for albeit our Sauiour called the Scribes and Phari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, which were ſworne enemies vnto the Goſpell, and ſought by their counterfait holines to ſeduce others, generations of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and ſerpents <hi>Herod</hi> that foxe, and Saint <hi>Paule,</hi> called the falſe Apoſtles dogs: yet is it no excuſe or colour, for your prophane impiety, againſt all degrees and ſorts, both of men and women, which are no ſuch enemies, but loue and imbrace the Goſpell, when you giue them the names of thoſe vile beaſts and birds: and eſpecially when as this your moſt vile reproach, reacheth not alone vnto all the aſſemblies in <hi>England,</hi> but alſo vnto all the holy Churches which haue imbraced &amp; profeſſe the glorious Goſpell. For all the Churches haue the Pſalmes in meeter, which they ſing in their publick aſſemblies, and their preſcribed leiturgies, which ye make ſo horrible. Moreouer, y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> people in other Churches, you make to be but prophane multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, as in the aſſemblies of <hi>England,</hi> as we ſhall afterward ſee where you charge maſter <hi>Caluine at Geneua,</hi> that with ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance and raſhnes, and diſorderly procéedings, hée at the firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſh made no ſcruple to receaue all the whole ſtate, euen all the prophane ignorant people, into the boſome of the church, which you terme a confuſe route, &amp;c. A pernicious example vnto all <hi>Europe:</hi> whome then haue you called Wolues, Foxes, Dogs, Owles, &amp;c? Your tongs are your own, who is Lord ouer yee? <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 12. Your ſufferings are for Chriſt, ſo are theirs which lye bound in bedlem. I doo not doubt but that in ſundry places the Pſalmes in M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tremiſſe of the ſtrict ſence, &amp; ſo no doubt do their Pſalmes in any Church, but yet there is nothing in them vnholy, or diſagréeing from the truth. All the knowledge which
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:19449:22"/>
you haue is wholly from the writings, expoſitions, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of thoſe whom you cerine Owles, Vultures, Dogs, Foxes, &amp;c. For take away the tranſlations of the Bible, and what could you haueſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n: And where had you the direction vnto the ſight of thoſe things which you hold in truth, but from the writings of others: Would you make vs beléeue that you had found them out of your ſelues? In déede your vnſound and craſed principles, vpon which you ground are your own, and nothing elſe. And yet as if you had all knowledge in the foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines of the holy Scriptures, and knew a right ſenſe and ſcope in them, which none beſides your ſelues haue attained vnto, you reprehend the Pſalmes as well concinnate to the eare, but no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the ſenſe, and alſo the preachers, as not rightly deu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the word. If you had ſhewed ſome one Pſalme for in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, firſt in laying open the natiue ſenſe (wherein yet for all your great brags, you muſt truſt <hi>Tremellius,</hi> becauſe ſome one word wrong tranſlated may carry the ſenſe another way) and then how the méeter hath wholly ſwarued from the ſame, it had béen ſomewhat. If you haue any true grammer ſenſe of the Pſalmes (for that is it which we eſtéeme as the ground of truth) or of the reſt of the Scriptures, which you haue not from ſuch Owles and Foxes, as Maſter <hi>Tremellious, Beza,</hi> and other tranſlators, we would be glad to know it. But remember what is ſaid of ſome, that they are ſwelling waues of the ſea, foming out their owne ſhame: what greater ſhame and diſcredit can there be then for men to fall into ſuch inſolency and ſwelling, that being groſly ignorant, &amp; hauing no knowledge but through the helpes miniſtred by others, yet take vpon them as if they wereſent from heauen, as the onely men that haue ſée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the true light? This is no exceſſiue ſpéech, ſéeing y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>er<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in many things condemne all Churches and their learnedſt reachers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the reader conſidet of the prophanenes and falſehoode of your other ſpéeches, of the preacher going to his géere and not offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding any, and ſuch like. I doo not know Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> what your former conuerſation hath bée<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>: but by your ſpéeches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> man would iudge that you had ſpent your time<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> rather in the ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cieties of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arding and dicing, then in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Chriſt, here
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:19449:22"/>
therefore I conclude that with ignorance, falſehood and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane impiety, ye accuſe our worſhip to be blaſphemous and Idolatrous. Thus much for the firſt tranſgreſſion, now to the ſecond.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is that the prophane vngodly multitudes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out exception of any one perſon, are with vs receiued into, and retained in the boſome and bodie of our Church.</p>
            <p>In your preamble Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> you doo but babble, and that vpon your owne ſurmiſes, contrarie to my plaine words, and whether againſt your conſcience looke you; for I doo not allow euill miniſters, nor their admitting of open notorious ſinners vnto the table of the Lord. And when I ſaid the Church of <hi>Englang</hi> dooth not allow the ſame, I ſpeake of the eſtabliſhed publick order by the conſent of the whole land, which is both for the godlines of the miniſters, &amp; repelling the notorious of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors from the Sacrament.</p>
            <p>Moreouer, we doo not at any hand allow your arguments, which are drawne from the principles of Donatiſine, as name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that wée muſt ſeparate our ſelues where wée ſée any ſwarue from their duety, and offend.</p>
            <p>The reaſon which you brought to prooue this ſecond tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion (as you ſayd) at once, I reduced into forme of Sylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſme thus: where all are receiued in by baptiſme, and no po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer to caſt forth any by excommunication, there all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane multitudes are without exception of any one perſon re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued into, &amp; retayned in the boſome and bodie of the Church. But in the Church of England all are receiued in by Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, and no power to caſt forth any by excommunication. Therefore in the Church of England all the prophane multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes without the exception of any one perſon, are receiued into and retained in the boſome and bodie of the Church.</p>
            <p>Here you complayne and that grieuonſly, that I did frame this argument after mine owne conceipt, as I might beſt deale withall, and then did proceede to confute you. The falſification which you charge me ſo ſore withall is, that I haue put in a newe <hi>minor</hi> propoſition: as namely the whole bodie of the Church of England, for the particular aſſeblies. It is a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:19449:23"/>
caſe to ſee the witte of ſome man, what great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hee can contriue, if men will giue credit. He that is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> whether it be byſome one aſſemblie which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ower, or by the whole bodie of a Church in a kingdom, is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e not caſt forth? Did not <hi>Eſra</hi> with the Princes and Elders of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> publiſh a Proclamation, that hee that ſhould not come vp to <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> within three dayes, ſhould bee ſeparated from the congregation of the multitude that came out of captiuitie? <hi>Eſra. 10. ver. 8.</hi> this was excommunication. Moreouer, where you ſayd, that the Parſon and his pariſh hath not the power to caſt forth any by excommunication. I did not let this paſſe, but tolde you, that it is not meete that the Parſon and his pariſh ſhould haue this power to excommunicate, vnleſſe it be ſuch a pariſh as hath the conſiſtory of Paſtors and Elders. I gaue you the example of the Church of <hi>Geneua,</hi> where euery ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall flock hath a Paſtor: but yet theſe Paſtors and their flocks haue not the power to excommunicate. Why doo not you then, (if you will anſwere) prooue by the worde of God, that euery particular flock in a kingdome or region, is of neceſſitie for the being of a Church to haue this power whole and ſeuerall by it ſelfe. I take it you ſhall neuer be able to prooue that it ought to be, much leſſe ſhall you be able to prooue them to bee no true Churches, which haue not in euery ſeuerall congregation eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed the power of excommunication. For touching excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, there be Churches which are true Churches of Chriſt, which haue it not, nor iudge it needefull. Maſter <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> in his booke againſt <hi>Eraſtus pag.</hi> 2. ſayth: that he was char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged by ſome, to eſteeme them to be no Churches which wanted excommunication, or ſuch a Preſbyterie: which was vniuſtly layd to his charge, as he ſayth, the perpetuall conuiction of him and thoſe Churches; did ſufficiently witnes. You haue more worke in hand here Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> then you bee wate of: For if you had proued that the Church of England hath no power to excommunicate, yet there remayneth a further thing which is not ſo eaſie as you take it to bee conuinced, namely that it is no true Church of Chriſt which hath no excommunication. All Churches are againſt you in this poynt, and the light of the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:19449:23"/>
truth will be as ſtrong agaynſt you, as it hath beene agaynſt the Annabaptiſts.</p>
            <p>Here you make the chalenge anewe, and ſay: <hi>If I would vouchſafe to take mine aduerſaries with me into the field, and giue them leaue to bring and to vſe their owne weapons.</hi> I anſwere, that for all your outcries, yet there hath been no one weapon taken from ye, nor yet cut ſhorter. That ſpeciall wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon which you now haue drawen and burniſhed, wherein you repoſe your truſt, is this.</p>
            <p>Where all the prophane and vngodly are receiued into, and retayned in the Church as members thereof, there cannot bee ſayd the true eſtabliſhed Church of Chriſt. But in the Church of England all the prophane multitudes &amp; vngodly of the land were receiued into, &amp; are retayned in their Church as mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers thereof. Therefore the Church of England in this eſtate cannot be ſayd the true eſtabliſhed Church of Chriſt.</p>
            <p>You doo here conclude a new queſtion, for there may bee a true Church of Chriſt, and yet not in all things rightly or truly eſtabliſhed. Agayne, there be foure terminie in this your Sylogiſme: becauſe this clauſe <hi>(all the prophane &amp; vngodly)</hi> is taken more largely in the maior, then it is in the minor, or elſe your maior is falſe alſo, &amp; the ſcriptures which you quote falſely applied. It is certain that God did ſeparate his Church from the Heathen Nations that did not call vpon his name. Such were not compelled to enter. But if you looke vpon the Church of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Nation of the Iewes, which had the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, when they fell into Idolatry and horrible impietyes, you ſhall ſee that all the godly Kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> that reformed and reſtored the true worſhip of God, compelled all to the ſame. Doo you reade that the Idolaters or their ſeede, (which ſtill after a ſorte profeſſed the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and had the ſeale of the couenant vpon them) were caſt foorth? You may ſée in the Prophet <hi>Sophonie,</hi> that in the dayes of the godly King <hi>Ioſias,</hi> many of thoſe Idolaters did turne, but feynedly for feare of puniſhment, and ſecretly worſhipped Idoles. The nation of England did profeſſe Ieſus Chriſt, and were all ſealed with the ſeale of the couenant, but yet ouerwhelmed generally in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:19449:24"/>
and many horrible ſinnes: Our Noble Quéene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> placed by God vpon the Regall throne, compelleth them all being her ſubiects, according to their vow in Baptiſme to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce Idolatry, and to imbrace the holy fayth and Religion of Chriſt, appoynting ſharpe penaltyes for ſuch as ſhall obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately perſiſt either in Idolatrie or other horrible ſinnes. Now tell me Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> what doth ſhe herein other then the godly kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> did? She receiueth not in nor compel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth Turkes, Iewes, or heathen, but onely ſuch as are Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians by profeſſion. And therefore you may ſee that if you will haue your maior propoſition agree with the Scriptures, it muſt needes be taken more largely than your minor. And thus you are come forth into the field with your choyce weapon which deceiuethye vtterly. But yet here to make ſome face of true zeale, you reckon vp a number of horrible ſinnes. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede God requireth that al his ſeruants ſhould vtterly abhorre and condemne ſuch vices and ſpeak againſt them, but he allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not any to take occaſion thereby to condemne his Church. Such vices abound, but yet there are many thouſands which cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e charged w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> any one foule vice, whoſe conuerſation in the profeſſion of the true fayth, is &amp; hath been with much more ſobrietie and modeſty then yours, (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) vnleſſe your time paſt haue beene better ſpent then the preſent. And when God ſhall open your eyes, &amp; his terror ſhall be vponye, ye ſhall know that I haue not by the deuill blaſphemed yee, but ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Gods worde, that you haue with horrible preſumption and intruſion into Gods iudgement ſeate, and with moſt ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage crueltie ſought to rend vp and to teare the Lordes tender plants.</p>
            <p>In the next place commeth the Baptizing the Children of prophane men which profeſſe Chriſt, and remaine in the Church. Here Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> you are in a wonderfull diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and can not ſatiſfie your ſelfe with all the varietie of odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous tearmes which you doe euen fome out. The hereſie which I haue vttered about this matter is ſo foule (as you take it) that after many extreame wordes, you ſay you may by the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect warrant of Gods word hold me and mine ordinary moſt
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:19449:24"/>
heynous falſefiers, and corrupters of the whole law and worde of God, moſt blaſphemous and peruitions falſe Prophets. A man would thinke at the reading of theſe words, that the whole Church were on fire, eſpecially if I ſhould repeate but the one halfe of your ſpeeches, but that we know Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> it is but your faſhion: If it pleaſe God he may giue you ſome ſpark of modeſtie. But touching the matter it ſelfe, I did affirme that the children of prophane men which remayn in the Church profeſſing Chriſt, whether they bee cloſe hypoerites or openly wicked in conuerſation, do belong to the couenannt &amp; are to be baptized, ſo that the Church take care for their inſtruction and education in the true fayth. Your cauills here about verball confeſſion (which God alone can iudge) about pariſh aſſemblies (which are members of a Church, though euery one by it ſelfe ſeuerally hath not the full power, and ſo to becalled a Church) about expreſſe contrariety, error and ſacriledge (in my propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition as you ſay) are not worth the mention. Touching the Scriptures which I alleage to prooue that the intereſt in the couenant doth not depend vpon the ſyncere fayth or godlines of the next parents, youcrie out of ſo many errors, miſchines, and blaſphemies, that you doubt not (as you ſay) to pronounce and reiect theſe doctrines of this falſe Prophet moſt blaſphemous and deuiliſh.</p>
            <p>But now if it be true which I ſay and proue, agaynſt whom haue you powred foorth your poyſon? And what bring you to diſproue it; <hi>But that then all the world is within the Church holy, all being ſprong within farre leſſe then a thouſand gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations of many faithfull, and lineally come from the Patriarch <hi>Noah?</hi> And that then ought the Iſraelites vnder the lawe to haue circumciſed all their captiue Cananites and heathen that came into their power. Then ought the Church now to bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize al the ſeed euen of the moſt wicked and vngodly, whether Turkes, Papiſts, Idolaters, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You are out of the way Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> and the faſter you runne, the further: for you ſhould remember that I ſpake of the ſeede of ſuch prophane men as remayne in the Church and profeſſe Chriſt, and are ſealed with the ſeale of the Couenant.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:19449:25"/>
Will you make no difference betweene thoſe which were or are without the Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ncircumciſed, or vnbaptized, not profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> or the faith of Chriſt, and thoſe which were or be in the Church, circumciſed or baptized, profeſſing the the God of <hi>Abraham</hi> and the faith of Chriſt? The Cananites and other heathen, if they forſooke falſe Gods, and imbraced the religion of the true God, were circumciſed: &amp; ſo may the Turks and heathen be baptized at this day. But while they are with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out and blaſpheme and renounce Chriſt, what hath the Church to do with their children, which are not vnder her gouernment and power to bring vp? The Church is to take care that al thoſe children may bee inſtructed in the faith, and guided in the way of godlines, which ſhe admitteth vnto baptiſme. For the places of Scripture, where I ſayd that the couenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> was made thus, I will bee thy God, and the God of thy ſeede, and that to a thouſand generations, <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. And that becauſe of this S. <hi>Peter</hi> calleth all the Iewes in generall, <hi>the children of the Prophets and of the couenant. <hi>Act. 3. 25.</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>Paule, Rom.</hi> 9. 4 For which reſpect they are called holy, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. And the childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Idolaters among them are called Gods children, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 16. The whole nation of the Iewes, a very fewe men excepted, did at ſundrie times very grieuouſly ſinne agaynſt the Lord, and the greater part of thoſe neuer returned by true repentance, but yet remayned in the profeſſion of the God of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and were circumciſed. If the couenant had been diſanulled to their ſeede, how could Saint <hi>Peter</hi> ſay, they were the children of the Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant? Or how could Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſay, that theirs was the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doption and the Couenant? If none were outwardly to ſtand vnder the Couenant but the elect, how ſhould this haue been ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken? Or if the Couenant had been diſanulled by their fathers ſinnes? Unto this (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) you haue made none an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer at all. But you take occaſion at that which I alleage out of <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. to make ſome colour or ſhewe of matter, and ſay that I wittingly ſuppreſſe the next words of the ſentence, which are theſe; <hi>of them that loue me and keepe my commandements,</hi> which ſhew to whom this couenant is made and belongeth, and the condition on our part. And you require that I ſhould <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:19449:25"/>
one plate through the whole Scripture, where the Lords Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant is made vnto vs without this condition, and then you ſay I may peraduenture cléere my ſelfe, and mine ordinarie for publiſhing this wicked and diuelliſh hereſie, ſo directly contrary to the whole Scriptures in more then a thouſand places. Thus it is your pleaſure (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) euen in your deepe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and that in the grounds of Religion, to impugne the ſtablenes of Gods couenant made vnto his people. It is a thing indeed which any godly mind may with horror tremble at, when with ſuch furie you terme it a diuelliſh hereſie, which is indeed that doctrine of grace deliuered in the Scriptures, whereby the glorie of the Lord is moſt highly magnified. It is certayne that the Couenant or promiſe of God dooth not profite any, vnleſſe they receiue it, as the holy Ghoſt ſpeaketh, <hi>mixed with faith. <hi>Heb. 4. 2.</hi>
               </hi> Then where true faith is, there is ſanctification, there is obedience according to the meaſure of that faith greater or leſſe.</p>
            <p>Hereupon it followeth, that as God is become their God, ſo they are become his people, and this is required on our part. But now to inferre vpon this, that the ſtablenes of Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant dependeth vpon this condition, if we keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and that a man, yea a whole Church doth forfeit the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant (as your phraſe is) if they ſhewe rebellion, is moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked. For what is more manifeſt then this, that if it had been ſo, the couenant had been forfeited almoſt vnto all Iſrael, and that very often, for they oftentimes rebelled agaynſt God moſt grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uouſly, and brake promiſe on their part. The complaints of the Prophets are many: ſundrie Pſalmes doo ſet it forth: the booke of the Iudges declareth how oft they rebelled and fel vnto foule Idolatrie, and how oft he plagued them, and humbled them by deliuering them into the hands of heathen Kings. You will ſay they rebelled, but repented. And in the dayes of euery godly Iudge, and godly King were the viſible Church. But in the times of their defection when they committed Idolatrie, you ſay they were not the viſible Church. Yea you alleage teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture, to prooue that in their defection they were not the Lords people: as <hi>Deuteronom. 32. 19. Micha. 2. 7, 8, 9,</hi>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:19449:26"/>
               <hi>Amos. 8. 2. Ezech. 16.</hi> Alas Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> would any man looke for ſuch matter at their hands that had but euen read ouer the Byble? It is declared by <hi>Moſes,</hi> that God choſe them to be his people not for their owne righteouſnes, but of free mercie, and made his couenant with them. Likewiſe it is moſt certayne that hee continued his faith towards them, not for that they kept couenant with him, (for they often rebelled) but for his own names ſake.</p>
            <p>To ſay that they forfeited the Couenant by tranſgreſſing his commandements, and recouered it agayne by repentance, and ſo to be now out now in, is (that I may ſay no worſe) moſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhly ſpoken. For they did not enter agayne into a couenant which was loſt becauſe they repented, but contrariwiſe they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented becauſe they were in the couenant. That is, becauſe he had ſworne vnto them to bee their God, hee not onely brought them downe by afflictions, chaſtiſing them as a father, but gaue them the graces of repentance. This is ſhewed Pſalm. 106. where the Prophet hauing ſet foorth their manifold rebellions, and the plagues wherewith he plagued them, he ſayth: <hi>When they were brought downe by affliction, he looked to their distreſſe and heard their cry. And remembred for them his couenant: and repented for the multitude of his mercies.</hi> The Lord ſayth alſo, <hi>He foreknewe them to be an hard people: that their necke was as a barre of yron, and their forehead of braſſe, and that they would deale vnfaithfully. <hi>Eſay. 48. verſ. 4. 8.</hi>
               </hi> Yet he ſayth, <hi>I will be long ſuffering for my names ſake, and for my praiſe, I will refraine mine anger towards thee, that I may not cut thee off. <hi>verſ. 9.</hi>
               </hi> It were too long to repeate all the Scriptures where the Lord pronounceth that he choſe them for his owne names ſake, that they dealt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faithfully, and yet he kept them as his people, and forgaue their iniquities euen for himſelfe. You will ſay, that Gods couenant was to the elect among them, but the reſt were not vnder the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenant, nor the viſible Church. This is your grieuous blind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, that you cannot ſee that many ſtand outwardly vnder the couenant, and are the viſible Church, which yet receiue no bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite thereby, being wicked euen voyd of faith. And for this cauſe although the great ſwarme of the Iſraelites were wicked repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:19449:26"/>
and (as the Prophet ſayth) but a remnant ſaued, yet for their outward profeſſion the whole Nation was euer ſayd to ſtand vnder the couenant. Otherwiſe how could it be ſayd, <hi>That Chriſt came among his owne, and his owne receiued him not? <hi>Ioh. 1.</hi>
               </hi> How could theſe wicked infidels be called his owne, in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other reſpect, but that they ſtood outwardly vnder the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and were the viſible Church? And therefore when the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of that people ſhould ſtand no longer vnder the couenant, to be the viſible Church, but (as our Sauiour ſayth) <hi>the kingdome of God ſhould be taken from them. <hi>Math. 21.</hi>
               </hi> The Lord (to ſhew that he had ſtill kept his couenant with them, euen vntill that time in which they now breake off themſelues, and that hee had giuen their mother no bill of diuorſe) aſketh, <hi>where the bill of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uorſe of their mother is, by which he had put her away? <hi>Eſay. 50. verſ. 1.</hi>
               </hi> The tenne Tribes which fell from the houſe of <hi>Dauid,</hi> and worſhipped Idols, were yet in ſome ſort euen the whole bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die of them vnder the Couenant, and were ſo farre the viſible Church: for otherwiſe how ſhould the Lord bee called their God? For when <hi>Benhadab</hi> made warre agaynſt <hi>Achab,</hi> and tooke the foyle, and his ſeruants counſelled him to enterpriſe the warre agayne, and to fight with them in the valleyes, ſaying: <hi>That the God of Iſrael was the God of the mountaines, the Lord tooke it agaynſt himſelfe, and gaue them the ouerthrow the ſecond time.</hi> 1. <hi>King. 20. Achazias</hi> K. of Iſrael being ſicke vpon a fall he had taken, ſent his meſſengers to enquire of <hi>Baalzebub</hi> the God of <hi>Ekron. Elias</hi> the Prophet is ſent to meete them, and to ſay, <hi>Is it not becauſe there is no God in Iſrael, that you goe to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire of Baalzebub, the God of Ekron?</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Now, for the places which you alleage that they became not his people, you doo but peruert them. For the ſong <hi>Deuteron. 32. verſ. 5.</hi> If you will vnderſtand it ſo as you here apply it, how ſhould they after bee called his people and his ſeruants in the ſame ſong? <hi>verſ.</hi> 36. The breuitie and the placing of the words in that ſentence doo make it darke. This is the ſenſe, <hi>That the peruerſe generation corrupt themſelues by their owne vice, which is not of his children.</hi> For the holines of Gods children is from him; but when they tranſgreſſe and corrupt themſelues, it is
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:19449:27"/>
from their owne vice. And hee calleth all the whole people his ſonnes and daughters, not in reſpect of ſome former eſtate, (as you vainly imagine; ſeeing that very fewe of them were his ſonnes and daughters indeede in their beſt eſtate) but in reſpect that they ſtood outwardly vnder his couenant, and profeſſed his name. And that the Lord ſayth, <hi>Yeſterday which was my people, is riſen as an enemie. <hi>Mich. 2. verſ. 8.</hi>
               </hi> is not to ſhewe that they were now quite remooued and caſt off by the Lord from being vnder his couenant, though the multitude were the Church but in name; but their hoſtilitie among themſelues, both in <hi>Iuda</hi> and <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The ende which God ſayd was come to his people <hi>Amos.</hi> 8. is meant of their ſubuerſion and captiuitie. Will you ſay that they were neuer after nor no longer Gods people? If you dare not ſay this, why doo you alleage that place? You would haue me ſhewe ſome place in the Scriptures where God maketh his couenaut without this condition, that they ſhall bee his people and obey him.</p>
            <p>That is not the queſtion Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> but this, whether, when men breake couenant and promiſe with God by diſobey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him, whoſe couenant yet they chalenge, his couenant be bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and abrogated towards them? And for this I ſhewed you the plaine Scripture, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 89. where the Lord ſaith: <hi>If they ſhould for ſake his law, he would viſite their offences or defections with the rod<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but he will not diſanull his mercie towards them, nor falſifie his fayth. That he will not prophane his couenaunt, nor alter the thing which is gone out of his lippes.</hi> Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> what can be more expreſſe then this, to ſhew the ſtablenes of Gods souenant dependeth not vpon our obedience, or vpon that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition which you ſpeake of, and ſay the couenant ſtandeth no longer then they ſtand obedient? Why did you not anſwere this place, but require ſtill to haue that ſhewed which is playnly ſhewed you before? <hi>Solomon</hi> on his part brake couenant with God, will you ſay he did forfeyte the couenant? I conclude ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore with the ſaying of Saynt <hi>Paul,</hi> where hee ſpeaketh of the Iewes what preferment they had aboue other. <hi>What if ſome of them were vnfaythfull, ſhall their vnbeliefe make the fayth of God of none effect? God for bid. Yea let God be true, and euery man a ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er.</hi>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:19449:27"/>
               <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. Ceaſe therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> to hang the ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blenes of Gods couenant vpon the obedience of man, and do not ſo peruerſly reaſon againſt the truth in affirming that the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of God was diſanulled toward the Iewes, not to ſtand as the viſible Church, before ſuch time as they had reiected Chriſt.</p>
            <p>The next thing is that I ſay eyther wee are within the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant from our Auceſtors, and haue the ſeale thereof, euen Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme, or elſe your ſelues are without Baptiſme, and ſo muſt ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Catabaptiſts rebaptize, or elſe holde the couenant without a ſeale. Neyther of theſe you will doo, and yet ſtand in it that we haue no true Church nor true Sacraments. This therefore is your anſwere.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Iſraelites in their Schiſme, and the Iewes in their A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaſie, ſtill had and vſed Circumciſion. This Circumciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was no true Sacrament vnto them, neither ſealed the Lords couenant vnto them in that eſtate. Yet was this circumciſion true Circumciſion, concerning the outward cutting; and was vpon their repentance and returne, neither defaced nor reite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, but they were reſtored to the Temple, and receiued to the paſouer. In like manner in this generall Apoſtaſie and defe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction from the Goſpell, the Baptiſme continued in theſe A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtaticall and falſe Churches, cannot in this eſtate thus admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred, be ſayd a true Sacrament or ſeale of Gods couenant vnto them. Yet concerning the outward waſhing, it is true Baptiſme, the outward action neede not, and ought not to bee againe repeated, after the abuſe thereof in the falſe Church is purged away by true repentance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre be your wordes Maſter <hi>Barrow.</hi> Alas poore crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, how much is your ſiely blindnes to bee pitied, that can ſet down things ſo directly contrary at the ſame inſtant, &amp; yet eſpie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it not? for you ſay that Circumciſion in their Apoſtaſie was no true Sacrament vnto them, neither ſealed the Lordes coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant vnto them in that eſtate. And yet (you ſay) it was true Circumciſion concerning the outward cutting. Likewiſe you ſay that Baptiſme in the poperie cannot bee ſaide a true Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment or ſeale of Gods couenant vnto them. And yet concerning
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:19449:28"/>
the outward waſhing ye confeſſe it true Baptiſme. Is not this all one, as if a man ſhould ſay, it is the true ſacrament and ſeale of Gods couenant; it is no true Sacrament nor ſeale of Gods couenant? I pray you M. <hi>Barrow,</hi> is not the outward waſhing the whole Baptiſme, and the whole ſeale of Gods couenant? Was not the outward cutting the whole circumciſion, and the whole ſeale of Gods couenant? And if the outward waſhing be the whole Sacrament, and the whole ſeale of Gods couenant, as indeede with the word it is: (for the inward grace is no part of the Sacrament, but we may ſay that this inward grace is the thing repreſented and ſealed by the Sacrament) Then when you ſay, concerning the outward waſhing it is true Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme: doo you not affirme the whole Sacrament and ſo the whole ſeale of Gods couenant to be true? But you ſay, <hi>it is no true ſeale vnto them in their Apoſtaſie, or it doth not ſeale Gods Couenant vnto them in that eſtate, but when the abuſe thereof is purged away by true repentance.</hi> What abſurde ſpeeches be theſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> can a man deuife more groſſe folly? the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward true Sacrament, is the true ſeale of Gods couenant, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen vnto thoſe which be hypocrites, and vtterly voyde of fayth, which haue it. For if we ſhall ſay it is no true Sacrament, or no ſeale of Gods couenant, or that it doth not ſeale Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, but vnto thoſe which haue the inward grace, the efficacie and fruite thereof: then was it ſometimes no true Sacrament which the Apoſtles themſelues did adminiſter, becauſe there were ſome vnto whome they did adminiſter both the holy Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme and the Lords Supper, which had not the inward grace. And if the Sacraments be not the true ſeales of Gods Coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, euen vnto thoſe which haue no fruite thereby; how ſhould the receiuers which are vtterly vnworthie, be guiltie of the body and blood of our Lord? Alſo when a man doth receiue Baptiſme which is alwayes the ſeale of Gods couenant, and is voyde of fayth, and receiueth it at their handes which doo mixe it with ſundry additions and corruptions, and after commeth vnto true faith, he himſelfe is purged by his fayth, and hath the vſe of that ſeale which hee had before, but without fruite, we cannot ſay as you doo, but with moſt wicked and foule abſurditie, that the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:19449:28"/>
it ſelfe was a falſe Sacrament, and now through ſayth is purged and became a true Sacrament. That which is the Lordes doth ſtand in it ſelfe pure and vnde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iled, euen when cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions bee added. The Wheat in it ſelf is as pure lying among the Chaffe, as when it is purged from the Chaffe. The golde and ſiluer in themſelues be as pure when the ruſt is vpon them, as when it is ſcowred off. If a thing in the mixture of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue not a true being, ye cannot by purging bring it to haue a true being. And when you ſay that concerning the outward waſhing it is true Baptiſme miniſtred in popery, which is as much as I haue ſhewed, as to ſay it is a true ſacrament concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the whole (becauſe the outward waſhing is the whole, and therefore all that <hi>Iohn</hi> the Baptiſt taketh to himſelfe is this, I baptize ye with water). Doo you not acknowledge a mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie in popery? Will you ſay it is concerning the outward waſhing true Baptiſme, by whomeſoeuer it bee done? Nay, you ſay where there is no true miniſtrie there is no true Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament. Then where there is no part of a true miniſtrie, there is no part of a true Sacrament.</p>
            <p>In your other booke Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> which you tearme a briefe diſcouerie of the falſe Church, from the 102. page, vnto 121. you make a large diſcourſe about this point, taking vppon you to bee a ſtickeler, betwéene Maſter Doctor <hi>Some,</hi> and the Scholler of <hi>Oxenford,</hi> writing againſt him in defence of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Penrie.</hi> There you lay about you with your woodknife vpon both parties. Maſter Doctor <hi>Some</hi> holding the Baptiſme ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred in the popery to be true Baptiſme, alleaging that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Caluine</hi> held ſo, as in déede all the Churches, and all the moſt excellent and worthy lights, which God hath raiſed vp in theſe laſt times doo hold the ſame with ſound reaſons from the Scripture, you ſcoffingly <hi>tearme him a great Clarke, and ſay, that in certaine marginal notes added to his booke, this incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenience was moued vnto his further conſideration, how hee would auoyde the blowe of flat Schiſme? Alſo you ſay he was friendly aduiſed to ſpare this deepe diuinitie, deriued from Maſter Caluine and others of this time, leaft h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſhould open ſuch a gappe to the Papiſtes, as neither the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:19449:29"/>
               <hi>nor Geneua, nor any other that hold this opinion ſhall e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be able to ſhut, for if it be true Baptiſme deliuered in the Church of Rome, then will it follow that the Popiſh prieſts be true miniſters. And then may the ſeale of the couenant be giuen to open Idolaters, then dooth Gods couenant of peace belong to the babiloniſh harlot, then hath Chriſt many bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies, or elſe cannot three ſo diuers Churches, as the Church of Rome, the Church of England, the Church of Geneua, all or any two of them (I will not ſay any one) bee true Churches. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he may be an husband where his wiues rule. Infinit other abſurdities would then proue lawful. And let me adde yet this vnto the reſt: if the Baptiſme of the Church of Rome be a true Sacrament, then haue they one true Sacrament, and another falſe.</hi> Thus you wound the one party, that is Maſter Doctor <hi>Some.</hi> Then touching the Scholler of <hi>Oxenford,</hi> hée is bla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med for that he alleageth for his patron Maſter Doctor <hi>Fulke,</hi> to proue that the Baptiſme adminiſtred in popery, is no true Baptiſme. And he is ſet to counteruaile Maſter <hi>Caluin,</hi> as his equall in all learning. Grieuous abſurdities you ſhew in déede, which muſt néeds follow from the opinion of the foreſaid Schol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler. Touching the compariſon betwéene Maſter Fulke and Maſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> for my part I am not ſo learned, as that I can bring a full meaſure to meaſure them iuſtly withall. I know not what might ſlip from Doctor <hi>Fulke,</hi> in any part of his wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, vpon ſome occaſion which may ſéeme as though he fauo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that opinio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: but this I know, that ſundry times crauing his iudgement in that matter, he held it to be true Baptiſme which hath béen adminiſtred in the popery. And what a thing is this Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> that when you haue a long time taken on, you yéeld the whole matter vnto Maſter Doctor <hi>Some.</hi> For what hath he ſaid more, then that it was and is true Baptiſme tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the outward waſhing? Doth he euer ſay that all which had the true ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ale, had alſo the inward grace? And for warding the blow of flat ſchiſme: it is a very weake blow. The Romiſh Antichriſt vſurped an vniuſt power and tyrannie, and brought in many moſt wicked abominations, cannot the Churches caſt him foorth, with his inuentious, but they commit Schiſme?
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:19449:29"/>
Can any thing be more friuolous? Are all ſeuerall kingdomes tied vnto <hi>Rome,</hi> or ſhall we be tied to ioyne where there be ſome remnants of a Church, with Idolatrie? And concerning the reſt, your ſelf do in effect now confeſſe, that ſome part of Chriſts miniſtry remaineth in the popery, when you ſay that their Baptiſme concerning the outward waſhing, is true Baptiſme. And moreouer what ſhould be, we diſpute not, but this proueth that the true ſeale of Gods couenant is giuen to open Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters. For the ſeale is the ſame in it ſelfe, but the Idolater hath not the fruite of it, vntill he come to true faith. And ſo your next abſurdities fall off themſelues, ſéeing the hauing of the true ſeale (that is the outward waſhing in Baptiſme) dooth not make the papiſts true Chriſtians, nor proue that Gods coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of peace and loue, dooth belong to the Romiſh harlot: ſo many among them as come to true faith, receiue that vſe of the ſeale. All this I ſay dooth follow vpon your owne confeſſion, who build with the one hand, and breake down with the other. But it paſſeth all the reſt, that then Chriſt muſt néeds haue di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers ſeuerall bodies, or elſe he cannot ſtand an head to thrée ſo diuers Churches, as the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and the Church of <hi>Geneua.</hi> Why Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> you wil not deny but that to the elect in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> Chriſt is the head. And this is further to be noted, that when we ſpeak of a viſible Church, we ſpeake not of men alone, but of Gods ordinances. And ſo touching the holy Sacrament of Baptiſme in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſo much of the truth as remaineth, Chriſt is the Author of them, and ſo ſtandeth the head of his own, he is not the head of the Apoſtaſie, or to the wicked inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. So then in all Churches Chriſt is the Author and head of that which is his ordinance, and of thoſe which belong vnto him. What blaſphemies are then hereby allowed? And if the Papiſts haue quite ouerthown the one Sacrament, by turning it from a Sacrament, into a Sacrifice propitiatory, what rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is it therefore to ſay Baptiſme is ouerthrowne? We muſt yet a little further deale about the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe you make all our people to be but as heathen without the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, and not rightly entred to become a viſible Church: but all
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:19449:30"/>
receiued in at the ſound of her Maieſties trumpet. I ſay our people ſtood vnder the couenant before, as a part of the viſible Church; and that our ſoueraigne Quéene did not compell thoſe which before were not vnder the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, to become the church, but by her regall power giuen vnto her of God, baniſhed the v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped power of Antichriſt, aboliſhed Idolatry, and compelled her people, hauing receaued the ſeale of the couenant and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing Chriſt, to receiue alſo the true doctrine. This was not to begin a Church, but to reforme a Church: hereupon it fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth out in queſtion, whether the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church of Chriſt in time of Idolatry. It is vſually ſaid, that the Church is in the papacy, but the papacy is not the Church: I ſaid we may rather ſay (to ſpeake more plainely) the papacy was in the Church, becauſe Antichriſt who brought in all the papacy, erected his throne in the Church. You begin with this Maſter <hi>Barrow, and ſay that I hold it not enough to affirme with the learned deuines, that the inuiſible Church of God is in the papacy, as in all other places of the world, becauſe God hath his elect there, and in all other places: but to be ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular, I haue inuerted the propoſition, and ſay that the papacy is in the Church.</hi> O Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> it is your bold ignorance as in all other matters? Who be thoſe learned diuines, that when they ſay the Church is in the papacy, but the papacy is not the Church, doo meane no more but that there be Gods E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, as in other places of the world? If you haue any modeſty, bring forth ſome one learned deuine which is of that iudgement. I did like rather to ſay the papacy is in the Church, then to ſay the Church is in the papacie, becauſe I ſée diuers doo miſtake it, as though it were onely meant, that in the papacy there are Gods Elect and no further, that is no outward viſible Church in any reſpect. I doo not differ any iot in the ſpéech from the ſenſe which Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> and others doo giue: for when I ſay the papacy is in the church, but the papacy is not the church: by the papacy we muſt néeds vnderſtand that vſurped tyranny of the Pope and his Clergy, with all their abominable inuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. By the Church we may not vnderſtand only Gods E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect, but alſo ſo much of Gods ordinances as remaine, not only
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:19449:30"/>
in the points of doctrine, and publike profeſſion of the name of Chriſt, but alſo in the holy Baptiſme, the ſeale of the couenant which all haue, and may ſo farre be called the viſible Church. That the papacy ſhould inuade the viſible Church, remaine in it, and not vtterly or quite deſtroy it, I did alleage that Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, Antichriſt ſhould ſit in Gods Temple.</p>
            <p>Now let vs ſee whether this bée not the meaning of the moſt learned diuines, when they ſay the Church is in the papacy. Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> handleth this point in the fourth booke of his Inſtitutions, Chap. 2. ſection 11. 12. Which booke though it be in our language, yet is it little read and ſtudied of our peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as the weakenes and readines of many to be ſeduced by he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks and Schiſmaticks dooth euidently declare. I will ſet downe his words for ſuch as haue not the booke. <hi>But yet as of old time</hi> (ſaith Maſter <hi>Caluine) among the Iewes there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned certaine peculiar prerogatiues of the Church, ſo doo wee not at this day take from the papiſts, thoſe ſteppes of the Church which God would haue to remaine among them not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the diſſipation. God had once made his coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with thoſe Iewes, that ſame couenant did continue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holden by the ſtablenes of it ſelfe, as it were wraſtling againſt their impietie, rather then kept of them. Such therefore is the certainty and conſtancy of Gods goodnes, that there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned the couenant of the Lord, neither could his faith giuen, be made voyde by their vnfaithfulnes, neither could circumciſion be ſo prophaned by their impure hands, but that it was ſtill the true ſigne and Sacrament of his couenant. Whereupon the Lord called the Children which were borne vnto them, his ſonnes, Ezech. 16. which nothing at all perteined vnto him, but by a ſpeciall bleſſing. So when he hath left his couenant in France, Italie, Germany, Spayne, England: ſince theſe Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces haue beene oppreſſed with the tyrannie of Antichriſt, yet that his Couenant might remaine inuiolable, he firſt there pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued Baptiſme, the teſtimony of his couenant, which being conſecrate with his owne mouth, retaineth her owne force, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the vngodlines of man: then furthermore he hath by his prouidence brought to paſſe, that there ſhould other</hi>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:19449:31"/>
               <hi>remnants alſo remaine, leaſt the Church ſhould vtterly periſh. And as oftentimes buildings are ſo pulled downe, that the foundations and ruines remaine, ſo hee hath not ſuffered his Church to be ſubuerted by Antichriſt, euen from the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or to be laide euen with the ground (howſoeuer to puniſh mens ingratitude, which had deſpiſed his word, he hath ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red horrible ſhaking and diſsipation to chance) but euen after the laying waſt, hee would haue the building remaine, halfe pulled downe. Whereas therefore wee will not ſimplie graunt to the Papiſts the title of the Church, we doo not therefore de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that there bee Churches among them: but onely wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about the true and lawful ordering of the Church, which is required both in the Communion of the holy things, which are the ſignes of the profeſsion, &amp; alſo of doctrine moſt chiefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie. Daniel and Paule foretold that Antichriſt ſhould ſit in the Temple of God: among vs wee account the Biſhop of Rome the Captaine and ſtanderd bearer of that wicked and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable Kingdome. That his ſeate is placed in the Temple of God, thereby is meant that his Kingdome ſhall be ſuch, as may aboliſh neither the name of Chriſt nor of the Church. Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by therefore it is manifeſt, that we denie not but that there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine Churches alſo vnder his tyrannie: but yet ſuch as hee hath prophaned with ſacrilegious impietie: ſuch as hee hath afflicted with outragious dominion: ſuch as he hath corrupted and almoſt killed with euill and deadly doctrines, as it were with poyſoned drinkes: in which Chriſt lieth halfe buried, the Goſpel ouerwhelmed, godlines expelled, the worſhip of God almoſt aboliſhed: furthermore in which all things are ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed and out of order, that there appeareth the face of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, rather then of the holy citie of God. Briefelie, I ſay they be Churches, in as much as the Lord dooth there merueilouſlie preſerue the remnants of his people, howſoeuer miſerably diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed and ſcatred: and in as much as there remaine ſome bad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges or ſeales of the Church, and theſe eſpecially, whoſe efficacy neither the craft of the diuell, nor the wickednes of men can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy: but on the other ſide, becauſe thoſe notes or markes are blotted out, which wee ought chiefely to reſpect in this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſie,</hi>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:19449:31"/>
               <hi>I ſay that euerie one of their aſſemblies, and the whole bodie wanteth the lawfull forme of a Church,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre be Maſter <hi>Caluines</hi> words: tell me now Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> is Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> to be accounted among the learned Diuines? Dooth he ſay the Church is in the papacy, that is no more but that the Elect are among them, as in other places of the World? Looke alſo what I haue ſaid touching this whole matter which he dooth not here ſay, yea euen from that which is in <hi>Ezechiel</hi> 16. Where you aſke, who but this per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſe fellow (ſpeaking of me) could thus ſtumble and cauill at thoſe words, my ſonnes and my daughters, &amp;c? But if it bee not plaine enough which Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> ſaith in this which I haue recited, to proue that you would beare the ſimple in hand, that the learned Diuines are of another minde, and yet vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand not their minde: I will adde a little more out of the ſame Author. In his Epiſtle 404. thus hee writeth, <hi>Quòd eccleſiae reliquias manere in papatu dico, no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> restringo ad electos qui illic di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperſi ſunt: ſed ruinas diſſipatae eccleſiae illic extare intelligo. Ac ne mihilongis rationibus disputandum ſit, nos pauli autoritate con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentos eſſe decet, qui Antichristum in temple deiſeſſurum pronun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiat, quamquam &amp; hoc rationibus ſatis validis me probaſſe puto, eceleſiam, licet ſemiruptam, imo ſilubet, diruptam, ac deformem, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquam tamen manere in papatu.</hi> In that I ſay the remnants of the Church remaine in the papacy, I doo not reſtraine it to the Elect which are diſperſed there: but I meane that the ruines of a diſperſed Church are extant among them. And that I may not diſpute the matter with reaſons at large, it becommeth vs to be content and ſatiſfied with the authority of <hi>Paule,</hi> which pronounceth that Antichriſt ſhall ſit in the Temple of God. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit I ſuppoſe I haue proued this with reaſons ſtrong enough, that there remaineth neuertheleſſe ſome Church in the papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, although halfe broken downe, or if you will, broken downe, and deformed. Alſo Maſter <hi>Beza,</hi> Epiſtle 81. page 356. For the remnants of the Church in the papacy is of the ſame minde, affirming that there remaine not onely Gods Elect, but alſo the Sacrament of Baptiſme, and ſundry poynts of ſound doctrine.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:19449:32"/>Now let vs ſee what horrible blaſphemies you ſay will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe of this that I ſay, Antichriſt ſhould ſit in the Church, and yet the ſame remayne ſtill the viſible Church, ſo farre foorth as Maſter <hi>Caluines</hi> words and Maſter Bezaes doo import. For when you will needes haue it that God hath giuen me vp into a reprobate ſenſe, the matter toucheth not me ſo much, as Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> and many other moſt worthie men which ſo expound it. Nay, if God open your eyes you ſhall ſee whether you doo not like Rabſaka reproach the Lord God who hath vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered it by his Apoſtle. The firſt is this: <hi>If Antichriſt may be ſayd to ſit, raigne and remayne in the Church of God, then Chriſt is not made heire and Lord of all, and ſet as King vpon Mount Sion.</hi> A worthie collection is it not? becauſe God in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous iudgement for the puniſhment of thoſe that receiued not the loue of the trueth, giueth power vnto: Satan and Antichriſt to ſeduce the multitude in the viſible Church, Chriſt is not heire of all things, nor raigneth as K. vpon Mount Sion. Wil you ſay, if the diuell haue a kingdome in the world, Chriſt is not Lord of the whole world? Mount Sion may be vſed for the vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church, but moſt properly for the inuiſible which is the Communion of Saints, of which are none but the elect. Satan and Antichriſt are not able to pluck one of theſe out of his hand, he raigneth ouer them and in them. Moreouer, he raigneth ouer the whole viſible Church and ouer the whole world (for hee is aſcended, and filleth all things) ſo that Satan, Antichriſt and all Tyrants, can proceed no further then his will.</p>
            <p>The next is: <hi>If Antichriſt ſit in the Church, then Chriſt is either caſt out of his houſe made ſubiect vnto Antichriſt, or els deuideth with him.</hi> Chriſt is not caſt out of his houſe nor made ſubiect, (theſe be moſt friuolous and fantaſticall imaginations) but in his moſt high and ſoueraigne power he vſeth Antichriſt and Satan as the inſtruments of his wrath, not vtterly to raſe and deſtroy his Temple, but miſerably to afflict the choſen, and ſo ſeduce the reprobate, euen all wicked hypocrites which are in the viſible Church. I knowe not what you will vnderſtand by diuiding, but the diuell may in ſome ſenſe be ſayd to diuide with God, in that he receiueth one part vnto damnation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:19449:32"/>The third is: <hi>If Antichriſt ſit in the church, then the church of Chriſt may remayne ſubiect vnto and be gouerned by An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt.</hi> Here we muſt diſtinguiſh. Firſt, the viſible Church con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſeth of men, and of Gods ordinances. The men are of two ſorts, the elect and the reprobate. He exerciſeth a ſauage tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and oppreſſeth the elect whome yet he cannot bring into his ſubiection, to make them hang their faith upo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, or his lawes. For God did miraculouſly preſerue a remnant in the poperie, which were not vtterly poyſoned. He corrupteth the lawes and ordinances of Chriſt, but yet had not power giuen him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all. His full dominion is ouer the reprobate, which receiue his marke and worſhip him.</p>
            <p>The fourth is: <hi>If Antichriſt ſit in the Church, then the Church is ſubiect vnto two heads, and Chriſt then is not the onely head.</hi> This is fully anſwered in the former: for his ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannie and vſurpation dooth not make him head, but vnto thoſe whoſe head Chriſt is not, more then by hypocriticall profeſſion of his name.</p>
            <p>The fift is: <hi>If Antichriſt in the Church, then Antichriſts miniſters and marked ſeruants may be brought into and ſet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the Church of God, &amp; then is not Chriſts miniſtrie which he hath ordeined in his Goſpell and his Church, permanent vnto the worlds end, but variable at the will of man, and then may the Church of God caſt out Chriſts miniſtrie, and receiue Antichriſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is alſo moſt friuolous: for as Antichriſt did almoſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy all, but yet not all, in other things, ſo in the miniſtrie: for the miniſtrie of Chriſt was not vtterly deſtroyed. Agayne, the Church if you vnderſtand Gods true people, did not this: but Antichriſt did it.</p>
            <p>The ſixt is: <hi>That if Antichriſts lawes may be brought and ſet vp, and remayne in the Church, then Chriſt is not the onely Prophet and law giuer, and then may the Church be built vpon another foundation then vpon Gods word.</hi> Chriſt is the onely true Prophet, whoſe lawes onely are wholeſome. Antichriſt hath vſurped a power to make lawes and to ſet them vp in the Church. The elect, though ſome of them for a time haue gone
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:19449:33"/>
a ſtray and followed Antichriſt, vntill it pleaſed GOD to open their eyes: and many of them holding Chriſt haue been infected and ſtayned with ſundrie errors of Antichriſt, yet their ſaluation being onely through faith, it cannot be ſayd that they were built vpon any other foundation then that which the Prophets and Apoſtles haue layd. The reprobate which haue worſhipped the beaſt, though in reſpect that hauing been borne vnder the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian profeſſion, and had the true ſeale of the Couenant, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the name of Chriſt, they might bee the viſible Church, or of the viſible Church, yet they were not built vpon Chriſt vnto ſaluation, but vpon the lawes of Antichriſt vnto deſtruction.</p>
            <p>The ſeuenth is, <hi>That if all Antichriſts abominations, here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies and Idolatries may bee brought into and remayne in the Church of God, then no blaſphemie, hereſie, Apoſtaſie, or any thing that man can commit or deuiſe, can break the couenant.</hi> If the fayth of God might be made of none effect by the vnfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes of men, it were a wofull caſe. The couenant of God is founded vpon free grace. The Lord would not (euen becauſe of his Couenant) ſuffer the deuill and Antichriſt vtterly to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>face his Temple: but preſerued the holy ſeede, preſerued ſome of his ordinances, yea ſo farre, that in ſome ſorte the Couenant was not diſanulled to the very reprobate, but that outward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly they ſtoode vnder it in their Apoſtaſie: and it might bee ſaid of them (though indeede they were no true Children) as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſayth of the rebellious Iewes, theirs is the Couenant and the Adoption.</p>
            <p>The eight is, <hi>That if thoſe that worſhip the beaſt and his Image may be ſayd to be in the Church, and their ſeede out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly within the Couenant, then the moſt abominable and execrable in this eſtate may be ſayd members of Chriſt, waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and purged with his blood, ſainctified and led by his ſpirite in aſſurance of ſaluation, for none can be ſayd to bee within the Church but the members of the Church. And whoſoeuer we may affirme to be within the Church, thoſe (ſo long as they continue in that eſtate) we are alſo to iudge aſſuredly ſaued, for any thing to vs reuealed or knowen to the contrary.</hi> Theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re things eaſily ſpoken by ſuch as are bolde to vtter whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:19449:33"/>
they imagine. The Prophets complayned that the great multitude both of Iuda, and the ten Tribes were rebels, and that the Lord had but a remnant among them: ſhew when that multitude of open wicked ones, and their ſeede were caſt out from being the viſible Church, &amp; then ſhew when they were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued in agayn. For both theſe you muſt do, becauſe the whole nation when Chriſt came were the children of the Couenant, &amp; it is ſayd that Chriſt came among his owne, and his owne re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued him not. You muſt prooue that the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſies, the high Prieſts and all the Capitall enemies of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour Chriſt were deemed vndoubtedly ſaued euen when they ſhewed their enmitie againſt him. For they were then in the Church. They could not ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chayre and not be in the Church. The Uineyard was not taken from thoſe wicked huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmen which had ſlayn the ſeruants, vntill they had ſlayn the ſonne and heire himſelfe. Theſe things are ſo manifeſt by the Scriptures Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> that if it ſhall not pleaſe God to open your eyes to ſee your palpable groſſe ignorauce, and bolde preſumption, yet others may ſee and tremble leaſt God giue them ouer alſo, for the pride of their hearts.</p>
            <p>Whereas I ſayd that the Apoſtaſie is in the Church but not the Church: you think it ſtrange repugnancie. Yet indéed there is none, as may appeare by that which I haue ſet down before, and ſhould appeare vnto you, if your minde were not ſo deepely infected with the principles of Donatiſme. You runne ſtill vpon this Rock, <hi>that becauſe none ought to bee in the Church, but ſuch as appeare godly, therefore no open Idolaters can be ſayd to be in the viſible Church, to ſtand out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, and their ſeede in any reſpect, vnder the couenant.</hi> I haue plainely prooued the contrary. What ought to be, is one thing: and what hath béen or what is, is another. To your o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther queſtion I anſwere, that it is no Schiſme to depart from the Church of Rome, although in ſome reſpects they were the viſible Church. This matter Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> hath beene as throughly purſued by the Papiſts as euer you or any Donatiſt ſhall be able, and ſuch anſwere they haue receiued from the Churches that haue made ſeparation from them, as that they
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:19449:34"/>
haue no cauſe to glory. The ten Tribes remayned ſtill in ſome ſorte the viſible Church, and vnder the Couenant, as I haue prooued before, but yet they were not ſuch a true Church as men might ioyne withall in their worſhip: and therefore when <hi>Ieroboam</hi> had ſet vp the golden Calues, the Leuites departed from them and went to <hi>Ieruſalem, 2. Chron, 11. 23. 14.</hi> Then you come to expound how this may bee taken that Antichriſt ſhal ſit in the Temple of God. And firſt as you take it his ſitting in the Temple of God, <hi>may be vnderſtood as in regarde that he tooke his originall before he was reuealed.</hi> Let any ſimple man looke vpon the wordes of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſee whether he ſpeake of any ſuch cloſe ſitting. Then that he ſhould ſit where ſometimes the true Churches haue beene, which hee ſhould ſo deſtroy and waſte, as there ſhould be no ſhape or ſteps of any of them left vpon the earth: as it was foretolde, <hi>Matth. 24, 29. Reuel. 6. 14.</hi> See what two places Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> hath found to proue Antichriſt ſhould vtterly deſtroy the viſible Church. Theſe be the wordes: <hi>And immediately after the oppreſſion of thoſe dayes the Sunne ſhall be darkned, &amp; the Moone ſhall not giue her light, and the ſtarres ſhall fall from heauen, and the powers of heauen ſhall be ſhaken.</hi> This is<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſpoken of Chriſts comming to iudgment, and is meant indeed of the Sunne, the Moone and ſtars themſelues: and therefore moſt fooliſhly concluded, that Antichriſt ſhall vtterly deſtroy the viſible Church. And for the place in the Reuelation, <hi>The heauen departed away as a booke that is roled vp,</hi> you may euen as well conclude, that the whole Church in the world vtterly fayled, as to ſay therefore Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt vtterly defaced the viſible Church. And if you will haue the matter tried by ſo darke a place, your light had neede to be great. But your pretieſt reaſons of all are yet behinde. <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt ſhall be lifted vp aboue all that is called God, this can not be done by any Miniſter in the Church, ſeeing euery ſoule muſt bee ſubiect.</hi> They ſay it will weary an old bodie to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe a Child vp and down all day that can newe goe. I am ſure it will weary any man to follow you Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> in all your trifles. God commandeth euery ſoule ſhall ſubmit it ſelfe vnto
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:19449:34"/>
the higher powers: doth it here vpon follow that if a king vſurp that which belongeth to God, they muſt therein <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ay him ſo long as he remayneth their king? Alſo when it is ſayd, that he is God, you ſay what blaſphemie will not inſue, if this ſhould be literally taken? It may as well be inforced (ſay you) by this place, that Antichriſt is God, as that the place where he raigneth is the Temple of God. You will not haue this place expounded literally, and then what ſhall we make of it, or howe ſhall we finde Antichriſt: May he not be the Turke or ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: If the Papiſts could proue y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> which you ſpeake, but with ſome little ſhew, how much would they glory? For grant the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a myſticall ſenſe of theſe words, and they will carie it whither they liſt. To exalt himſelfe aboue all that is called God, is lite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally ſpoken, and literally fulfilled, when the Pope exalteth himſelfe aboue all Kinges and Emperours which are called Gods. So that he ſhall ſit as God in the Temple of God, ſhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing himſelfe that he is God. What blaſphemie is it which will enſue if theſe wordes bee all conſtrued literally after the Grammaticall ſenſe? The wordes doo not import that he ſhall bee God indeede, but that he ſhall take that to himſelfe which belongeth to the moſt high God. The thing which deceiueth you Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> is in the word, ſhewing, for euery thing that a ſhew is made of, is not ſo in truth. There is a true ſhew and there is a falſe ſhew, when one doth arrogate that to himſelfe, and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſt of it, which belongeth not vnto him. As Antichriſt vſurping not onely an earthly dignitie, but euen the high power and authority of God, is therefore ſayd to ſhewe himſelfe to bée God.</p>
            <p>And now wheras I ſtand vpon this, that the Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land was a true Church of God before popery, and that in po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery it ſtood a member or part of the vniuerſall viſible Church (fo farre as the remnants of Chriſts Church remained not vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly defaced by Antichriſt) &amp; that the caſting out of Antichriſt and his lawes, and vſurped power is not the beginning, but the reſtoring and repayring, or recouering a Church from miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deſolation. And as <hi>Ioſias</hi> and other godly kings of <hi>Iuda</hi> by terrour of puniſhment draue Idolaters which outwardly ſtood
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:19449:35"/>
vnder the Couenant being cyrcumciſed, from falſe worſhip vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the lawes of God: ſo Quéene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> hath done with her ſubiects being baptized, and thereby bound to renounce falſe worſhip, and to imbrace the holy doctrine of the Couenant.</p>
            <p>Here you ſay that to make my concluſion follow, <hi>I muſt proue, and make euident demonſtration by Scripture that the Church of England was rightly gathered vnto, and eſtabliſhed in that holy fayth and order which Chriſt hath left vnto his Church in vniuerſall and particular, according to the rules and examples in his Teſtament. Next, that they fell not away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this holy fayth in the time of popery, and that now they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue and faythfully walke in the ſame fayth and order. If I had done this, you ſay I had powerfully conuinced and ſtopped the mouthes of all Schiſmatikes for euer.</hi> I ſée you can make your mach wiſely Maſter <hi>Barrow.</hi> I muſt make euident demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration by the Scriptures: of what? of that which was not mentioned by the Scriptures. For there is no particular men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of planting the fayth of Chriſt in England. If wee ſhew it out of auncient records, then doe I not ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ilfie your deſire at all. Agayne it muſt be ſhewed by the Scriptures, that the Church of England receiued orderly the fayth and order of Chriſt, not onely in generall, but in euery particular. This is a ſurer knot than the former. And me thinkes you ſhould bee a little more kinde, for the honour of your countrey: not that any honour is to be rendred againſt truth, but whereas you confeſſe that a true Church may erre in diuers things, ſo that it be not conuinced &amp; ſinne obſtinately. If the planters of the fayth and diſcipline of Chriſt in England did erre it ſome things (which yet you know not) how can you tell but that they did it in ſimplicitie? wee ſée that in auncient times, and of late dayes GOD hath had many Children in England which haue been begotten and nouriſhed vp in the land, and haue acknowledged her their mother. And we are ſure herevpon that God hath put his couenant of mercy in England, and planted a true Church: And therefore if you deale rightly, you muſt proue againſt vs. I haue ſhewed that popery did not vtterly deſtroy the viſible Church. And there be at this day multitudes that ſo walke in the holy fayth, that no
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:19449:35"/>
man is able to accuſe them. And therefore if either all, or the moſt part of Schiſmatikes were not obſtinate cauillers, their mouthes might be ſtopped for euer. Thus much might fuffice agaynſt that you affirme our people neuer had any entrance to be vnder the couenant, and ſo to ſtand the viſible Church, but to be as heapes of prophane heathen: but that your matter rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth further then againſt the aſſemblies in England, condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning other Churches which profeſſe the holy Goſpel. And leaſt ſome may think that in this poynt I charge ye but by ſome hard collection in ſo horrible preſumption, as to condemne all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Churches, I will recite the wordes which you haue ſet downe in your other booke, <hi>pag. 33.</hi> where after long diſcourſe agaynſt the reaſons which Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> vſeth both out of the olde and new Teſtament, to proue that neither the worſhip it ſelfe, nor the faythfull are defiled by the company of the open wicked, you ſpeake thus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>This and ſuch like deteſtable ſtuffe, hath Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> in his ignorance, partly to confute that damnable ſect of Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, which fantaſtically dreame vnto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues a Church without ſpot in this life, and for euery tranſgreſſion that ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth are ready to leaue &amp; forſake the felowſhip of the Church, without due and orderly reproofe. Partly alſo is this ſtuffe brought to defend his owne raſh and diſorderly proceedings at <hi>Geneua,</hi> whileſt hee at the firſt daſh made no ſcruple to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue all the whole ſtate, euen all the prophane ignorant people into the boſome of the Church, to adminiſter the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments vnto them: which confuſe route could not fit with Chriſts heauenly gouernement, neither could it by any meanes agree vnto them in this eſtate. But that monſtrous diſorders and haynous enormityes dayly enſued thereof, whereby this their Church became a iuſt reproch vnto all men, euen to thoſe wicked Heretikes, yea that which is worſe, and more to be lamented, it became a miſerable preſident, and perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious example euen vnto all <hi>Europe,</hi> to fall into the like tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſion: as the confuſed eſtate of all thoſe regions (where the Goſpell is thus diſorderly taught) declareth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let the Reader here conſider (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) what a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:19449:36"/>
Champion you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re become for the Papiſts, for Heretickes and Schiſmaticks, agaynſt all the Churches which profeſſe the Goſpell, and agaynſt all their teachers. What was Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> to bee regarded, if he were ſo ignorant, ſo raſh, and ſo diſorderly in his doings? How miſerable was his caſe, that he muſt be ſo pernitious an example to the ruine of many? What is or what hath the Church of <hi>Geneua</hi> been, and together with the aſſemblies of <hi>England,</hi> all Churches in Europe, but heapes of prophane multitudes, no better then heathen or dogs, if your words be true? True Chriſt they haue none, for they fit not his gouernment, nor his gouernment them (as you ſay). But Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> as the Churches and their miniſters haue been able &amp; haue iuſtly defended themſelues (though not from all faults, becauſe there is no Church ſo pure) agaynſt the wiſeſt and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedſt reuiling <hi>Rabſakaes,</hi> the Hereticks and Schiſinaticks: ſo muſt you thinke that they ſhall be able to withſtand two or thrée which are ſo ignorant in ſome grounds of religion, as that their bookes are a bundle, or rather a dunghill of abſurdities. Whom ſhal you euer perſwade that hath any true light, that your know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſo farre paſſeth the learned of all Churches? Were it not honour enough for ye to triumph ouer the miniſters of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> whom ſo often in diſdayne you terme lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Prieſts, but ye muſt be generall conquetors, like <hi>Alexander</hi> the great? Faine you would ſeeme to bee farre from the Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, but how néere you are vnto them, euen in their tents, all that haue ſkill doo ſee. Well then to conclude this poynt, he that will finde a true Church with which he may ioyne himſelfe, he muſt not ſeeke it in the publike aſſemblies either in <hi>England, Scotland, Geneua,</hi> or any region of Europe, (for by your iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment they be all prophane heapes) but he muſt ſeeke the fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and ioyne with the Donatiſts of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the ſecond part of the aſſumption, where you ſay, that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath power to caſt foorth none by excommunication. I am of the minde that Chriſt hath giuen ſuch a power to his Church, and alſo doo take it that the Church of <hi>England</hi> is not boyd thereof. But you condemne all excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication which is not executed by an Elderſhip, and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:19449:36"/>
of euery particular aſſemblie. If excommunication be onely to bee ſo executed; then how could <hi>Eſra</hi> with the Elders and Princes of Iſrael publiſh an excommunication generall againſt euery one that ſhould not within three dayes come vp to <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem? Eſra. 10. verſ. 8.</hi> And where doo you proue that excommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication is to be executed vpon any, but for contumacie and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of the Church? Doo you hold that a man which doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent him for his adulterie, theſe, hereſie, or ſuch like, and is caſt downe in ſorrowe, is yet to be deliuered vp to Satan? If not, why doo you vpbrayd, that there is none caſt foorth among vs, but for contumacie?</p>
            <p>In the next place you take vpon you to confute and cut downe foure falſe expoſitions, as you ſay, of <hi>Math. 18. verſ. 17. Tell the Church. The firſt ſort take the word Church, for the Pope: the ſecond for the Archbiſhops and Biſhops, which exerciſe this power for the whole Church: the third for the companie of the Elders apart from the people, which they call the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorie: the fourth are they which would haue the people ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicate without the Elders.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The two firſt ſorts (that is the Pope and the Biſhops) doo depend (you ſay) vppon one line, and build their preheminence vpon the promiſe made to the Apoſtle <hi>Peter, Math. 16. verſ. 18. 19.</hi> where the keyes of the kindome of heauen are giuen him. And vpon the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> his example, who deliuered <hi>Hyme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus</hi> and <hi>Alexander</hi> vnto Satan, <hi>Timoth.</hi> 5. 10. You are ſo learned and ſkilfull (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) yea ſo truſtie and true, that wee muſt holde them for Oracles that doo proceede out of your mouth, although indeed they be neuer ſo falſe, as ſhall appeare. Touching the place in <hi>Mat.</hi> 16. for the keyes giuen vnto <hi>Peter,</hi> it is agreed vpon by all parts y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> there is a power giuen to be exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in the Church. The diſagréement is chiefly about this, to whom it is giuen. The Pope with his adherents ſayth, it was giuen onely vnto <hi>Peter</hi> and his ſucceſſors. He ſayth further, that <hi>Peter</hi> was Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> that there is his chaire, and that this power is annexed to that chaire, and ſo the Pope alone is to haue it, and from him all other are to participate which ſhall exerciſe any part of it in the Church. The Biſhops of the church
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:19449:37"/>
of <hi>England,</hi> and they that maintaine the government by preſby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teries doo both alike condemne that challenge of the Pope, as an vſurpation. Both parts affirming, that although our Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our doo ſpeake onely to <hi>Peter,</hi> ſaying; to thee I giue the keyes of the kingdome of heauen: yet he giueth him nothing but that which he gaue vnto the other Apoſtles. This they prooue by <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. where he breathed vpon them, and ſayd ioyntly to them all; <hi>As the father ſent me, ſo I ſend you, and whoſe ſinnes ye ſhall forgiue they are forgiuen, &amp;c.</hi> With what face can you ſay then (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) that the Biſhops and the Pope depend vpon one line, and build their preheminence vpon that promiſe made vnto <hi>Peter?</hi> You might truelier haue ſayd, that the Biſhops and preſbyteries depend vppon one line for their preheminence, not only for that they expound thoſe places, <hi>Math.</hi> 16. and <hi>Ioh.</hi> 20. alike, but alſo that the Biſhops challenge none other power then the preſbyteries do. For the controuerſie betweene the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and the preſbyteries, is whether of them by Gods word, &amp; for the benefit of the Church are to exerciſe that power which Chriſt hath left vnto her. The one ſide doth affirme that by Gods word the execution of this her power doth belong to the Biſhops, as being moſt properly the Apoſtles ſucceſſors: and therefore do hold that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath done right in reſeruing this power vnto them. The Churches which hold the other gouernment, do affirme, that when our Sauiour ſaith, tell the Church, it is not meant, tell the Biſhop or thoſe which are ioyned with them: but tell the Church, is tell the Conſiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, which conſiſteth of Paſtors, Teachers, and Elders choſen from among the people. This Conſiſtorie (ſay they) is to haue and to exerciſe that power and iuriſdiction which the Biſhops do hold. Now (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) as you ſay, the gouernment thus by the Biſhops is popiſh, ſo you grieuouſly condemne the Conſiſtorie: affirming that it is irregular, that it hath no ground or warrant in Gods word, but vtterly ſubuerteth all order, and openeth a wide gap vnto all licentiouſnes. &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Then come the fourth ſort which expound theſe words (tell the church) wrong. And thoſe are they which ſay tel the church, is tell the congregation of people without the Elders. Here you
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:19449:37"/>
ſhew ſome ſkill alſo to confute: which is but to fight with your owne ſhadow, for this fourth ſort (I thinke) haue neuer been heard of, but among your ſelues. And in déede your heauenly patterne (whatſoeuer ye ſpeake of paſtors, teachers, and El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders) is nothing elſe but an heape of people, without any of theſe officers. For was it euer heard of among men, that there bee offices, in which there is no power or authority at all annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto the officers which execute them, not euen in the things wherein their offices conſiſt, aboue thoſe which haue not the ſame offices? For if it be true which you ſay, that the greateſt miniſter hath no more power to bind or looſe the ſinnes of the leaſt member, then the ſaid member hath to bind or looſe his. Or if Chriſt ſpeake to all, euen to the wemen, <hi>Iohn</hi> 20. whoſe ſinnes ye forgiue, they are forgiuen, &amp;c. If the word haue no more efficacie to worke faith deliuered by the miniſtrie, or the Sacrament to ſeale the promiſes haue no more power deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by a miniſter, then when the ſame word is vttered, and thoſe Sacraments deliuered by any man or by any woman, or if eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry young man, yea euery maide (which is of the aſſembly) haue equall power with any to excommunicate, we would ſee where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the power of any of your officers conſiſteth: where all or eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one haue equall power, there all are officers: where all are officers, we may ſay that in déed none are publick officers. This is Maſter <hi>Barrowes</hi> heauenly patterne, by which he hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinced all our Churches, and found them ſo obſtinate for reiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it, that they be quite ſeparate from Chriſt. Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> will ſay he ſpake not of the Sacraments, for he faith a miniſter onely is to deliuer them. And I ſay one part of the power of looſing is by the Sacraments, in as much as they ſeale our faith.</p>
            <p>The power of diſcipline exerciſed by the preſbytory, as it is in the Churches of <hi>France, Scotland, Geneua,</hi> the <hi>Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, &amp;c.</hi> you moſt grieuouſly condemne: the reader ſhall ſee your own words, in your other booke page 189. and 190. thus you ſpeake. <hi>Theſe men in ſtead of this groſſe Antichriſtian gouernement, &amp;c. would bring in a new adulterate forged go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement in ſhew, or rather in deſpite of Chriſts bleſſed go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement,</hi>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:19449:38"/>
               <hi>which they in their pride, raſhnes, ignorance, and enſualitie of their fleſhly hearts, moſt miſerably, iunouate, cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt and peruert, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo page 166. you tearme Claſſical and Prouinciall ſynods and counſels, a diueliſh forgery. Here you ſay the fault and pride of the Elders is intollerable. Alſo (you ſay) <hi>that many were the reaſons, and more the inconueniences that might bee alleaged againſt this preſumptuous irregular conſiſtorie, which hath no ground in the word of God but vt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly ſubuerteth, deſtroyeth and corrupteth the whole order and Communion of the Churches, openeth a wide gap vnto all licenciouſnes, and prophannes of manners, &amp;c.</hi> Thus the Church of England is no Church of Chriſt, becauſe of their go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernement by Biſhops. In other places where the gouerne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is by preſbytreies, not onely the people (by your ſentence) are prophane multitudes, but their miniſters proud, raſh, ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, and in the ſenſuality of their fleſhly hearts, haue cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted Chriſtes gouernement, &amp; in deſpite thereof haue ſet vp a diueliſh forgery, and open the gap vnto all prophaneneſſe, &amp;c. O Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> what reproaches are theſe againſt all chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches and their miniſters? I muſt néeds tell you againe, that there is not any which hath any ſparke of Chriſtian modeſty, but will ſay God hath not ſent ye, your ſufferings are not to be gloried in, you are but <hi>Rabaſaka,</hi> that thus reproach the church of Chriſt. What Schiſmaticks haue gone beyond ye? Now followeth the ſuſpenſion from the Sacraments. You muſt vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand, that al your friuolous cauils about this, and all your reproaches reach not alone vnto the Church of <hi>England,</hi> but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ormed Churches which practiſe a ſuſpention. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Beza</hi> in his booke againſt <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> page 10. ſheweth the vſe and practiſe of it, not onely in their Church, but in the aun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Churches. Alſo page 124. he proueth it by the example of <hi>Moſes</hi> ſiſter, and of thoſe which were reſtrained a whole month from eating the paſſeouer: theſe ceaſed not in the meane time to be accounted members of the congregation. When the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance is not throughly teſtified, or the reſt ſtand in néed of ſome terror, as wel as the party that hath offended, then is there vſe of ſuſpention.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:19449:38"/>To proue that neither the worſhip of God, nor yet the godly are polluted by the open wicked that communicate with them in the ſame, and that the couenant of God is in no wiſe thereby diſanulled, I alleaged firſt the auncient Church for example, vnder the conduct of <hi>Moſes</hi> in the wildernes, in which there were heapes of wicked rebels, and ſo in the time of <hi>Ieſay, Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie,</hi> and other of the Prophets, whoſe complaints are grieuous: for it is manifeſt that few godly ones among ſwarmes of wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed did worſhip together in the Temple. Here Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> your cauiles are more then ſlender: firſt that our Churches were neuer true Churches, and therefore no compariſon be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene ours and them. Touching this I haue ſpoken before. Then next you ſay that in y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> times of wicked Kings, when Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latry was ſet vp in <hi>Iuda,</hi> the godly did not communicate with the wicked, which is moſt true, but the wicked did Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate with the godly in Gods true worſhip, in the dayes of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Kings. And for the time of <hi>Moſes,</hi> you ſay thoſe wicked re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels were of the common wealth, but not of the Church, and would haue me proue that they were admitted to the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle or publick worſhip. If they were not of the Church ſtill in outward account, how were their children all receiued? Or where reade you of any family among them, which was of the common wealth, and not of the Church? There is no ſhew of ſuch a matter. Againe Saint <hi>Paule 1. Cor. 10.</hi> ſheweth that they did all communicate in the Sacraments. <hi>They did all eate the ſame ſpirituall meate, and drunke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the ſame ſpirituall drunke.</hi> What can be more clere then this? If men would not wickedly cauile againſt the holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>Then next for the time that our Sauiour liued vpon the earth, in what miſerable eſtate was the Church? The moſt of the teachers very corrupt, both in doctrine and maners Very few of the people did in déed feare God, and yet came all on heapes to the Temple together with the godly. Vnto this you anſwer that at the byrth of our Sauiour, and vnto ſuch time as they oppoſed themſelues againſt him, things were in meetly good caſe. Would any man that were not paſt all care what he ſaith, make ſuch an anſwer? Did thoſe grieuous ſects of the
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:19449:39"/>
Scribes and Phariſies riſe of a ſuddaine? Or did the high Prieſt by due courſe come to the office? Or were the open wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſeparated, where ſuch wicked men bare ſway? And if they had not of ſome long time before, brought in their owne traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, how could they haue called the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the traditions of their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. <hi>Math. 15? Mark 7.</hi> And when the Phariſies, and Sadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, the Prieſts &amp; Elders reiected and withſtood our Sauiour, they, (you ſay) <hi>then ceaſed to be the viſible Church, and that our Sauiour did ſeparate himſelfe and his Diſciples from them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What ſhould one ſay vnto you Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> are you euen bent to gainſay the manifeſt word of Chriſt? The Scribes and Phariſies did ſit in <hi>Moſes</hi> chaire, <hi>Matth. 23.</hi> Was <hi>Moſes</hi> Chaire out of the viſible Church? And what can be more plaine then that our Sauiour willeth the people to heare them? For otherwiſe how ſhould he commaunde them to obſerue and doo all things which they ſhould ſay: but after their workes hée would not haue them doo? At this you ſet vp your throate and crie out; <hi>What execrable blaſphemie and horrible hereſies doth this wretched man runne into. &amp;c. ? Doth he not hereby make our Sauiour Chriſt guiltie of the open breach of Gods lawes, and the deſtruction of all the people?</hi> Indeed that were moſt horrible and damnable blaſphemie, and he ſhould be a moſt vile and wretched man, that ſhould make our Sauiour guiltie of the breach of any lawe of God. And if you had but the true knowledge of ſome godly childe of foureteene yeres of age, you ſhould plainly ſee that our Sauiour did command them indeed to heare the Scribes and Phariſies expounding the lawe and the Prophets, and that therein he is not guilty at all of the open breach of Gods lawes: but indeed if he therein committed any offence, it was but agaynſt the principles of Donatiſme and Annabaptiſme, which Satan vnder the ſhewe of an Angell of light, hath bewitched men withall, and which you haue ſetled in your minde in ſtead of Gods lawes. For would you make vs beléeue that the Phariſies and Doctors of the lawe were euen of a ſuddaine become naught? Chriſt himſelfe when he was twelue yeares old ſate among them in the Temple, &amp; did heare them and propound queſtions vnto them, <hi>Luk.</hi> 2. And when hee
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:19449:39"/>
preached, his cuſtome was to goe into the Synagog vppon the Sabboth, and to reade and expound the Scriptures. <hi>Luk.</hi> 4, But let vs ſee what you alleage to prooue that he did not meane that men ſhould heare them.</p>
            <p>You demaunde, <hi>if God doo not in all places where he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth to heare true Prophets, forbid to heare falſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets?</hi> What then Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> how blinde are you? Do you not know that our Sauiour by mentioning their ſitting in <hi>Moſes</hi> Chayre, doth bind the auditors to receiue their doctrine ſo farre as it was the true doctrine of <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets? Hee doth heare the falſe Prophet which heareth and receiueth falſe doctrine. So farre as the Phariſies ſet foorth the truth, ſo farre they were to bee heard, and their Doctrine as our Sauiour willeth, was to bee followed. But men were to take heede of their Leuine, that is of their falſe doctrine and humane traditions. Our Sauiour doth not at all approoue their open wickednes, when hee willeth them to follow that true Doctrine which they ſhould deliuer out of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and not to follow their workes. The Prieſts and teachers ought indeede to be holy, but it hath fallen out farre otherwiſe, and that many times in Gods Church. And now if it were an abuſe that ſome of theſe Scribes and Phariſies which did teach, were not Leuites, but of ſome other Tribe, as <hi>Paul</hi> was of <hi>Benia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min:</hi> yet there were greater abuſes about the high Prieſt, &amp; the reſt and begun long before that time: &amp; yet the whole Church and our ſauiour himſelf ſo long as he did liue as a priuate man, frequented the Temple and publike, worſhip and heard them expound the Scriptures. Therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> albeit you exclaime in this ſorte, theſe blaſphemies doth this wicked man publiſh, his ordinarie and all the Cleargie in England ſuffer them to paſſe in print: yet neither you nor all the Dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſts and Annabaptiſts vnder heauen, ſhall euer be able with all your ſhifts to wring this place from vs, which indeede ouertur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all the chiefe grounds and principles of your ſect. Be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed therefore to oppoſe your ſelues ſo wickedly againſt the cleare doctrine of Chriſt, and ceaſe to imagine abſurdities, which are but from your blind miſtaking. Agayne we ſee that
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:19449:40"/>
our Sauiour healing a man that had the Leproſie, commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him, ſaying, goe ſhew thy ſelfe vnto the Prieſt, and offer that gift which <hi>Moſes</hi> hath commaunded for a teſtimony vnto them, <hi>Math.</hi> 8. 4. Alſo he ſendeth ten Leapers at once to ſhew themſelues to the Prieſts, <hi>Luk.</hi> 17. 14. which were alſo to offer according to the law. And this was not long before he ſuffered. You do very fondly imagine, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> if the Prieſts, the Scribes and Phariſies and Saduces, and the multitude which claue vnto them were the viſible Church, then were there two Churches, vnles we will denie that our Sauiour &amp; his Diſciples were the Church. For at y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> time they were all in the ſame viſible Church euen thoſe open wicked and the good. Our Sauiour doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them and layeth open their wickednes, to the end that men might beware and not be ſeduced and kept from truth by them. But why are they not caſt forth? The Prophets in olde time did ſharply reprehend the wicked of all ſorts in the Church, but they had not the ordinary power to execute the cenſure of excommunication, no more had our Sauiour himſelfe.</p>
            <p>There be diuers teſtimonies and examples of the holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which I alledged to proue this thing which you knitte vp ſhort, but in your other booke you deale in them at large. And becauſe Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> hath written ſtrongly and plentifully in theſe matters againſt the Annabaptiſts, and ſuch as moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedly did condemne the Churches in his time, you take vpon you to confute him, as if he were the author of theſe things, and you tearme vs his wretched diſciples. Whereas in very déede M. <hi>Caluine</hi> followeth but the ſteps of the auncient writers, <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> and the reſt agaynſt the Cathariſts and Donatiſts. And you lighting into their Tents, ſet very freſhly vpon the worke euen as a chiefe Captayne, to repayre and fortifie the ruines of that auncient Cathariſme and Donatiſme, and yet can bring nothing which they brought not.</p>
            <p>Touching the reformation by Princes, which compell their ſubiects that profeſſe Chriſt, and haue the ſeale of the couenant, to forſake Idolatrie, and to imbrace the holy word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, I haue ſpoken before: and therefore I come to the 17. page of your booke, where you write after this ſort: <hi>The next</hi>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:19449:40"/>
               <hi>ſhiftes theſe Balaamities haue for the aminiſtring vnto, and Communicating with, and retaining the prophane in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of their church: are certaine arguments drawne by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter Caluine, from Matth. 13. againſt the Annabaptiſts, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the church to a corne field, where the good ſeed, and the bad grow together, to a net, and in Matth. 3. To a floar where the corne and the chaffelye together.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In deed Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> theſe were ſpeciall places which the auncient Fathers ſtood vpon againſt the Donatiſts, and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Caluine</hi> againſt the Annabaptiſts, and which we in as great right vrge againſt you and your ſect. If we bee Balaa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites, then what was Maſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> what was <hi>Auguſtine</hi> and all the reſt? Againſt whome haue you powred foorth your railings? Take héede it be not againſt our Lord Ieſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, being againſt his expreſſe word: for let vs ſée how you can auoyde theſe places. Touching the parable of the ſéed, you op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (as you ſay) againſt Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> and his Diſciples, firſt the interpretation of our Sauiour himſelfe: who ſaith not that the field is the Church, but the field is the world. And ſo the good ſéed and the bad are together in the world, but not in the Church. And then you ſhew an abſurditie of flat contradic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the holy Scriptures which would follow, if we take it that the good ſéed and the bad ſhould grow together in the Church. The contradiction is this, there is power and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement giuen to the Church to caſt forth the open wicked, and here he bids let them alone. Therefore this let them alone, let them grow together vntil the harueſt, muſt néeds be expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded let them alone, and let them grow together in the world, but not in the Church.</p>
            <p>In déed your expoſition Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> is the very ſame which the Donatiſts made, and obſtinately ſtoode vpon. The field is the world, our Sauiour hath ſaid it, the truth hath ſaide it, accurſed be he that ſhal gaineſay it: but to gather from hence, that the good ſéed and the bad ſhal not be together in the church but in the world, is directly to ouerthrow the whole parable. For firſt, what is it which is reſembled or likened? The words are plaine, it is the Kingdome of Heauen. The Kingdome of
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:19449:41"/>
Heauen ſaith he is like, &amp;c. What is it which is here called the Kingdome of Heauen, is the world ſo called? Who dare ſay ſo? It is the Church, in which there is the Goſpell of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and in which Chriſt dooth raigne. If our Sauiour had ment to ſec forth, and to reſemble the ſtate of the world by the good ſéed and the bad mingled together (as he ſaith) the enemy did ſow the tares, <hi>ana meſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> tou ſitou,</hi> in the middeſt or among the wheate, and that they grew vp together, or to ſay looke how in a field good ſéede and bad grow together, ſo in the world good men and bad: it could not then be ſaide, the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen is like, but the ſtate of the world is like. Was it euer heard of, that a man would expound a parable, that is a ſimilitude, and exclude that which is reſembled by the ſimilitude? For if the good ſéed and the bad, ſowen and growing together in the field, do not reſemble and ſet forth the ſtate of the viſible church, while it is alſo in the field, that is to ſay in this world, mingled of good and bad men, ſhew what there is in the whole parable, whereunto the Kingdome of Heauen is likened. Moreouer in the expoſition of the parable our Sauiour ſaith, as the tares are gathered and burned, ſo ſhall it be in the end of this world, the ſonne of man ſhall ſend his Angels, which ſhall gather out of his Kingdome all offences, and thoſe which worke iniquitie, &amp;c. If they ſhall be gathered out of his Kingdome, which is his Church (peculiarly ſo called, though he be Lord of Heauen and earth) then are they vntill the end of the world in his Church. I doubt not Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> but that ſimple men, yea poore Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (looking vpon this parable, and conſidering what it is likened, and how Chriſt dooth expound it) ſhall bée able to ſée what a ſpirit of giddines God hath in iudgement caſt vpon yée, for the loftines of your mindes. And now for that abſurdity of flat cóntradiction in the Scriptures, which you imagine, if wee expound it that the good and the bad ſhall bee mingled in the church, ſo long as it is in the field. There is no ſuch thing, as I will ſhew by as great an abſurdity which will follow of y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ſenſe which you giue, for ſpeaking of the wicked in the Church, if he ſhould ſay let them alone, it would ouerthrow the cenſures Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall which are expreſſely commaunded: then ſpeaking
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:19449:41"/>
of the wicked in the world, and ſaying let them alone, let them grow together, leaſt ye pluck vp the wheat, it ſhould ouerthrow the power of Kings and rulers, in putting euil dooers to death, which is expreſſely commaunded: for I truſt Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> ye will not deny Chriſtian Kings to be one part of the ſeruants of the maſter of the houſe. Then whereas you reaſon thus, <hi>the power of excommunication which is giuen to the Church, and which the Church is commaunded to execute, may not be ouerthrowne: but if Chriſt will to let the tares grow in the Church, he forbiddeth to execute that power, and ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, therefore he doth not ſpeake of open wickednes in the Church, but in the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I will reaſon agaynſt your expoſition thus. The power which God hath giuen vnto the ciuill Magiſtrates to put mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therers and other wicked malefactors to death, is not to be ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne: but if Chriſt will men to let the wicked ones in the world alone, &amp; will haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> grow to the harueſt, leaſt in pluck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them vp they deſtroy the wheate, hee taketh away that po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer from the Magiſtrates. Therefore this parable muſt not bée taken of the good and the bad together in the world. And mark how he ſayth not, let them alone, becauſe it belongeth not vnto ye, but let them alone leaſt ye pluck vp the wheate. What then? ſhall we neither take it of the Church nor of the world, becauſe of an abſurditie which ſeemeth to followe on either ſide? Of the world indeed it cannot bee taken, as I haue ſhewed before, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he ſayth, not the world is like, but the kingdome of heauen is like, but of the Church it is ſayd, that as the good ſeede and the bad are ſowen and grow together vntill harueſt in the mans field, ſo the good and bad men are mixed in the Church ſo long as it remayneth in the world. How then for theſe words, let them alone, let them growe vnto the harueſt? It is plaine (if we will auoyd abſurdities on both ſides) that our Sauiour doth not here meddle either with the Ciuill or Eccleſiaſticall power, but as it is the manner in parables to vtter ſome ſayings which are onely to ſhew ſome poynt of doctrine, &amp; not to be taken ſtricktly according to the letter. As for example, when our Sauiour would ſhew in that place Luk. 16. which is partly a parable, that
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:19449:42"/>
ſuch as cannot be brought to repentance by hearing <hi>Moſes</hi> and the Prophets, will not repent if one ſhould riſe from the dead: to bring in this doctrine, the damned ſoule is ſayd to intreate <hi>Abraham</hi> that hee would ſend <hi>Lazarus</hi> vnto his fathers houſe to warne his brethren, leaſt they ſhould come into that place. Shall we think that damned ſoules haue ſuch a care that others may repent and be ſaued? Nay, as I ſayd, it is onely to bring in a doctrine. What is the doctrine then which our Sauiour doth bring in by theſe words, let them alone, let them grow together vnto the harueſt? This it is, that when the Chriſtian Princes haue done what they can in reforming the Church, and put the wicked malefactors to death: and when the cenſures eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call bee moſt diligently and wiſely executed, yet will there bee heapes of vngodly ones in the Church, and that ſeeing it cannot be auoyded, men are not to make Schiſmes, and ſo to rend vp the wheate, but meekly to expect the harueſt when the full ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhall be made. Be not therefore (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) ſo ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd, as by an imagined abſurditie, to ouerthrowe the doctrine of a parable ſo cleerely expreſſed.</p>
            <p>The next place to prooue that the open wicked ſhall alwayes be mixed with the good in the Church is the parable of the draw <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>et out of the ſame chapter. <hi>You ſay this is graunted to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of the planted Church.</hi> Who are they which graunted this? Indeed the Donatiſts granted this, and it is ſome gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes that you will graunt ſo much. For if in this parable the kingdome of heauen be the viſible Church, which is compared to the net which draweth together good and bad: why is not the kingdome of heauen in the former parable, alſo the Church, and ſo the eſtate therof likened while it is in the field, vnto the wheat and the tares growing together? You ſay the euil fiſhes are not open ſinners but hypocrites, and ſo ſayd the Donatiſts. And I meruaile you ſhewe no reaſon for it, ſeeing the diuell did ſuggeſt this friuolous ſhewe of reaſon vnto the Donatiſts, that hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crites are very fitly reſembled by fiſhes in the net vnder the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which the fiſher men cannot ſee vntill the net bee drawne to land. This I haue anſwered in my former booke. There is no doubt but that cloſe hypocrites which outwardly appeare holy,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:19449:42"/>
are one great part of thoſe euill fiſhes which the net of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell draweth together: but to exclude all the reſt, there is no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</p>
            <p>The place in <hi>Math.</hi> 3. He ſhall purge his floar and gather the wheate into his barne, but hee will burne the chaffe with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenchable fire, dooth manifeſtly ſhewe, that as the corne and chaffe for a time lye vppon the floar, ſo the good and the bad lye mingled together in the viſible Church. Here you make an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of your owne, and then take on grieuouſly that Chriſts Church ſhould be compared to ſuch a floar as the chaffe and the corne lye together. And aſke what the Church then differeth from the world? It is certaine that both the ciuill and eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall power ought to bee imployed with all diligence and care that may bee to purge the Church: that albeit the floar cannot be cleane rid of the chaffe, yet it may bee rid ſo farre as men are able. That is not the queſtion: but when theſe dueties of men haue been neglected, and that there he heapes of chaffe in which the graynes of corne doo lye couered, whether it bee not ſtill the viſible Church? It is a moſt cléere caſe that in the Church of Iſrael, which at that time was the viſible Church, there were very great heapes of chaffe, and very fewe graynes of good corne in compariſon of the whole multitude. <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> threatneth eternall iudgement vnto thoſe hypocrites, wicked and faithleſſe people, ſhewing that the place they held in the Church for a time ſhould nothing helpe, ſeeing the Lord will fanne them out like chaffe, which for a time lyeth with the corne, but defileth not the corne, nor cannot turne it into chaffe. You thinke you haue great hold that hee ſpeaketh of ſeparating the chaffe from the corne: but anſwere this one queſtion, was it not his floar, that is his viſible Church out of which he would purge the chaffe? Doth he make it his floar by purging it, or was it his floar be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it was purged? The words are cléere, hee ſhall purge his floar, &amp;c. whether the open wicked pollute the holy things of God, or the conſcience of the faithfull which doo communicate with them, I referre the reader to thoſe things which I haue noted betwéene the ancient Churches and the Donatiſts, where euery thing hath been as ſtrongly vrged by thoſe Donatiſts, as
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:19449:43"/>
you are able, or any of your ſect. Seeing then in your ſecond ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſation your grounds and reaſons are flat Donatiſme, &amp; that in your blind furie you condemne all Churches both of auncient time, and in theſe dayes, moſt deepely reuiling and rayling at all the moſt excellent inſtruments which God hath raiſed vp vnto his Church, what remayneth, but to warne ſimple men to take heed they bee not ſeduced by you? Thus much for the ſecond, now to the third accuſation.</p>
            <p>The third accuſation is, that we haue a falſe Antichriſtian miniſtrie impoſed, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N your former writings, where ye came to deale a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout our miniſtrie, ye were in a great diſpleaſure (hauing made ſo great a chalenge) for that I did intercept this buſines fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the hands of the learned, vnto whome (ye ſay) it did by many rights more neerely appertayne then vnto me. I made anſwere to this, that in very deede it is no reaſon, that ſuch as you ſhould be encoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred by men of great learning: becauſe in all your dooings, yee are ſo full of falſe accuſations, ſo raſh, ſo preſumptuouſly bold in powring foorth without any diſcretion, whatſoeuer lighteth into your brayn: ye are ſo miſerably ignorant, ſo full of foule errors, being altogether vnlearned (this onely excepted, that yee haue ſcraped ſome things out of other mens writings, which yet ye peruert) that all wiſe men, both of learned and vnlearned, doo playnely ſee, it is but mad frenſie, by which yee are led. For let the things which I haue noted out of theſe your laſt bookes witneſſe vnto all, I will not ſay the learned (for what ſhould they ſpend time about them) but to all the Artificers and huſband<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men which haue any ſound knowledge, whether I haue in this charged ye with more then is true.</p>
            <p>Ye would beare the Reader in hand, that the learned men doo abſtayne from dealing with ye, becauſe they know our cauſe is bad, and that it is better therefore it ſhould be raked vp, then ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare the worſe by the handling.</p>
            <p>Ye ſayd moreouer, that if I haue conſulted with my learned
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:19449:43"/>
Brethren, they would haue giuen me counſell not to write, but to deale in the pulpit, where it may bee without controulment: leaſt the fowlenes of things ſhould appeare.</p>
            <p>To one part of this I made anſwere, that whereas yee doo imagine that all the learned are afrayd ye would be too hard for them, if they ſhould deale with yee, and therefore they doo not nor dare not meddle, it is nothing ſo. But as one among the beaſts (ye know of whome it is ſayd) had gotten a Lyons ſkinne vpon him, and went about and frayed all the ſimpler beaſts: vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till one more ſubtill, whether he eſpied the long eares, or whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he heard him bray (which is nothing like the roaring of a Lion) made anſwere, that otherwiſe indeede, hee ſhould haue béene ſcared as well as the reſt. For you comming with a moſt terrible outcrie againſt our Church, ye wil néeds haue vs think the Lion roareth. Let not the Reader ſuppoſe that I ſpeake this vpon mine owne conceipt: for in the fourth page of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle of your other booke, which ye call <hi>A briefe diſcouery of the falſe Church,</hi> ye haue ſet it downe ſo your ſelues. Ye would not haue thoſe dreadfull things which ye denounce leſſe feared, becauſe they are pronounced by a frayle man: but would haue vs all know that the Lyon roareth, and that the Lyon roareth not in the Forreſt if no pray be preſent. Doubtles your voyce hath beene terrible, and eſpecially at the firſt you ſcared many of the ſimpler ſorte, which tooke it to bee the roaring of a Lyon: But ye muſt vnderſtand that the learned euen at the firſt did diſcerne the voyce not to be the roaring of a Lion, but the bray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of him that put on the Lyons ſkinne. Therfore ye are much deceiued in thinking they all feare and tremble at it. They ſee playnely that it is but mad frenſie, and ſo they diſdayne to deale with it. And for mine owne parte, if I did not ſee what hauock the Donatiſts made, how many the Annabaptiſts ſeduced, and how weake much of our people are, I ſhould count it great folly to giue you anie anſwere.</p>
            <p>And now, whereas I did require if there bee any ſpark of modeſtie left in ye, to make ſome colourable ſhew, that the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned would councell not to deale in theſe matters, which they knowe can not bee defended, but by the diſcuſſing will become
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:19449:44"/>
more odious: thus ye make anſwere. <hi>That theſe preachers had taken this courſe (ſay you) among themſelues, we know certaynely, by a letter that two of the chiefe of them ſent vnto vs, denying that conference which they had before promiſed, becauſe we denyed their Church and miniſtrie. After that, two of them being procured to our priſon, denied to deale with vs concerning thoſe exceptions we made agaynſt their church and miniſtrie, alleadging that they were forbidden by their brethren to deale with vs in thoſe matters. To be ſhort, what elſe can with any probabilitie be coniectured to bee the hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance of the firſt company of preachers, that at the firſt ſent vnto vs to know the cauſes of our diſlike, promiſing to aſſent, or to ſhew vnto vs the cauſes why they could not, that they v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the ſight of that little paper, (wherein we ſet downe vnto them the cauſes of our ſeparation from theſe pariſh aſſemblies, as alſo what we purpoſed in our owne aſſemblies) neuer as yet could be drawne to make any anſwere in writing or confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, if not that they perceiued, that they were neither able to defend their eſtate, neither yet had fayth to leaue it for feare of perſecution and danger.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Who can now doubt but that Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> and Maſter <hi>Greenewood</hi> be honeſt ſimple dealing men? Who can ſay they haue ſlaundred the learned, or that they haue vttered any thing raſhly, when they now affirme that they did for certainty know that the preachers had taken ſuch a courſe among themſelues, and alleadge ſuch proofe for the certaintie hereof, as no man néedeth to doubt of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> matter. For will any man bee ſo impudent as to lie, and to publiſh it to thoſe which do know he doth Iye? I haue heard Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> by ſuch as haue dealt with yee, that ye make no conſcience of lying, and nowe it falleth out ſo here: for one of thoſe which came to the priſon, comming to the fight of your booke, hath ſet downe in the margent that ye make a moſt ſhameles lie. It may be in this ye will ſtand vpon your Pantoffles, it is but your yea, and his nay. But for the letter you ſpeake of which the other two whome ye name, ſent vnto ye: I haue talked with them both, to knowe why they denied conference, and what they had written. They ſay they denied
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:19449:44"/>
conference with ye, onely becauſe yee denied them to be Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, to pray with them, and that ye denied all the preachers in the land to bee Chriſtians and all thoſe which ioyne with them: not hoping that ye could take any fruit by their writings which would not yeeld to receiue any fruite or comfort by their prayers. I take it Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> you haue the letter. If you haue it, ſhew it vnto ſome honeſt man that may ſpeake for you and defend ye, not to be paſt ſhame in forging ſuch a ſenſe. If ye haue it not, I can let ye haue the perfect copie of it, and will let any friend ye haue ſee it. They are ſo far off in the letter from giuing the leaſt ſuſpition that they doubt of our Church and miniſtrie, as that they pronounce it your heatheniſh opinion, whereby ye denie vs to be Chriſtians. What preachers ſent vnto ye I know not, but that they refrayned to haue conference with ye, perceiuing vpon the ſight of your little paper (as yee ſay) that they could not defend their eſtate, doe yee indeede think ſtill, that they tooke it to be the roaring of a Lyon? could they not diſcerne (thinke ye) betwéene <hi>rudere</hi> and <hi>rugire?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Your multitudes, and armies of wordes (being but vayne <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>anglings) I will paſſe by, and come directly to the ſubſtance of the matter. And becauſe our miniſtrie is ordayned by Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops (which is by one part of their gouernement) your third and fourth accuſation, ſhall bee handled ioyntly, as it were vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der one.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In page 104. Ye wonder (as ye ſay) that in this floriſhing eſtate of our Church, which ouerfloweth with ſo great lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, aboundeth with ſo many writers, that not one of them ſhould vndertake to proue the miniſtry of their Church di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly by the rules of Gods word, in their office, entrance, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, and maintenance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe may very well be ſome of thoſe ſwelling words of ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, which Saint Peter ſpeaketh of, for who (if he know not before the vaine inſolencie of Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> and his fellow) reading this wonder, would not iudge them to bee men very deepely read? Haue they not read ouer (thinke ye) all the lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned writers of this age, wondring that there is not one among them all, that hath vndertaken to proue our miniſtrie directly by
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:19449:45"/>
the rules of Gods word? Is it not pitty that there be no moe learned writers, that theſe men might ſearch them alſo, to haue this poynt handled? If you haue now done wondring Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> giue vs leaue a little to wonder. The Papiſts denying that the churches which haue reiected popery haue any miniſtry, and requiring proofe thereof, many learned writers, both of other Churches, and of our owne nation, haue vndertaken this matter, and haue ſo directly proued our miniſtry by the rules of Gods word, as that the Papiſts haue no cauſe to glorie. Now there be two things here which we may wonder at: the one how it ſhould be poſſible, that ſuch ſwelling inſolency could be found in the hearts of men groſely ignorant, as that hauing read al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt nothing, and vnderſtanding leſſe by ſundry degrees, yet o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly vaunt, as if they had read all, and could finde no ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. The other how men of ſo contrarie diſpoſition, ſhould vſe the very ſame weapon againſt the Church, for this is one wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon of the Papiſts, and now in your hands, <hi>Ye haue no mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrie of Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If the reader ſhal here thinke that I grate too hard vpon Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> who directeth his ſpéech but againſt the miniſtry of our Church: the matter is farre otherwiſe, as I will make it appeare: for firſt he denieth the miniſtry of all Churches in expreſſe words: <hi>affirming that there is no miniſtry in all Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, nor in all theſe knowne parts of the world.</hi> Secondly, we are to note, that although the reformed Churches doo differ, ſundry of them each from others, in the manner of the calling and ordination of miniſters, yet the defence which the learned writers doo make, is generally for the miniſtry of all thoſe Churches (as well for the miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as of others) which haue forſaken Antichriſt, and preach the Goſpell. Therefore Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> read all the learned wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which haue ſtood to maintaine againſt the Papiſts, that Maſter <hi>Luther,</hi> Maſter <hi>Caluine,</hi> Maſter <hi>Bucer,</hi> Martyre &amp; the reſt, were miniſters of Chriſt, and ſeeing ye will needs fight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God and his truth, try your ſtrength, and ſee how ye can gratefie the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in ouerthrowing that which all her learnedeſt patrons are not able to ſhake more then they be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:19449:45"/>
to ſhake or remoue a mountaine.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The miniſtry of our Church is not (you ſay) the miniſtry of the Goſpell, or the miniſtry of Chriſt, but the miniſtry of Antichriſt, comming in the life and power of the beaſt. Your reaſon is that we are the children of the Biſhops, &amp; the Biſhops are the creatures of the Pope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againſt this I did alleage, that the popiſh Biſhops haue their conſecration and power from the Pope, they ſweare obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience vnto him, to maintaine his dignity, religion, lawes, and ceremonies. And alſo with him doo exerciſe a power ouer the faith and conſcience of men. But the Biſhops of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> haue not their ordination, conſecration, or power from the Pope, but from our Church which hath renounced Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt. The Biſhops of <hi>England,</hi> acknowledge no ſubiection to the Pope, but by anoath, haue renounced his vſurped po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer and tyranny. The Biſhops of <hi>England</hi> are not ordayned to vphold and maintaine the religion or lawes of Antichriſt, but quite contrary they promiſe and profeſſe, to aduaunce the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell of Ieſus Chriſt, &amp;c. They vſurpe not a Lordſhip ouer the faith and conſcience of men.</p>
            <p>Let vs ſee now what ye bring againſt this, <hi>It helpeth not our Biſhops (ye ſay) any thing, that they haue broken their faith and Schiſmed from the Pope, &amp; renounced his yoake, euen his vſurped power and tyrannie, ſeeing they vſurpe and retaine (if not the ſame) yet as Antichriſtian and enormous a power as the Pope, exerciſing their authoritie and commaundements contrary vnto, and aboue all lawes, both of God and of their prince, page 113.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be thus our caſe is hard: but Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi> remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber the old Prouerb, a lier needeth to haue a good memorie, for in page 181. and 182, you haue quite forgotten what ye had ſet downe here, for there yee doo affirme, <hi>that the Biſhops which died for the Goſpell were godly bleſſed Martyres, of whoſe happie and bleſſed eſtate ye doo not doubt. Your reaſon is, for that they were not conuinced, but did exerciſe that power ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norantly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray ye tell me Maſter <hi>Barrowe,</hi> could they bee godly and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:19449:46"/>
had but broken their faith and Schiſmed from the Pope? Could they be godly men, exerciſing as Antichriſtian and enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous a power as the Pope? Yea could they bee true thriſtians, exerciſing their commaundementes and power, contrary vnto, and aboue all lawes both of God and man? Or could ignorance excuſe them in theſe matters? Then tell vs why the Pope might not be a good Chriſtian alſo, before he was conuinced? Which way dooth the whéele turne now Maſter <hi>Barrow?</hi> Ye can neuer be able to bring both ends together in theſe, yee muſt either condemne thoſe Martyrs, or elſe make the gouernement by Biſhops, not ſuch as you ſet it forth: well let vs procéede. Here now we muſt lay open what power the Pope dooth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, and what power the Biſhops in our Church doo exerciſe, to ſée if it be the ſame, or the like. Alſo whether the Biſhops doo exerciſe any power, but that which Chriſt hath giuen to his Church, to be exerciſed by men, that is either by Biſhops, or Preſbyteries. Touching the Pope, he hath vſurped power o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer the whole word of God, affirming that the holy ſcriptures haue no authority (as they ſay vnto vs) no certainty for the ſenſe, no life, but as hee doth giue vnto them. And for this cauſe hee doth take vpon him to expound them as he will, contrary to the grammer ſenſe. Hee doth take vpon him to diſpenſe with all, and to abrogate expreſſe lawes of God. And further he taketh vpon him to make lawes of his owne, to bind the fayth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience of all men, euen as the articles of our fayth doo bind, or the expreſſe doctrine of the ſacred Scriptures. Hee doth vſurp in ſundry things of ſo high nature, apperteming peculiarly to God, as that he ſheweth himſelfe as God.</p>
            <p>The power which the Byſhops of our Church do exerciſe, is firſt, in examining, appro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uing and ordaining miniſters and authoriſing them to preach the Goſpell. Secondly, it is in this, that they are to ſée the orders of the Church, for the publick ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration duly obſerued, and ſo they haue power to excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate, ſuſpend and depriue, &amp;c. ſuch as ſhall tranſgreſſe ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther againſt doctrine, order, or in manners. Touching lawes, they haue not power to make any one, not euen in things méete indiff rent, neither haue they power to abrogate, or to take a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:19449:46"/>
any one that is made, and by the publick authority of our Church eſtabliſhed: they can giue no commaundements of their owne. That Chriſt hath giuen power to ordaine mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and to execute the cenſures Eccleſiaſticall, you doo not call into queſtion: the controuerſie is but, by whome this pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhould bee executed, whether by Biſhops or by Preſbyters. If there be an error in the execution of it by Biſhops, or if there be a fault in the execution by Elders, this fault or error dooth not deſtroy the power it ſelfe, nor yet maketh it Antichriſtian, as ruling ouer the faith and conſcience.</p>
            <p>I knowe Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> that ye will here take great excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſay that the chiefe thing is yet behind. For as ye charge the preſbyteries moſt heynouſly, in that they take vpon them to decree and ordayne Canons and conſtitutions, vnto which they inioyne obedience in the people: ſo the Biſhops execute the lawes and Canons which haue been ordeyned by men (though not by themſelues) the matter is all one. Is not this to exerciſe Lordſhip and dominion ouer mens faith and conſcience? About this then muſt be our ſpeciall queſtion, whether Chriſt hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen ſuch a power vnto the Church, as to make lawes or Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons in externall matters, which wee call things indifferent? And whether the vrging men to kéepe them, be not to take away Chriſtian libertie, and ſo to rule ouer the faith and conſcience? I knowe this queſtion is hard to bee diſcuſſed, to make euery ſimple man vnderſtand the matter. You (Maſter Barrow and Maſter <hi>Greenwood</hi>) are moſt blind in it. I wiſh the reader to obſerue, becauſe it is one maine rocke vpon which ye are runne. And crye out what ye can, that I like a marked ſeruant of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt, like a graceles man, that hath his conſcience ſeared with a hot Iron, doo change yee wrongfully: yet it ſhall bee euident, that by ſeeking an Annabaptiſticall freedome, ye do abridge the power of the Chriſtian Magiſtrate, and of the Church.</p>
            <p>To come therefore vnto the matter: that which S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth muſt firſt ſtand ſure, namely, <hi>That there is one lawgiuer which is able to ſaue and to deſtroy. <hi>Iam. 4. verſ. 12.</hi>
               </hi> Hereupon it is moſt ſure that God alone hath Lordſhip ouer the conſcience of man to binde the faith and conſcience. For looke what God hath
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:19449:47"/>
by his lawe commaunded to bee done, it is good, it is holie: no King, nor the whole Church can make any part of it euill, or commaund it not to be done. Looke what God hath forbidden to be done, that ſame is euill and vnholy; no King, nor yet the whole Church can make it good and holy, or command it to bee done. I ſay further, that the law of God is ſo abſolutely perfect, that there is no righteouſnes for men, but it is therein contey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned: neyther is there any vnrighteouſnes, but it is therein for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden. Wherefore they which take vpon them to make lawes to binde the conſcience eyther by abrogating or by adding, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit moſt high and blaſphemous ſacriledge, of which the whole poperie is to be condemued. But now there are certayne middle actions, and things, which we call indifferent, becauſe if we ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply reſpect them in themſelues, or in their owne nature, they bee neither good nor euill. In theſe conſiſteth one part of Chriſtian libertie to vſe or not to vſe with knowledge and diſcretion. Now if we reſpect y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very nature of theſe things, no Prince or church can change it, as to make them to become neceſſarily good, or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily euill in themſelues to the conſcience. And therefore, <hi>touch not, taſt not, handle not, <hi>Coloſſ. 2. verſ. 21.</hi>
               </hi> making the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward indifferent things vncleane to the conſcience, is to vſurpe an Antichriſtian power ouer the conſcience euen agaynſt God. Alſo to make thoſe externall things to be of neceſſitie to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, is to lay a yoake of bondage: and agaynſt this wee are willed <hi>to ſtand faſt in the freedome wherewith Chriſt hath made vs free. <hi>Gal 5. verſ. 1.</hi>
               </hi> Hetherto (Maſter <hi>Barrow</hi>) I thinke yée will agree with me. But now touching the externall vſe of theſe things, either for Princes to make politick lawes to commaund the vſe or to reſtraine the vſe of them, or for the Church to make Cannons and conſtitutions to commaund or reſtrayne the vſe as ſhall ſerue for order and comelines, therein lieth our diſagree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and therein ye pleade for your Annabaptiſticall freedome, and confuſion, I meane that ataxia, or ouerthrowe of all order.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, ye call it a ſubtill diſtinction which Maſter Caluine vſeth, of the externall or ciuill Court, and the Court of conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, in your diſcouerie pag. 88. And you ſay Maſter Caluine hauing very truely ſet downe, that it is heinous preſumption in</hi>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:19449:47"/>
               <hi>any mortall man to reſtrayne or make lawes of ſuch things as the Lord hath left in libertie: hee ſtraight way (leaſt he ſhould keepe backe ciuill Magiſtrates from receiuing the Goſpell) in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenteth a politick diſtinction, betwixt the ciuill court, and the court of conſcience: ſaying, that this outward court reſpecteth men onely, and bindeth not the conſcience of the doer, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther concerneth matters belonging vnto God, and therefore bindeth the conſcience. Thus hath he both loſt and entangled himſelfe, and vtterly ouerthrowne all his former doctrine. pag. 93. In pag. 247. of this booke agaynſt me, Maſter Greenwood ſayth, that Maſter Caluin would but diuide the ſoule and the bodie in ciuill cauſes, but I would goe a note further.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus farre be your wordes. How ſhall Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> doo that is thus ſet vpon by ſuch great diuines, which haue ſo pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued him that he hath loſt himſelfe, and they haue ſnared him in his owne wordes? Alas poore ſoules, I cannot but lament with pitie to ſee your blindenes, for I knowe this is of meere ignorance, that ye cannot vnderſtand Maſter <hi>Caluine</hi> in a doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine which yet is cleare by the Scriptures. Ye ſay he inuented this politique diſtinction of the ciuill court and the court of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, leaſt he ſhould keepe Princes back from the Goſpell. Then by your owne words it doth follow, that if it be prooued that Princes haue power in ſuch matters to make lawes, ye do fouly abridge their ſacred power by denying it. And for that Maſter <hi>Greenwood</hi> ſaith I go a note further then M. <hi>Caluine,</hi> it is his ignorance: for let him reade well the fourth booke of his inſtitutions, and he ſhall finde hee holdeth this diſtinction not onely in ciuill cauſes, but in eccleſiaſticall canons. And now to the matter. I would I were able though in neuer ſo rude ſpeech, to lay it ſo open as that a childe might vnderſtand. I will doe the beſt I can: and I will come vnto it by degrees. Ye cannot ſee how there ſhould be ſuch a diſtinction of an externall action to reſpect men, and not to binde the conſcience before God: Mark well and ſee. There bee ſundry ſortes of cloath of ſundry colours, and there be ſundry faſhions of garments. I am a miniſter of the Goſpell, I haue by mee a yelow gowne, a gréene hat, white hoſe, a tawny coate, I doo for ſome néede
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:19449:48"/>
ſecretly where no man ſeeth me, vſe them: my conſcience is not polluted by them, I ſinne not. But now I come with theſe garments into the publique aſſemblie, I ſinne grieuouſly. What is the reaſon of this? It is becauſe the garments them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, the colours or faſhions which were before God to the conſcieuce of man indifferent, are now altered and become not indifferent to the conſcience before God? In no wiſe. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twéene God and the conſcience, they remayne as they did. But now the whole matter lyeth in this: it is vncomely and offenſiue before men. Who cannot here ſee the diſtinction betweene the ciuill courte, that is for the action before men: and the court of conſcience before God? Will ye ſay becauſe it is euill for a man to doo thus before men, therefore it is euill to his conſcience before God, euen for the very dooing, not reſpecting men? Might I not alleadge a thouſand things of this nature, which I may doo and no ſinne betwéene God and my conſcience, but the ſinne commeth by the ſight and view of men? Nowe when the ſight and view of men doth reſtraine me from dooing them openly, the fréedome of my conſcience in them is not taken away before God, or my conſcience is not bound by them before God: but I am reſtrayned in the externall vſe of them before men, becauſe they be not expedient; they be lawfull, but not comely. We ſee how Saint Paul ſpeaketh about this matter, 1, <hi>Cor. 10 ver. 23. 24. <hi>All things are lawfull for me, but all things are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedient: all things are lawfull, but all things doo not edifie.</hi>
               </hi> This is meant onely of things indifferent, for all which are in their owne nature euil, be vnlawfull, and all things ſimply good are expedient: and doo edifie. Then we ſée by this there are things which are lawful vnto our conſcience before God, and in which our concſience retayneth ſtill her fréedome before God, euen when we are reſtrayned the outward vſe before men. This we may ſée further in the ſame Chapter, <hi>eate what is ſet before ye, asking no queſtion for conſcience. But if any ſay this was offered to Idoles, eate not of it for conſcience. Conſcience I ſay, not thine, but of that other.</hi> When he ſayth not thine, doth hee not ſhew his conſcieuce remayneth free before God, euen when he is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrayned before men? And when he ſayth, <hi>All things are lawfull,</hi>
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:19449:48"/>
               <hi>but I will not be brought vnder the power of any thing:</hi> 1. <hi>Cor. 6. verſ. 12.</hi> doth he not ſhew it is ſome bondage, if a man haue not freedome to refrayne the vſe of a thing lawfull? This is one ſteppe towards our matter: But what is this for making lawes either politique or eccleſiaſticall to inioyne men to doo that which God hath left free, or to reſtrayn the vſe of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures which hee hath graunted libertie to vſe? This is your mayne reaſon Maſter <hi>Barrow.</hi> I haue already ſhewed that he which ſhall enioyne or reſtrayne, to lay it vpon the conſcience before God, committeth high ſacriledge: But the vſe of things may be enioyned or reſtrayned in reſpect of men, as ſhall bee profitable or vnprofitable, comely, or vncomely, &amp;c. A good part of a kingdome doth conſiſt of Cappers. The people are giuen all to weare Hats, and by this meanes thoſe ſubiects doo fall into pouertie. The Prince maketh a law, that all his ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects ſhall at certaine times not weare Hats, but Capps. If the ſubiect ſhall now ſtand vp &amp; ſay, to weare an Hat or a Cappe is frée before God, and ſéeing God hath giuen mee fréedome of conſcience to vſe or not to vſe, no mortall creature hath power to binde my conſcience. Will not the Prince make anſwere, thou fooliſh man, I doo not binde thy conſcience in the thing before God, but I enioyne it as a thing expedient and profita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to my common wealth? It is free for a man to eate any kinde of meate. The Prince doth ſee it profitable that ſome kindes of meate ſhould be ſpared, and therfore doth make a law that at ſome times men ſhall abſtayne from the ſame. The Subiects ſhall make aunſwere, GOD hath giuen vs frée<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of conſcience to eate, no power can binde our conſcience from it, GOD hath made it lawfull and frée. Will not the Prince make anſwere and ſay: ye Annabaptiſts doo ye not knowe that there bee many things lawfull and frée to the conſcience before God, which yet are not expedient among men? I doo not reſtrayne ye to take away the freedome of your con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience in it before God: but it is profitable to my kingdome. It is free for a man that hath grounds to ſowe or to graze: but if men be giuen wholly to grazing, and corne waxe deare, and the Prince maketh a law that whoſoeuer occupieth ſuch a quantitie
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:19449:49"/>
of ground, ſhall plow thus many acres, doth he now binde the conſcience, or onely ſeeke the publike profite?</p>
            <p>There he thouſands of ſuch like matters Maſter <hi>Barrow:</hi> and therefore conſider how foully ye doo abridge the power of Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to the ouerthrowe of Common wealths, in denying them authoritie to make permanent lawes, in things indifferent. But ye make one obiection more which is of ſome ſhewe: and that is that princes lawes are to be obeyed for conſcience: out of which a man may reaſon thus: ſeeing none can make lawes to binde the conſcience but God: and no lawe but in things good or euill can binde the conſcience, and not in things indifferent, for that were to binde where God hath left free: therefore Princes haue no power to make lawes in things indifferent. To anſwer this in ſuch ſort as a ſimple man may ſee the falſehood of it, is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what hard: but I will doo the beſt I can. I ſay therefore I am bound for conſcience to obey the Princes lawes, and yet the Princes lawes of themſelues, doo not binde my conſcience. It is an honeſt, a good, and profitable thing, when the Prince maketh a lawe and reſtrayneth the vſe of ſome things outwardly, which the conſcience hath freedome in inwardly before God, when it is for a publike good. Now I am bound to further a publike good, it is a great ſinne to ſhewe contempt agaynſt the Prince whom God commandeth me to obey: in theſe reſpects then I am bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d euen for couſcience to keep the lawes. The nature of the things indifferent is not altered before God vnto my conſcience by that reſtraint of lawe: neither yet the vſe is taken from me, when and where it may bee without contempt of my Prince, without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to men, and without hindring a publike good or commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie. They that ſpeake in words of Arte, doo ſay that Princes lawes doo not binde the conſcience <hi>haplôs,</hi> but <hi>cata ti:</hi> not ſimply by themſelues, but for ſome reſpect, or by ſomewhat which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth as a <hi>medium:</hi> which is as I haue before ſhewed. Take an example, put caſe ſome dying of clothes ſhould be harmefull to the Common wealth, as to dye in blewe: I am a Dyer, this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraynt doth not make the very dying in blew it ſelfe vncleane to my conſcience before God, and ſo binde my conſcience: but if I dye in blew contemning the power, &amp; ſo giue a publike offence,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:19449:49"/>
and hinder a common profite, I doo ſinne, God doth forbid theſe things, and they doo binde the conſcience.</p>
            <p>Now to come to the lawes Eccleſiaſticall, which M. <hi>Green<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wood</hi> ſayth is to goe a note further. The Church (as in our Countrey the Prince, the Nobilitie, and Commons aſſembled in Parliament) doo agree vpon ſome lawes in things indifferent for comelines and order, and edification in Gods worſhip: as in ſome other places the Preſbyteries, with the conſent of the chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Magiſtrates. This (ſay you) is to binde the conſcience. Well, let vs ſee your reaſons. If (ſay you) they binde not the conſcience, why ſhould men be excommunicate and deliuered vp to Satan, for violating ſuch ceremonies and orders as bind not the conſcience? This ſeemeth vnto you a thing moſt abſurd: but marke a little. The Princes lawes (as I haue ſhewed) doo not bind the conſcience, but yet he that with contempt of the Prince, to a publike euill example, and harme of the Common wealth doth breake the lawes, is guiltie of great ſinne, and if he ſtand in it worthie to be excommunicate. Euen ſo hee that violateth a lawfull rule or ceremonie of the Church in matters indifferent, which are not layd vpon him to bind his conſcience before God, but for order and comelines before men, though his conſcience touching the things themſelues is not bound before God, yet in ſhewing any contempt agaynſt y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> publike authoritie of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> church, &amp; in giuing an offence, by bringing in vncomelines or diſorder, he ſinneth, &amp; if he perſiſt obſtinatly is to be excommunicate. Tel me M. <hi>Greenwood,</hi> is it not a thing betweene God and a mans conſcience free to weare a gowne of greene cloath, were it not in regard of comelines among men? The Church then taketh or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der that no Miniſter ſhall come into the publike aſſemblie to preach in a green gown, &amp; he doth it; is he not to be reproued as for a great ſinne, &amp; if he ſtand obſtinatly in it to be caſt forth? But you ſay all theſe things muſt be left to the diſcretion of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter. So ye may alſo take away the power of making lawes in matters ſimply euil: for euery man hath not loue or care. And now whereas I haue ſhewed by y<hi rend="sup">•</hi> example of the holy Apoſtles <hi>Act.</hi> 15. who decreed that the Gentiles ſhould abſtaine from bloud and from ſtrangled, that the Church hath power to decrée in things indifferent, orders for edification: let vs ſee what a lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned anſwer you (M. <hi>Greenwood</hi>) haue found out. Firſt, you ſay
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:19449:50"/>
I haue ouerthrowne my ſelfe by ſetting downe that the holy Ghoſt and the Apoſtles did this, becauſe theſe were the maſter builders, and were to make lawes, &amp;c. Alas poore man, doth the holy Ghoſt euer make law or the Apoſtles in things indifferent, as eating blood or ſtrangled, to change the nature of the things, or to binde a mans conſcience before God, ſo that he might not ſecretly where it might neuer be knowne to the weake Iewes? Then ye ſee there may bee lawes made (the holy Ghoſt by the rules of the Scriptures guiding the Paſtors) in things indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, which binde not the conſcience. But (ſay you) they doo not inioyne it as a lawe, but tell them they ſhall do well if they ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue theſe things, by no neceſſitie inforced, pag. 251. Then it ſeemeth they might haue eate bloud and ſtrangled and giuen of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence to the weake Iewes and not haue done euill. That which ſeemeth good to the holy Ghoſt for them to obſerue, they may if it ſeeme not good to them, not obſerue. How abſurd is this? And if ye mark well what S. <hi>Iames</hi> ſayth, <hi>Act. 21. verſ. 25.</hi> you ſhall ſee it was not left arbytrarie, ſo long as there might offence growe thereby. Well, if the Church then haue power to make ſuch decrees to auoyd publike offence and diſorder; what if the Church erre and appoynt ſome orders and Ceremonies which are hurtfull? This error and fault of the Church is not in that high offence of binding the conſcience, which indeede is Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian, but in miſſing what is moſt comely, moſt without of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, and fitteſt for edification. The Church of Chriſt is ſo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious a thing, and the ſoules of men to bee regarded with ſuch sender compaſſion, that all Chriſtian gouernours and guides ought to be carefull, not onely, not to lay any yoke vppon the conſcience, but euen to redreſſe the leaſt error that may breede or worke any harme touching comelines and order. To ende this poynt, Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> vntill you can ſhewe wherein any power is vſurped and exerciſed ouer the faith and conſcience, wee muſt needes take all that ye haue here ſet downe, to be but your la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſh ſpeech.</p>
            <p>Now touching thoſe reaſons which I brought to proue the miniſtry of our Churches, to be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> miniſtry of Chriſt. The firſt is this, <hi>they haue the calling of the Church.</hi> What ſound ſtuffe ye haue brought to warrant your moſt vngodly preſumption, in condemning the Church of <hi>England,</hi> as alſo al Churches in Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:19449:50"/>
let the reader iudge. Alſo that the Churches doo in ſome things differ about the manner of calling and ordaining miniſters, how you or any other by this can proue all to be void, would be ſeene.</p>
            <p>Then next the miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> is the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of reconſiliation: bringing no doctrine, but the doctrine of the holy Scriptures. Here ye cauill fooliſhly, that although they exerciſe an office, yet they hauing no true calling, doo it but as priuate men. <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Caluine</hi> and all the reſt which haue preached the Goſpell in theſe times, ye confeſſe in ſome ſmall meaſure, according to that little which they did ſee (nothing comparable to that you haue attained) haue vttered the truth: but yet as priuate men. Here beſides your wicked barking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the miniſtry of all Churches, which God hath ratified: your ignorance is to be noted in this, that you doo not know, that if a man enter not rightly into a publick office, yet the office it ſelfe is not deſtroyed: as if a King haue but vſurped the crown, yet he is a King while he be depoſed. It is more then fooliſh that ye ſay, we haue a leiturgy or preſcript forme of praier, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we bring other doctrine beſides the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the miniſtry of the Church of <hi>England</hi> dooth bring men to faith, there being ioyned with it the effectual power and bleſſing of the holy Ghoſt, &amp;c. In anſwering this Maſter <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row,</hi> yee fall into your former ſtincking puddle, into which yée draw many a raſh ignorant man. I meane ye vtterly deny with the vngodly Swinckfeldians, all the whole efficacy, power and bleſſing, which God hath annexed vnto the miniſtry of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell. Here is a great patch ſet on to help the Papiſts, how by this alſo ye ſay, they may reaſon to proue their miniſtry and Church to be ſuch, as they that ſeparate themſelues muſt néeds be Schiſmatikes. Why Maſter <hi>Barrow,</hi> do you not know that as God made a promiſe to his Church to the end of the world, and hath giuen gifts &amp; a miniſtry, to continue euen to the worlds end, to build it, for Saint <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith, <hi>this miniſtry is giuen, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till we all meete together in the vnity of faith, which cannot bee, vntill the laſt day, that the whole number be accompliſhed. <hi>Epheſ. 4. 13.</hi>
               </hi> So hee hath alwaies reſerued not only ſome miniſtry in the popery, but alſo in all times ſome godly miniſters? How little help this bringeth to the Papiſts, or all thoſe ſound points
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:19449:51"/>
or doctrine that remained and do remaine among them to proue that the Churches which haue forſaken them are but Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, or that the Churches ſhould not caſt foorth the vſurped power of Antichriſt, I thinke children might be made to ſée and vnderſtand, for although they hold ſundry points of the faith, yet they quite ſubuert the holy faith. And whereas the Apoſtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip and miniſtry of Saint <hi>Paule</hi> being called into queſtion, he vſeth this reaſon vnto thoſe which had receaued the faith and power of the holy Ghoſt by his miniſtry, <hi>If I be not an Apostle vnto others, yet am I vnto you:</hi> I ſaid the ſame is to be made the defence of the miniſtry of the Churches at this day, vnto all ſuch as by the publick preaching of the word, and adminiſtration of the Sacraments are called vnto an aſſured faith and comfort in God, and vnto vnfeined repentance. For let all theſe iudge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther there be no efficacy &amp; power, in the publick adminiſtratio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the word and Sacraments, more then from the mouth of any priuat perſon. Vnto this you anſwer is too foule and beaſtly: for ye ſay it w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l fit the Papiſts againſt vs: and then I ſay it might fit the falſe Apoſtles againſt S. <hi>Paule.</hi> For if the Papiſts can or may as well ſay, though wee bee no miniſters of Chriſt vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet vnto you that féele the comfort and power of our doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine and ioy in it, we are miniſters of Chriſt. Then might the falſe Apoſtles in like manner haue riſen vp againſt S. <hi>Paul,</hi> and ſpoken the ſame vnto thoſe which delighted to heare them. Is there no difference betwéene that power of the Goſpell, that aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of faith, of peace and ioy in the holy Ghoſt, and of vnfained feare of God, and repentance which it worketh: and that blinde zeale, and comfort which hereticks and Papiſts haue in falſe doctrine and ſuperſtition? Will ye confound all? When ye pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce that there is no ſuch faith nor repentance, nor ioy in the holy Ghoſt, nor peace of conſcience wrought in the hearts of any by the miniſtry of our Church: how far aboue the clouds doth your ſwelling blind pride, lift vp her hands? Let al ſuch as haue felt the effectual calling of God, beare witnes in this matter.</p>
            <p>In the fourth, I alleadged that the Martyrs which ſuffered in the dayes of Quéene <hi>Marie,</hi> were moued and brought to fayth &amp; repentance, at the preaching of Maſter <hi>Latimer, Taylor, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, Bradford,</hi> and others. Your replie is, <hi>that this reaſon ſtandeth vpon popiſh and Annabaptiſticall grounds. For po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:19449:51"/>
               <hi>don alleadge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> as<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> many martyrs his predeceſſors</hi> Let me then aſke this queſtion? when it is confeſſed that they were holy martyrs, &amp; died for the true faith, will it not follow, if the Pope could prooue that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had held ſtill that holy fayth, that it ſhould bee the true Church? We hold the ſame fayth with the holy Martyrs. <hi>The motions ye ſay at our preachings are but the illuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of Sathan,</hi> and this is the cauſe that you account the reaſon to be Annabap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſticall. God is highly to be bleſſed, who hath ſo ratified the effectual power of the miniſtrie of his word in the hearts of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thouſands, both: in this land and in other countries with ſuch aſſurance and conſtancie of faith, that the whole power of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> out of the mouthes of papiſts, Annabaptiſts, Schiſmatiks, and frantick perſons, is not able to bring it into doubt. Laſtly, I did aduiſe men to be ſomewhat moued with the iudgement of other Churches. This (you ſay) <hi>is an old popiſh reaſon.</hi> M. <hi>Barrow</hi> it is not popiſh at all vnto ſuch as ſhall conſider that y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churches with theſe principal inſtruments which God rayſeth vp as lights, doo diſcuſſe matters by the Scriptures: men are to ſeeke for the truth at their handes. But I muſt tell yee it is the trick of all ranck heretikes and ſchiſmaticks to deſpiſe the iudgement of the Churches. Shall we think that a few igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant raſh men haue receiued ſuch light from God, as al the moſt noble inſtruments rayſed vp, haue not? Thus ye haue anſwered no one reaſon which I brought, but only with vaine, yea more then vayne cauills.</p>
            <p>The foule reproachfull ſpeeches, which yee vſe to deface all the miniſters of Chriſts Goſpell, both of other Churches, &amp; of the Church of England, are ſo many, and that in ſundry pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of your bookes, but ſpecially in your Diſcouery, from pag. 140. vnto pag. 187. that hee that will ſearch all that is written of the Cathariſts, the Donatiſts &amp; Annabaptiſts, and ſundry hereticks, ſhall not be able to finde the like, for the ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous preſumption, &amp; prowd contempt. The preaching of the Goſpel it ſelle, in our church ye do moſt prophanely blaſpheme, in ſaying, that ther with, as with a goodly embrodered couerlet and fine ſhéets of <hi>Egipt,</hi> we couer <hi>Ieſabels</hi> bed, &amp; hide al our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s. When ye ſay it as a ſweet whiſtle &amp; as a charme, yea when ye tearme it the whores ſcarfes to couer her ſhame, pag.
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:19449:52"/>
141<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Alſo wher as in many places of this land, but chiefly when the Spaniards came to inuade, there were faſts, &amp; the word of God preached in ſome places by two, in ſome by 3. miniſters: this ye call a ſtage play. pag. 97. Ye ſay ye are no Donatiſts nor Schiſmaticks, &amp; out of that which I haue written to ſhewe that ye are full Donatiſts, ye gather ſundry diſſimilitudes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt your ſelues and them. Ye might perhaps by diligence finde out ſome other things in which ye are not like them: as it may be they did weare blew caps, or gréene cloaks, which ye doe not. The truth is you do agrée with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the ſum &amp; ſubſtance of all y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> fowleſt things, which ye cannot denie: at leaſt if ye come behinde them in any one poynt, ye are before them in two other for it. To follow ye in all points wher in ye erre tither with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or with ſome other as wicked, would be ouer tedious: onely I note theſe and ſet them downe together.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt that ye do moſt preſumptuouſly againſt the expreſſe rules of Gods word, intrude your ſelues into the Lords office, in taking vpon ye to condemne the whole Church of <hi>England,</hi> as ſeparated from Chriſt, refut page 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That ye condemne al the Churches in Europe which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe the Goſpell, that their people are but heapes of prophane men. diſe. page 33. That their worſhip is blaſphemous Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie, in as much as they haue leiturgies, which is (as ye ſay) to haue another Goſpell, another Teſtament, Refut. page 244. That there is no miniſtry of the Goſpel in al Europ, Diſc. page 104. that the gouernement of al Churches is falſe and wicked, Refut. page 74. 75. Diſcou. page 189. 190.</p>
            <p n="3">3 That ye confound errors and hereſies, as to make all errors, hereſies being conuinced to his conſcience that erreth &amp; held, and to make none to be hereſies, vnles he be conuinced that er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, Refu. page. 24.</p>
            <p n="4">4 That with <hi>Nouatus</hi> the wicked heretick, ye take away all hope of ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe which offend of knowledge willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, in as much as ye make euery obſtinate perſiſting in the leaſt error, to ſeparate fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the faith &amp; Communion of Chriſt pa. 24.</p>
            <p n="5">5 That ye deny the diſtinction of errors fundamentall and not fund amentall, calling it popiſh. Refut. page 26.</p>
            <p n="6">6 That yee iudge of the whole Church to bee conuinced in conſcience as of one man, page 24.</p>
            <p n="7">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:19449:52"/>7 That ye hold it a due conuincing, not onely of particular perſons, but alſo of whole Churches, and ſuch as doth caſt them forth as heathen, ſo ſoone as any priuat man dooth reproue the leaſt error, &amp; they forthwith do not reforme the ſame. page 24.</p>
            <p n="8">8 That ye condemne al without exception, both learned and vnlearned, men and wemen young and old, which profeſſe the Goſpell in publick aſſemblies, vpon falſe accuſations, without admonition, &amp; in matters wherein if there be errors, yet excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent godly men haue erred in them finally, euen by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wne confeſsion. Refut. page 180.</p>
            <p n="9">9 That ye ſay the beſt part of the booke of common praier is no better then a peece of ſwines fleſh, and abomination to the Lord. Refut page 48.</p>
            <p n="10">10 That ye ſay the greateſt miniſter hath no more power to binde or looſe the leaſt member, then the ſaid member hath to binde or looſe him: and ſo with the Swinckfeldians, deſtroy the whole power of the miniſtry. page 37.</p>
            <p n="11">11 That ye ſpeake ſo prophanely of ſinging of Pſalmes, and ſo diſhonorably of Chriſtian people. Diſcou. page 180.</p>
            <p n="12">12 That moſt offenſiuely and prophanely, ye tearme the ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles of our faith, our forged patcherie. Diſcou. page 76.</p>
            <p n="13">13 That ye deny men are to ioyne in that worſhip, where a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny errors whatſoeuer doo appeare, and are not reformed, and ſo open a moſt wide gap vnto all Schiſmes. Refut page 27.</p>
            <p n="14">14 That you are ſo groſly ignorant how the falſe Apoſtles vrged circumciſion, and ſo from the words of S. <hi>Paule</hi> to the <hi>Galathians</hi> affirme that paying tithes, or the obſeruing any times as it is in our church, is an error fundame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tal. Refut. pa. 36</p>
            <p n="15">15. That ye iudge them to be no true Churches which haue not excommunication. pag. 54. 73.</p>
            <p n="16">16 That ye denie baptiſme to the children of open ſinners, which yet remayne in the Church. Refut. pag. 58. 59.</p>
            <p n="17">17 That ye make the ſtablenes of Gods couenant towards his Church to depend vpon the works of men. Refut. pag. 60.</p>
            <p n="18">18 That ye hold circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g the ten tribes, or in Iuda in time of Idolatrie, was no true ſeale of the couenant, &amp; yet ye ſay that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerning the outward cutting it was true circu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciſion: the like ye ſay of baptiſme adminiſtred in popery. Ref. pag. 64.</p>
            <p n="19">19 That in your Diſc. from pag. 16. to pag. 45. and Refut.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:19449:53"/>
pag. 97. ye take vpon ye to confute almoſt all which M Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiue hath written againſt the Donatiſts &amp; Annabaptiſts, hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding that the prayers and Sacraments, &amp; the conſciences of all that communicate together are defiled, where any open ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners are admitted.</p>
            <p n="20">20 That ye deny the diſtinction of the external court, &amp; the court of conſcience: &amp; ſo take away the power of the ciuil ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, &amp; the power of the Church in making lawes, in things indifferent, taking vpon ye to confute M. Cal. Diſc. pa 94. 95.</p>
            <p n="21">21 That ye condemne Logick, Rethorike and other liberal Artes. Refut. pag 117.</p>
            <p n="22">22 That ye would haue al authors (the bible only excepted) caſt aſide in the ſtudy of diuinitie. Diſc. pag. 146.</p>
            <p n="23">23 That ye wickedly blaſpheme the operatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; motions of Gods ſpirit in the harts of men at the preaching of the goſpel, as if they were but the illuſions of the diuel. Diſco. pa. 141. 156</p>
            <p n="24">24 That ye ſpeake ſo reprochfully of all the moſt excellent learned diuines which God hath rayſed vp in al Churches, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning them of pride, ignorance, raſhnes, ſenſualitie, &amp;c. Diſco. from pag. 140. vnto pag. 191.</p>
            <p n="25">25 That ye ſtill ſtand to maintaine, that priuate men may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble and erect a Church with all the offices &amp; officers. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fut. pag. 191.</p>
            <p n="26">26 That ye affirme there bee no true miniſters any where to be found vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> earth, nor yet any extraordinary miniſters to be looked for, &amp; therfore meere priuate men are (as ye ſay) to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect and eſtabliſh the Church Refut pag. 196.</p>
            <p n="27">27 That ye affirme theſe priuate men are not to ſtay for the Prince Refut. pag. 196.</p>
            <p n="28">28 That ye maintaine that no fault is to be tolerated in the church: but if any priuate man do eſpie a fault and reproue it, if they will not amend it he is to forſake that church. This is your whole practiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I will not ſtand to lay open euery particular but vpon theſe conclude, that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ye hold ſo many foule errors, and with ſuch outrage in your dealing, God hath not ſent ye, nor ſet ye a work, more then he ſent the Donatiſts and Anna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptiſts, but Satan hath ſeduced ye, &amp; ye labor to ſeduce others. And if it pleaſe God I beſeech him for his ſonns ſake to open your eyes, and to giue ye ſome ſpark of wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orepent. Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:19449:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
